<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;इतिहासः on ज्योतिषे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/astrophysics/history/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;इतिहासः on ज्योतिषे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/astrophysics/history/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Akṣara the Basic Unit of Time</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/astrophysics/history/akShara-time/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/astrophysics/history/akShara-time/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Akṣara the Basic Unit of Time Measure in Ancient India&lt;br&gt;&#xA;R. N. Iyengara∗, H. S. Sudarshan, Anand Viswanathan&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Distinguished Professor, and Research Associates,&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Centre for Ancient History and Culture, Jain University, Bangalore.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;(Received 15 August 2020)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In this paper after a brief review of ancient Indian time units, the ingenious method of Indian astronomers for calibrating the small time unit of vighaṭikā (24 seconds) phonetically by the recitation of a Sanskrit verse in the līlākhelā meter with sixty gurvakṣaras, is experimentally verified by sixty independent sample recitations. This is followed by exploring the concept of congruence of akṣara count and time periods such as the month and the year in Vedic texts. This leads to the symbolic equivalence of the bṛhatī meter of 36 syllables to the Year and several other numerical synchronies between phenomenal time and akṣara. The 1000 bṛhatī verses of the prātaranuvāka nocturnal performance in the atirātra ritual is the traceable most ancient origin and inspiration for gauging and estimating lapse of time by recognizing audible syllable as a time measure. To verify this, apart from text based theoretical estimates, real time information from a famous śrauta expert on his prātaranuvāka performance is presented. It is further demonstrated empirically that the rate of 3600 gurvakṣara per ghaṭikā of siddhānta astronomy is closely correlated with the speed of present day traditional chanting of the Ṛgveda, the fidelity of which has remained stable over millennia.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Asterisms</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/astrophysics/history/asterisms/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/astrophysics/history/asterisms/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;intro&#34;&gt;Intro&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;For general records of asterisms and their myths, see &lt;a href=&#34;../../naxatram/tArAmaNDala/&#34;&gt;tArAmaNDala page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;naxatra-history&#34;&gt;naxatra history&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Summary via &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2010/02/18/the-oldest-surviving-planetary-ritual-of-the-hindus/&#34;&gt;MT&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;There was a nakShatra list predating the Indo-Iranian divergence.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol start=&#34;2&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Both in the core RV and Avesta period there was no dedicated ritual to the nakShatra-s. However, they were collectively or by specific names referred to within recitations in this period.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol start=&#34;3&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;In the beginnings of the elaborate shrauta ritual of the agni chiti-s they were incorporated into the ritual of laying of pebbles.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol start=&#34;4&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;In the core YV/later AV period full-fledged rituals dedicated to the deities in conjunction with their associated nakShatra-s emerged.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol start=&#34;5&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;In parallel, the Iranians developed later liturgy for specific asterisms (perhaps as euphemisms for the deities associated with them, because the deities themselves were demonized by zarathuShTra). We see these developments as internal to the Indo-Iranian world. At least in the Indo-Aryan world the development was largely a consequence of the increasing calenderical emphasis in the shrauta ritual.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;observations&#34;&gt;Observations&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;vaidika naxatreShTi rituals.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Astrology</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/astrophysics/history/astrology/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/astrophysics/history/astrology/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;There was definitely a pre-yavana Indian astrology. It was just of a different nature from the jAtaka and hora astrology of yavana origin. The old astrology is found in the aushanasa adbhutAni and nakShatra parishiShTha-s of Atharvan tradition.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;No planets are involved but it works mostly as omenology: e.g. when a planet goes close to rohiNI alpha Tauri they said the following could happen: lakes drying, rivers changing course, suffering to animals including humans, the saMrAT dying.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;In a more cryptic account a disease, lasting 20 nights said to arise during planetary conjunctions.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;A planet going close to the kR^ittikAH (Pleiades) is said bring death to goats, sheep and rats.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gravity-like forces</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/astrophysics/history/gravity/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/astrophysics/history/gravity/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;rgveda&#34;&gt;Rgveda&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Via S kAk: r̥gveda 10.136.2 speaks of the stars of the Ursa Major (the Seven Sages) having ropes of wind. (munayo vāta raśanāḥ).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Via S kAk: ŚB 4.1.5.16 describes the sun as puṣkaramādityo, “the lotus of the sky”. ŚB 8.7.3.10 says :  tudasāvāditya imūmlokūnt sūtre samāvayate, tad yat tat sūtram vāyuh &amp;hellip;. The sun strings these worlds (the earth, the planets, the atmosphere] to himself on a thread. This thread is the same as the wind &amp;hellip;..&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;suryasiddhanta&#34;&gt;sUryasiddhAnta&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Via S kAk: Surya Siddhānta (SS) seems to remember this pre-epicyclic astronomy of the earlier period. The uccas and the node (pāta) are thus described in SS 2.1-5: &amp;ldquo;Forms of time, of invisible shape, stationed in the zodaic, called the sīghrocca, mandocca, and node (pāta), are causes of the motion of the planets. The planets, attached to these points by cords of air, are drawn away by them, with the right and left hand, forward or backward, according to nearness, toward their own place. A wind, called pravaha, impels them toward their own ucсas, being drawn away forward and backward.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Heliocentrism, spherical earth …</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/astrophysics/history/heliocentrism_spherical_flat_earth/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/astrophysics/history/heliocentrism_spherical_flat_earth/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;references&#34;&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Many of the uncited quotes and translations are by the mAnasatarangiNIkAra.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;aitreya-brāhmaṇa-27-1kbce-or-older&#34;&gt;Aitreya Brāhmaṇa 2.7 1kBCE or older&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;The (sun) never really sets or rises. In that they think of him “He is setting&amp;rdquo;, having reached the end of the day, he inverts himself; thus he makes evening below, day above. Again in that they think of him “He is rising in the morning”, having reached the end of the night he inverts himself; thus he makes day below, night above. He never sets; indeed he never sets.&amp;quot;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Subhash kAk on this passage: &amp;ldquo;One way to visualize it is to see the universe as the hollow of a sphere so that the inversion of the sun now shines the light on the world above ours. But this is impossible since the sun does move across the sky during the day and if the sun doesn&amp;rsquo;t set or rise it doesn&amp;rsquo;t move either. Clearly, the idea of “inversion&amp;rdquo; denotes nothing but a movement of the earth.&amp;quot;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;shatapatha-brahmana-1k-bce&#34;&gt;shatapatha-brAhmaNa 1k BCE&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;ŚB 4.1.5.16 describes the sun as puṣkaramādityo, “the lotus of the sky”. ŚB 8.7.3.10 says :  - tudasāvāditya imāmlokānt sūtre samāvayate, tad yat tat sūtram vāyuh &amp;hellip;.&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The sun strings these worlds (the earth, the planets, the atmosphere] to himself on a thread. This thread is the same as the wind &amp;hellip;..&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;This suggests a &lt;strong&gt;central role to the sun&lt;/strong&gt; in defining the motions of the planets and ideas such as these must have ultimately led to the theory of the śīghrocca and the mandocca cycles.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;suryasiddhanta&#34;&gt;sUryasiddhAnta&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Earth is said to be a stationary globe around which sun, moon and five planets orbit, with sun (via śīghrocca position) playing a major role in propelling the outer planets.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;It calculates the earth&amp;rsquo;s diameter to be 8,000 miles (modern: 7,928 miles), diameter of moon as 2,400 miles (actual ~2,160) and the distance between moon and earth to be 258,000 miles (actual ~238,000).&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Thus everywhere on [the surface of] the terrestrial globe, people suppose their own place higher [than that of others], yet this globe is in space where there is no above nor below.&amp;rdquo; —Surya Siddhanta, XII.53&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Via S kAk: Surya Siddhānta (SS) seems to remember this pre-epicyclic astronomy of the earlier period. The uccas and the node (pāta) are thus described in SS 2.1-5: &amp;ldquo;Forms of time, of invisible shape, stationed in the zodaic, called the sīghrocca, mandocca, and node (pāta), are causes of the motion of the planets. The planets, attached to these points by cords of air, are drawn away by them, with the right and left hand, forward or backward, according to nearness, toward their own place. A wind, called pravaha, impels them toward their own ucсas, being drawn away forward and backward.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;aryabhata-500-ad&#34;&gt;Aryabhata 500 AD&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Aryabhata (born in 476 AD. ) appears to have held the view that the &lt;strong&gt;stars did not revolve round the earth, but the latter revolved round itself&lt;/strong&gt; and gave the illustration of a man sitting in a moving boat feeling that it is the stationary objects on the banks that rush past in the opposite direction. &amp;hellip; This was more than eleven hundred years before Galileo and there is nothing to show that Aryabhata suffered in the least for his views.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Moon</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/astrophysics/history/moon/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/astrophysics/history/moon/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Moon gets its light from the Sun.&amp;rdquo;&lt;br&gt;&#xA;From a 6th-7th century CE commentator of Ṛgveda (1.84.15), Skandasvāmin, who further quotes 7th-5th century BCE Vedic etymologist Yāska.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/vishvAsa-prastutiH/01/084/15_atrAha_goramanvata.md&#34;  newLevelForH1=&#34;5&#34; includeTitle=&#34;false&#34;&gt; &lt;/div&gt;  &#xA;&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/01/084/15_atrAha_goramanvata.md&#34;  newLevelForH1=&#34;5&#34; includeTitle=&#34;false&#34;&gt; &lt;/div&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Trepidation</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/astrophysics/history/Trepidation/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/astrophysics/history/Trepidation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;(The below includes extracts from: wikipedia.)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Trepidation (from Lat. trepidus, &amp;ldquo;trepidatious&amp;rdquo;), in now-obsolete medieval theories of astronomy, refers to hypothetical oscillation in the precession of the equinoxes. The theory was popular from the 9th to the 16th centuries. Trepidation was the mainstay of Hindu astronomy and was used to compute ayanamsha for converting sidereal to tropical longitudes.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;in-suryasiddhanta&#34;&gt;In Suryasiddhanta&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The third chapter of the Suryasiddhanta, verses 9-10, provides the method for computing it, which E. Burgess interprets as 27 degree trepidation in either direction over a full period of 7200 years, at an annual rate of 54 seconds. This is nearly the same as the Arab period of about 7000 years.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Universes</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/astrophysics/history/universes/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/astrophysics/history/universes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;parallel-universes&#34;&gt;Parallel universes&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Source: [Nyāyakusumañjali.2.287]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;a pūrvapakṣa made by a Yogin who said there can be different universes with humans living in them with knowledge of religion and they can travel through space &amp;amp; time to reach our world to instruct us&amp;hellip;+ Udayana rejects this view on the grounds that it is extremley difficult to travel from one continent to another, even harder to travel from one planet to another. So how can you propose travel between two different universes? How hard would this be? Impossible nearly. एतेन ब्रह्माण्डान्तरसञ्चारिवर्णव्यवस्थया सम्प्रदायप्रवर्तनमपास्तम्- सञ्चारशक्तेरभावात् वर्षान्तरसञ्चरणमेव हि दुष्करम् कुतो लोकान्तरसञ्चारः? कुतस्तरां च ब्रह्माण्डान्तरगमनम्?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ज्योतिर्मीमांसा</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/astrophysics/history/jyotir-mImAMsA/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/astrophysics/history/jyotir-mImAMsA/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;परचय&#34;&gt;परिचयः&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;ज्योतिर्-मीमांसा निलकण्ठसोमयाजिकृता। तत उद्धरणानि। pdf &lt;a href=&#34;https://archive.org/details/jyotirjyotismimamsaofnilakanthainvestigationsintoastronomicaltheoriessarmak.v.vishveshvaranand_958_P/page/n41/mode/2up&#34;&gt;अत्र&lt;/a&gt; ।&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;पठ&#34;&gt;पाठः&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;पञ्चसिद्धन्तास् तावत् क्वचित् काले प्रमाणम् एव +इत्य् अवगन्तव्यम् । अपि च यः सिद्धान्तः दर्शनाऽविसंवादी भवति सोऽन्वेषणीयः+++(5)+++ । दर्शन-संवादश् च तदानीन्-तनैः परीक्षकैः ग्रहणादौ विज्ञातव्यः ।&#xA;…&#xA;गणितोन्नीतस्य चन्द्रादेः देश-विशेषान्वयस्य प्रत्यक्षेण संवादः , ततो निश्चितान्वयस्य परस्य गणितलिङ्गोपदेशः , ततस् तस्याप्तोपदेशावगतान्वयस्य +अनुमानं संवादः , परस्मै चोपदेशः इति सम्प्रदायाऽविच्छेदात् प्रामाण्यम् ।&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;…&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;ननु &amp;ldquo;तपोभिᳶ प्रसन्नो ब्रह्मा आर्यभटाय भ-गण-परिध्य्-आदिकं ग्रह-गणन-साधन-भूतं संख्या-विशेषम् उपदिदेश । तद् उपदिष्टं पुनर् आर्यभटः सर्वं यथोपदिष्टम् एव दशभिर् गीतिभिः निबबन्ध&amp;rdquo; इति केचिन्मन्यन्ते । तस्य कुतः परीक्षणम् ब्रह्मणः सर्वज्ञत्वात् राग-द्वेषाद्य्-अभावाच् च अ-वितथत्व-निश्चयात् इति चेत्+++(5)+++ -&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
