<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;MT on ज्योतिषे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/astrophysics/articles/MT/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;MT on ज्योतिषे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 20 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/astrophysics/articles/MT/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Some ruminations on</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/astrophysics/articles/MT/2023-02-20_some-ruminations-on-asteroids-and-meteoritic-falls/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/astrophysics/articles/MT/2023-02-20_some-ruminations-on-asteroids-and-meteoritic-falls/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2023/02/20/some-ruminations-on-asteroids-and-meteoritic-falls/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Some ruminations on asteroids and meteoritic falls&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Recently, we received the news of a Russian spacecraft meant to bring some astronauts back to earth being hit by a meteorite. In early February we saw an obscure news item of the sighting of a meteoric fireball over Krasnoyarsk. This brought to mind the several spectacular meteoritic falls in Russia. There was the dramatic Tunguska event that occurred on June 30, 1908, in a remote part of Siberia. While no one was killed by the fall, it is said that people standing over 60 km from the site of the hit were felled by the shock waves it unleashed. Modern estimates say the Tunguska explosion might have been equivalent to 10 million tons (10 mT) of trinitrotoluene — effectively close to one of the biggest nuclear bombs that was in active American service during the Cold War according to declassified files from 2014 (B53). Thus, such an asteroid falling on a city would obliterate it.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The quest for faint objects</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/astrophysics/articles/MT/2005-10-02_the-quest-for-faint-objects/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Oct 2005 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/astrophysics/articles/MT/2005-10-02_the-quest-for-faint-objects/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2005/10/02/the-quest-for-faint-objects/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In the great expedition of last night the following unusually faint objects were captured: A galaxy and a planetary nebula.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;NGC242 in Cetus. The Nebula occurs just below a group of stars termed the Phi1 and Phi2 Ceti forming a near equilateral triangle with them. The object is a very faint shroud that appears to envelop a group of stars around int in nebulosity. Discovered by Wilhelm Herschel.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ne.jp/asahi/stellar/scenes/object_e/ic342.htm&#34;&gt;http://www.ne.jp/asahi/stellar/scenes/object_e/ic342.htm&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;IC342 in Cameleopardus is a low brightness galaxy of the Mafei group. Though it is very close to the Milky Way (about 8.2*10^6 light years), it is not at all easy to sight. A group of faint stars from the Milky way that surround it help one to distinguish the nebulosity.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ne.jp/asahi/stellar/scenes/object_e/ngc246.htm&#34;&gt;http://www.ne.jp/asahi/stellar/scenes/object_e/ngc246.htm&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Planetary nebula hunt</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/astrophysics/articles/MT/2005-09-06_the-planetary-nebula-hunt/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Sep 2005 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/astrophysics/articles/MT/2005-09-06_the-planetary-nebula-hunt/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2005/09/06/the-planetary-nebula-hunt/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A great hunt for the planetary nebulae was successfully conducted this night. After an initial survey of bright globulars we pursued the planetary nebulae with a vengence.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1) NGC 6210 in Hercules: Small faint disk. About 6500 light years away. Discovered by Wilhelm Struve, successor of Herschel in 1827. Hubble has revealed it to contain two shells of gas.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;http://antwrp.gsfc.nasa.gov/apod/ap981028.html&#34;&gt;http://antwrp.gsfc.nasa.gov/apod/ap981028.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2) NGC 6543 in Draco: Medium bright disk. Discovered by Wilhelm Herschel in 1786 is very close to the ecliptic north pole. Also known as the Cat’s eye nebula.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;http://hubblesite.org/newscenter/newsdesk/archive/releases/1995/01/&#34;&gt;http://hubblesite.org/newscenter/newsdesk/archive/releases/1995/01/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
