<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;परमेश्वरः on ज्योतिषे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/prakIrNam/parameshvaraH/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;परमेश्वरः on ज्योतिषे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/prakIrNam/parameshvaraH/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>गोलदीपिका</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/prakIrNam/parameshvaraH/goladIpikA/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/prakIrNam/parameshvaraH/goladIpikA/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[गोलदीपिका&#x9;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ebharatisampat.in/readbook3.php?bookid=MDk3Njc3ODE0MTA3NDc0&amp;amp;pageno=MjI0MjQyNjk5NTk=&#34;&gt;EB&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;[&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;[TABLE]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;[TABLE]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;[TABLE]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PREFACE&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The edition of the Goladîpikâis based on three plamleafmanuscripts in Malayalam charectersobtained from the Raja ofIdappalli.The manuscript markedक in the foot notes, contains fower mistakes than the other two manuscrits Through the work has neither commentary nor illustrationsn it is published in the hope that it might be of some use to students of Hindu Astronomy.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Theauthor of this work is Parameshwara. He says in the 69th sloka of this work that he has written acommentry called Siddântadîpikâ on the Mahabhâskariya Bhashya. In his Bhâshya on Âryabhatiya, Nîlakanthu observes**&amp;ldquo;अश्वत्थग्रामजो भार्गव परमेश्वर सिद्धान्तदीपिकया&lt;br&gt;&#xA;प्राह&amp;rdquo;&lt;strong&gt;। i e,&amp;ldquo;Parameshwara of the Bhargava Gotra&amp;rdquo;, born on the Asvatthagrâma is the same as the present &amp;ldquo;Âlattur&amp;rdquo; m kerala country. Agan the words&lt;/strong&gt;अत्रनीलातटे** in the line&lt;strong&gt;गोकर्ण ग्रहणं भानोनोत्र दृष्ट नीलातटे&lt;/strong&gt; iquoted by Nilakantha as taken from the siddantadipîkâ ofparameshwara, make it evident that Parameshwara must have also been an number of some place on the banks of the Nilâ Nilakantha observes in another place in his Bhâshya that Parameshwara was written n word calledदृग्गणित from which he (Nilakantha) quotes the following verse,&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
