<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;MT on ज्योतिषे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/naxatram/chAndra-naxatram/meta/articles/MT/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;MT on ज्योतिषे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 01 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/naxatram/chAndra-naxatram/meta/articles/MT/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>A note on the asterisms forming the nakṣatra-s</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/naxatram/chAndra-naxatram/meta/articles/MT/2017-07-01_a-note-on-the-asterisms-forming-the-nake1b9a3atra-s/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/naxatram/chAndra-naxatram/meta/articles/MT/2017-07-01_a-note-on-the-asterisms-forming-the-nake1b9a3atra-s/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2017/07/01/a-note-on-the-asterisms-forming-the-nak%e1%b9%a3atra-s/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In Hindu tradition the ecliptic is divided into 27 parts of&#xA;&lt;figure class=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &lt;a href=&#34;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=13%5Ctfrac%7B1%7D%7B3%7D%5Eo&amp;amp;bg=ffffff&amp;amp;fg=333333&amp;amp;s=0&amp;amp;c=20201002&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&#xA;        &lt;img src=&#34;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=13%5Ctfrac%7B1%7D%7B3%7D%5Eo&amp;amp;bg=ffffff&amp;amp;fg=333333&amp;amp;s=0&amp;amp;c=20201002&#34; alt=&#34;13\tfrac{1}{3}^o&#34; title=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &#xA;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&#xA;which correspond to 27 asterisms known as the nakṣatra-s. In the earliest extant layers of our tradition this number is 28 implying division into sectors of&#xA;&lt;figure class=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &lt;a href=&#34;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=12%5Ctfrac%7B6%7D%7B7%7D%5Eo&amp;amp;bg=ffffff&amp;amp;fg=333333&amp;amp;s=0&amp;amp;c=20201002&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&#xA;        &lt;img src=&#34;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=12%5Ctfrac%7B6%7D%7B7%7D%5Eo&amp;amp;bg=ffffff&amp;amp;fg=333333&amp;amp;s=0&amp;amp;c=20201002&#34; alt=&#34;12\tfrac{6}{7}^o&#34; title=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &#xA;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&#xA;or insertion of a nakṣatra with adjacent compressed sectors. The earliest complete nakṣatra lists are found in the Taittirīya-śruti and the Atharvaveda where they are recited as part of the nakṣatreṣṭi ritual which places the deities of pantheon in these celestial compartments. Indeed, ever since it has been common practice in Hindu astronomy to use the names of the deities corresponding to a given compartment alternatively for the nakṣatra itself. The old nakṣatra-lists in the TS, Laugākṣi’s sūtra-s and the Atharvaveda begin with Kṛttikā i.e., the Pleiades, suggesting that the system as described in these texts was put in place sometime in the interval of 4500-4000 years before present. However, we hold that the nakṣatra system did not begin with these texts. These texts are mostly predated by the ṛgveda, where we find stray references to specific nakṣatra-s and also the term itself in its generic sense. Thus, we believe a form of the system was already in place even in the days of the ṛgveda. Further, there are some homologies between nakṣatra-s and Iranian asterisms suggesting that some form of the system might have existed even in the Indo-Iranian past on the Eurasian steppes.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>nakShatra homa as per the kAThaka yajurvedins</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/naxatram/chAndra-naxatram/meta/articles/MT/2007-12-07_nakshatra-homa-as-per-the-kathaka-yajurvedins/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Dec 2007 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/naxatram/chAndra-naxatram/meta/articles/MT/2007-12-07_nakshatra-homa-as-per-the-kathaka-yajurvedins/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2007/12/07/nakshatra-homa-as-per-the-kathaka-yajurvedins/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The nakShatra homa as performed by the taittirIyaka-s utilizes the famed nakShatra-sUktaM and the elaborate mantra prescriptions from from the taittirIya brAhmaNa (3.1). The kaTha-s have a very different tradition of nakShatra homa. With the denudation and extinction of the kaTha tradition this appears to have been lost, but we can reconstruct it in large part due to the commentary of the kaTha ritualist devapAla. devapAla was in the line of great kaTha yajurvedins from like: 1) gauradhara the R^ig/yajur dvivedI from Kashmir who composed a now lost, but supposedly notable, commentary on the kAThaka saMhitA known as veda-vilAsa. 2) lakShmIdeva, a noted performer of shrauta rituals and 3) Adityadarsha. devapAla appears to have been one of those last great brahmin scholars who was intimately acquainted with the rituals of the kaTha tradition and he describes the denudation of brahminical tradition around him. While by all accounts he was smArta, in terms of tantric and laukIka disposition he was inclined towards the Kashimirian lineage of pA~ncharAtra mantra-shAstra and even composed a great stava on viShNu. In terms of philosophical affiliations he belonged to the yoga school and composed a scholarly commentary on the sUtra-s of pata~Njali. At the same time his work clearly shows that he was a master of the mImAMsa school. He was born in Jalandhar, Panjab, to a vedic scholar haripAla son of bhaTTa upendra. He wrote his great work on the laugAkShi kalpa sUtra-s in jayapura near Shrinagar, Kashmir.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The crossing of ashmanvatI</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/naxatram/chAndra-naxatram/meta/articles/MT/2006-11-26_the-crossing-of-ashmanvati/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Nov 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/naxatram/chAndra-naxatram/meta/articles/MT/2006-11-26_the-crossing-of-ashmanvati/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2006/11/26/the-crossing-of-ashmanvati/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://photos1.blogger.com/x/blogger2/6438/855/1600/606089/ashmanvatI.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;figure class=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &lt;a href=&#34;https://i2.wp.com/photos1.blogger.com/x/blogger2/6438/855/320/606078/ashmanvatI.jpg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&#xA;        &lt;img src=&#34;https://i2.wp.com/photos1.blogger.com/x/blogger2/6438/855/320/606078/ashmanvatI.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &#xA;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In the days of our earliest memories we were transfixed by the sight of that part of the sky which has inspired and continued to inspire all discerning beholders. We drew that little cluster, the mothers of our god, and the three stars in a line, which form the arrow of The god. All this got imprinted in our minds. Over the ages the language of myth has preserved the passage of time through this region of the sky and beyond. Tilak first and de Santillana and von Dechend thereafter (the latter two are possibly plagiarists of Tilak, who failed to cite him appropriately) realized some of the underlying celestial secrets. We continue this journey of exploration through this part of the heavens.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>rohiNI shakaTa bheda</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/naxatram/chAndra-naxatram/meta/articles/MT/2006-09-04_rohini-shakata-bheda/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Sep 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/naxatram/chAndra-naxatram/meta/articles/MT/2006-09-04_rohini-shakata-bheda/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2006/09/04/rohini-shakata-bheda/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2003/08/17/rohinis-cart/&#34;&gt;rohiNI shakaTa&lt;/a&gt; bheda is a peculiar conjunction mentioned repeatedly in Hindu astronomy. It is technically defined in the sUrya-siddhAnta (8.13) thus:&lt;br&gt;&#xA;vR^iShe saptadashe bhAge yasya yAmyo .aMshakadvayAt |&lt;br&gt;&#xA;vikShepo .abhyadhiko bhindyAd rohiNyAH shakaTaM tu saH ||&lt;br&gt;&#xA;In the constellation of vR^iSha (Taurus), at 17th degree, a planet of which the latitude is a little more than 2 degrees, south, will split the cart of rohiNI.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In his bR^ihat saMhitA, varAhamihira mentions that the planets that are considered for this conjunction are arka-nandana (the son of the sun, the inauspicious shanaishchara- Saturn), rudhira (the red Mars) or shikhI (a tufted one or a comet). varahamihira himself cites the Atharvavedic astronomer vR^iddha garga (author of the atharvanic nakShatra hymns, although I was unable to locate a direct reference to the event in the surviving sUkta-s and nivid-s of garga from the atharvan saMhitA as well as nakShatra kalpa) as the authority who described this type of conjunction. The shakaTabheda is believed by the Hindus to be a harbinger of immense destruction or the flooding of the world by the ocean. The medieval Maharatta astronomer gaNesha daivaj~na correctly noted that the shakaTabheda by the Moon was relatively common but that by Saturn or Mars was not possible in the current yuga and might possibly occur/ed in some very distant yuga.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The nakshatra kalpa of the Atharva veda</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/naxatram/chAndra-naxatram/meta/articles/MT/2005-11-27_the-nakshatra-kalpa-of-the-atharva-veda/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Nov 2005 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/naxatram/chAndra-naxatram/meta/articles/MT/2005-11-27_the-nakshatra-kalpa-of-the-atharva-veda/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2005/11/27/the-nakshatra-kalpa-of-the-atharva-veda/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The nakshatra kalpa of the Atharva veda that is considered the first parishishhTa of the AV adduces a R^ishi in addition to the tutelary deity to each nakshatra. These connections appears to have emerged much later than the devata-nakshtra connection, but may be of interest to investigate what these R^ishis meant. The list is:&lt;br&gt;&#xA;asterism |seer |god&lt;br&gt;&#xA;kR^ittika |agnivesha |agni&lt;br&gt;&#xA;rohini |anurohI |prajapati&lt;br&gt;&#xA;mR^igshiras |shvetAyI |soma and maruts&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Ardra |bhArgava |rudra&lt;br&gt;&#xA;punarvasu |vAtsyAyana |aditI&lt;br&gt;&#xA;pushya |bharadvAja |bR^ihaspati&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Alshlesha |jatukarNa |ahi&lt;br&gt;&#xA;magha |vyAghrapada |pitarah&lt;br&gt;&#xA;purva-phalguni |parAshra |bhaga&lt;br&gt;&#xA;uttara-phalguni |upashiva | aryama&lt;br&gt;&#xA;hasta |mAnDvaya | savitA&lt;br&gt;&#xA;chitra |gotama | tvashTa&lt;br&gt;&#xA;svati |kauNdiNya | vAyu&lt;br&gt;&#xA;vishAkhA |kapi | indrAgni&lt;br&gt;&#xA;anurAdhA |maitreya | mitra&lt;br&gt;&#xA;jyeshTha |kaushika | indra&lt;br&gt;&#xA;mUla |kutsa | NirR^iti&lt;br&gt;&#xA;purva-ashADhA |harita | ApaH&lt;br&gt;&#xA;uttara-ashADhA |kashyapa | vishvedevAH&lt;br&gt;&#xA;abhijit |shaunaka | brahmA&lt;br&gt;&#xA;shroNa |atri | vishhNu&lt;br&gt;&#xA;shravishTha |garga | vasavaH&lt;br&gt;&#xA;shatabhishak |dakshAyaNa | indrAvarunA&lt;br&gt;&#xA;pUrva-proshThapadA |vatsa | aja-ekapAda&lt;br&gt;&#xA;uttara-proshThapadA |agastya | ahirbudhnya&lt;br&gt;&#xA;revatI |shA~nkyAyana | pUshA&lt;br&gt;&#xA;ashvayuja |kAtyAyana | ashvinau&lt;br&gt;&#xA;bharanI |R^ishi-patnya| yama&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Comet Machholz 2004</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/naxatram/chAndra-naxatram/meta/articles/MT/2004-12-16_comet-machholz-2004/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Dec 2004 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/naxatram/chAndra-naxatram/meta/articles/MT/2004-12-16_comet-machholz-2004/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2004/12/16/comet-machholz-2004/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Comet Machholz 2004 &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.hello.com/&#34;&gt;&lt;figure class=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &lt;a href=&#34;https://i0.wp.com/photos1.blogger.com/pbh.gif&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&#xA;        &lt;img src=&#34;https://i0.wp.com/photos1.blogger.com/pbh.gif&#34; alt=&#34;Posted by Hello&#34; title=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &#xA;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://photos1.blogger.com/img/133/1300/640/machholz2004.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;figure class=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &lt;a href=&#34;https://i2.wp.com/photos1.blogger.com/img/133/1300/400/machholz2004.jpg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&#xA;        &lt;img src=&#34;https://i2.wp.com/photos1.blogger.com/img/133/1300/400/machholz2004.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &#xA;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We finally saw comet Machholz 2004 today with my 20X75 binoculars. It shone as fuzz ball in the southern sky, in the constellation of Eridanus (The southern river; the celestial yamunA of the Hindus which leads to the path of death). It was a little above the level of Sirius, the head of shabala praised at the morning shuna shairya offering of the pa~nchavimsha brAhmaNa. I estimate its magnitude as around 4.5 and was able to perceive a slight tail with the binoculars. It is supposed to rise higher beyond Orion. I uttered the incantation of the dogs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>rohiNi’s cart</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/naxatram/chAndra-naxatram/meta/articles/MT/2003-08-17_rohinis-cart/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Aug 2003 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/naxatram/chAndra-naxatram/meta/articles/MT/2003-08-17_rohinis-cart/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2003/08/17/rohinis-cart/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In Greco-Roman star lore the constellation Auriga is the charioteer. Traditionally, in India too the constellation is refered to as the sArathi, which means the same thing. The mainstream Western scholarship has believed that this is a recent acquisition of the constellation name from the Greco-Roman world.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;If Auriga is the charioteer, where is his car? India star-lore records an unsual name for the Hyades cluster in constellation of Taurus: rohINi shakaTa: The cart of roHiNi (alpha Tauri) [sUrya siddhAnta, 8.13]. Not surprisingly, the constellation is also called the shakaTa of prajApati or brahmA [ pa~ncha siddhAnta 238-241]. Traditionally, Hindu astronomy records the star Capella (alpha-Aurigae) as brahma-hR^idaya(the heart of brahmA).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mongol naxatra names</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/naxatram/chAndra-naxatram/meta/articles/MT/mongol-naxatra-names/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/naxatram/chAndra-naxatram/meta/articles/MT/mongol-naxatra-names/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One puzzle is whether the Mongols put together their nakShatra list from Uighur list or independently from the sUryagarbhasUtra, which the tAthAgata-s in their characteristic plagiaristic way claimed was taught by the sugata. e.g.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;kR^ittikA -&amp;gt; Uig: Kirdik; Mon: Kerteg&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;but rohiNI-&amp;gt; Uig: urughuNi; Mon: rokini;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;vishAkhA -&amp;gt; Uig: vishak; Mon shushagh. The Mongol transformation for vishAkhA is odd.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Others are quite similar &amp;amp; regularly derived from the H list. Notably, 1 the Indian transmission to the chIna-s begins with chitrA but Uighur &amp;amp; Mongol list begin with kR^ittikA.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ज्योतिष्-चक्रम्</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/naxatram/chAndra-naxatram/meta/articles/MT/jyotiSh-chakram/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/naxatram/chAndra-naxatram/meta/articles/MT/jyotiSh-chakram/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;ज्योतिश्-चक्रं ध्रुव-कर-गतं वात-रश्मि-प्रणद्धं&lt;br&gt;&#xA;&lt;strong&gt;छित्वा&lt;/strong&gt; बालः प्रथित-महिमा स्वानुगानां कराग्रैः ।&lt;br&gt;&#xA;दिक्ष्व् अष्टासु स्वयम् अपि &lt;strong&gt;दधन् धारयन्&lt;/strong&gt; व्योम-गङ्गां&lt;br&gt;&#xA;नक्रान् &lt;strong&gt;बध्वा व्यसृजद्&lt;/strong&gt; अभि-सं-भाव्य-पाथः पुनस् तान् ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;पश्चाद् ऊर्ध्वं महर् अपि जनस् तत् तपः सत्य-लोकं&lt;br&gt;&#xA;&lt;strong&gt;गत्वा गत्वा&lt;/strong&gt; तद् अधि वसतीन् विश्व-साध्यामरेन्द्रान् ।&lt;br&gt;&#xA;लीला-लोलो नव च &lt;strong&gt;कलयन्&lt;/strong&gt; वेधसो भीम-भूतान्&lt;br&gt;&#xA;लोकालोकं गिरिम् अपि मुदा प्राप चिक्रीड बालः ॥&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>मञ्जुश्रीय-मूलकल्प-नक्षत्राणि</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/naxatram/chAndra-naxatram/meta/articles/MT/manjushrIya-mUlakalpa-naxatras/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/naxatram/chAndra-naxatram/meta/articles/MT/manjushrIya-mUlakalpa-naxatras/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The unfortunately lacunose part of the ma&lt;del&gt;njushrIya mUlakalpa provides a division of the sky into 56 constellations that seems to have been one followed by the saugata-s. I am yet to see it in a H source. ShaT-pa&lt;/del&gt;nchAshad rAshayaH tadyathA -&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;meSha 2. vR^iShabha 3. mithuna 4. karkaTaka 5. siMha 6. kanya 7. tula 8. vR^ishchika 9. dhanu 10. makara 11. kumbha 12. mIna;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;vAnara 14. upakumbha 15. bhR^i&lt;del&gt;njAra 16. khaDga 17.ku&lt;/del&gt;njara 18. mahiSha 19. deva 20. manuShya 21. shakuna 22. gandharva 23. lokasatvajita&lt;br&gt;&#xA;24.ugrateja 25. jyotsna 26. ChAya 27. pR^ithivI 28. tama 29. raja 30. uparaja 31. duHkha 32. sukha 33. mokSha 34. bodhi 35. pratyeka 36. shrAvaka 37. naraka 38. vidyAdhara 39. mahoja 40. mahojaska 41. tiryakpreta 42. asurapishita 43. pishAcha 44. yakSha 45. rAkShasa&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;sarvabhUmita 47. bhUtika 48. nimnaga 49. Urdhvaga 50. tiryaga 51. vikasita 52. dhyAnaga 53. yogapratiShTha 54. uttama 55. madhyama 56. adhamash cheti |&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;If only we could put these on the sky.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
