<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;02 General Principles of Calendar Making on ज्योतिषे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar/02_General_Principles/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;02 General Principles of Calendar Making on ज्योतिषे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar/02_General_Principles/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 INTRODUCTION</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar/02_General_Principles/01_INTRODUCTION/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar/02_General_Principles/01_INTRODUCTION/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;time-indicators&#34;&gt;Time indicators&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Flux of Time, of which we are all conscious, is apparently without beginning or end, but it is cut up periodically by several natural phenomena, viz. :&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(1) by the ever-recurring alternation of daylight and night,&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(2) by the recurrence of the moon&amp;rsquo;s phases,&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(3) by the recurrence of seasons.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It is these recurring phenomena which are used to measure time.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;These phenomena have the greatest importance for man, for they determine all human and animal life. Even prehistoric men could not help. noticing these time-periods, and their effect on life.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>02 Natural periods of time</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar/02_General_Principles/02_Natural_periods_of_time/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar/02_General_Principles/02_Natural_periods_of_time/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The three events mentioned in (1), (2) and (3) above define the natural divisions of time. They are :&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Day: defined by the alternation of daylight and night.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Month : the complete cycle of moon&amp;rsquo;s changes of phase, from end of mew-moon to next end of new moon (amānta months), or end of full-moon to end of next full-moon (Pūrṇimānta months).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Year : and its smaller subdivisions, viz., the seasons.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>03 THE PROBLEMS OF THE CALENDAR</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar/02_General_Principles/03_THE_PROBLEMS_OF_THE_CALENDAR/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar/02_General_Principles/03_THE_PROBLEMS_OF_THE_CALENDAR/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Whatever may be the correct lengths of the astronomical month and the year, for application to human life, the following points have to be observed in framing a civil calendar.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(a) The civil year and the month must have an integral number of days.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(b) The starting day of the year, and of the month should be suitably defined. The dates must correspond strictly to seasons.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(c) For purposes of continuous dating, an era should be used, and it should be properly defined.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(d) The civil day, as distinguished from the astronomical day, should be defined for use in the calendar.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(e) If the lunar months have to be kept, there should be convenient devices for luni-solar adjustment.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A correct and satisfactory solution of these problems has not yet been obtained, though in the form of hundreds of calendars which have been used by different people of the world during historical times, we have so many attempted solutions. The early calendars were based on insufficient knowledge of the duration of the natural time cycles-day, month and year-and led to gross deviations from actual facts, which had to be rectified from time to time by the intervention of dictators like Julius Caesar, Pope Gregory XIII, or a founder of religion like Mohammed, or by great monarchs like Melik Shah the Seljuk, or Akber, the great Indian emperor.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>04 SUBDIVISIONS OF THE DAY</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar/02_General_Principles/04_SUBDIVISIONS_OF_THE_DAY/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar/02_General_Principles/04_SUBDIVISIONS_OF_THE_DAY/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;For pactical purposes, the day is divided into 24 hours, an hour into sixty, minutes and a minute into sixty seconds.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;time-keeping-devices&#34;&gt;Time keeping devices&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1 mean solar day=24 x 60 x 60 = 86,400 seconds. The subdivisions of time are measured by highly  developed mechanical contrivances (clocks, watches and chronometers), but they have come into use only during comparatively recent times. The ancient people used very primitive devices.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The time-keeping apparatus of the ancients were the &lt;strong&gt;gnomon, the sundial, and the water-clock&lt;/strong&gt; or the clepsydra. The first two depend on the motion of the sun, and require correction. The water-clock which probably was first invented in Egypt, appears to have been used down to the time of Galileo, when the discovery of &lt;strong&gt;pendulum motion&lt;/strong&gt; led to the invention of clocks based on pendulum motion or use of the balance wheel.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>05 Foreview</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar/02_General_Principles/05_Foreview/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar/02_General_Principles/05_Foreview/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;solar-calendars&#34;&gt;Solar calendars&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In the following sections, the different ways of tackling the calendar problem in different centres of civilization have been described. We have described in Chap. II, the &lt;strong&gt;purely solar calendars&lt;/strong&gt;, in which the moon is altogether discarded as a time-marker. This practice originated in Egypt about 3000 B.C. These calendars require only a correct knowledge of the length of year, and are therefore comparatively simpler. They required very little or &lt;strong&gt;almost no knowledge of astronomy&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>06 Ahargaṇa OR HEAP OF DAYS : JULIAN DAYS</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar/02_General_Principles/06_Ahargaa_OR_HEAP_OF_DAYS_JULIAN_DAYS/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar/02_General_Principles/06_Ahargaa_OR_HEAP_OF_DAYS_JULIAN_DAYS/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;ambiguity-in-calendar-dates&#34;&gt;Ambiguity in calendar dates&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Though the Flux of Time is a continuous process, it is divided for the sake of convenience and for natural reasons too, into years, months and days. The years are mostly counted from the beginning of an era, so that if we wish to date a memorable event, say the birth day of George Washington, it can be seen from an inspection of his birth register that it took place on Feb.11, of the year 1732. But this practice by itself does not enable a scientific chronologist to fix up the event unambiguously on the absolute Scale of Time, unless the whole history of the particular method of date-recording is completely and accurately known. One must know the lengths of the individual months, the leap-year rules, and the history of calendar reform. In the particular case mentioned, though George Washington. according to his birth register is stated to have been &lt;strong&gt;born on Feb. 11, 1732, his birth-day is celebrated on Feb. 22&lt;/strong&gt;. Why? Because Feb. 11 was the date according to the Julian calendar. But in 1752, England (America was then a colony of England) adopted the reformed Gregorian calendar, and by an Act of Parliament, declared Sept. 3 to be Sept.14, a difference of 11. days. Following the Gregorian calendar, Washington&amp;rsquo;s birth-day had to be shifted to Feb. 22. A scientific chronologist, say of China, would find it &lt;strong&gt;difficult to locate Washington&amp;rsquo;s birth-day unless he knew the whole history of the Gregorian calendar&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
