<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;01 Introductory on ज्योतिषे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/calendar_reform_comittee_report/02_PART-A/01_Introductory/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;01 Introductory on ज्योतिषे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/calendar_reform_comittee_report/02_PART-A/01_Introductory/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 Calendars in use</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/calendar_reform_comittee_report/02_PART-A/01_Introductory/01_Calendars_in_use/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/calendar_reform_comittee_report/02_PART-A/01_Introductory/01_Calendars_in_use/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;For official purposes, India has been using the Gregorian calendar since the imposition of the British rule in 1757. As the Gregorian calendar, on account of historic reasons, has attained the status of a World Calendar, it is still being used for official purposes after the attainment of Independence. There is a proposal sponsored by India before the UNO for the intro duction of a new World Calendar for civil and administrative purposes in place of the Gregorian calendar, which is inconvenient and unscientific (vide C §2.7).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>02 Hindu religions: unified calendar</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/calendar_reform_comittee_report/02_PART-A/01_Introductory/02_Hindu_religions_unified_calendar/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/calendar_reform_comittee_report/02_PART-A/01_Introductory/02_Hindu_religions_unified_calendar/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;These practices often produce a bewildering confusion in fixing up dates and moments of observance of the religious festivals, of which some detailed examples are given later. The Calendar Reform Committee was asked to make a study of the various Hindu religious calendars, and recommend to the Government a Unified National Calendar for Hindu religious purposes for the whole of India. The Committee has now finished its labours, and presents its report to the Government. The main points are summarized below:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>03 LENGTHS OF THE SOLAR MONTHS :</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/calendar_reform_comittee_report/02_PART-A/01_Introductory/03_LENGTHS_OF_THE_SOLAR_MONTHS/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/calendar_reform_comittee_report/02_PART-A/01_Introductory/03_LENGTHS_OF_THE_SOLAR_MONTHS/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Hindu solar month-lengths vary from 29 to 32, as the time of passing 30° of the ecliptic varies, accord ing to older data given in the Sūrya Siddhānta from 29.32 days to 31.64 days. These varying lengths, as is well-known, can be understood only from Kepler&amp;rsquo;s first two laws, which were explained fully by Newton in 1687 on the basis of dynamics and law of universal gravitation, but these laws and their explanation were unknown to astronomers in 400 A.D. Further these month-lengths are different in the three Siddhāntas be cause they were calculated according to three different formulæ. On account of the ignorance of Kepler&amp;rsquo;s laws. and of the shift of the equinoctial lines in the Earth&amp;rsquo;s orbit ( vide C § 5:6) the ancient astronomers probably assumed that the times of passage through 30° as calculated according to formulæ given by them would be valid for all times. But we now know this assumption to be incorrect, and cannot stick to the lengths as given in the Siddhāntas, which also differ amongst themselves.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>04 THE LUNAR CALENDAR :</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/calendar_reform_comittee_report/02_PART-A/01_Introductory/04_THE_LUNAR_CALENDAR/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/calendar_reform_comittee_report/02_PART-A/01_Introductory/04_THE_LUNAR_CALENDAR/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The lunar calendar depends on the correct calculation of the moments of conjunction (Amāvasyā), opposition (Paurnamāsi) and of the tithis (i.e., the moments when the moon gains 12° or its integral multiple on the sun). The Indian calendar-makers use for this purpose the formulæ on lunar motion given in the three Siddhāntas. But as these are known to be inaccurate, they use certain corrections called bīja introduced by later Indian astronomers.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>05 Effect of Indian Lunar Calendars</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/calendar_reform_comittee_report/02_PART-A/01_Introductory/05_Effect_of_Indian_Lunar_Calendars/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/calendar_reform_comittee_report/02_PART-A/01_Introductory/05_Effect_of_Indian_Lunar_Calendars/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As the orthodox Indian calendar-maker still uses the old formulæ dating from 400 A.D., his calculations of the ending moments of tithis do not agree with those given by the Nautical Almanacs, which are based on modern formulæ and are verified by actual observations as shown in the following example:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(Original pdf here contains a list of discrepencies in tithi boundaries)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Some of the Indian calendar-makers are aware of these discrepancies, and give the ending moments of tithis according to the Nautical Almanac. But all of them give the moments of beginning and ending of lunar and solar eclipses according to the Nautical Almanac, as times calculated according to the Siddhāntas may be grossly inaccurate, and the mistakes would at once catch public attention and lower their prestige. In the words of one of our colleagues (Dr. Gorakh Prasad), these almanac-makers are like bicycle-riders riding without lamps, who get down from their cycles on street corners, just to avoid being caught by the Police.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
