<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;मानम् on ज्योतिषे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/mAnam/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;मानम् on ज्योतिषे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/mAnam/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Coordinates</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/mAnam/coordinates/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/mAnam/coordinates/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Terms &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.physics.csbsju.edu/astro/terms.html&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;ecliptic&#34;&gt;Ecliptic&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;figure class=&#34;thumbnail&#34;&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &lt;a href=&#34;../ecliptic_coordinates.png&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&#xA;        &lt;img src=&#34;../ecliptic_coordinates.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &#xA;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&lt;figure class=&#34;thumbnail&#34;&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &lt;a href=&#34;../images/equatorial-coordsystem-with-ecliptic.png&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&#xA;        &lt;img src=&#34;../images/equatorial-coordsystem-with-ecliptic.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &#xA;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Sun is always at 0 deg latitude. It&amp;rsquo;s longitude (determinable using background stars) is 0 deg (=0 RA) during march vernal equinox, 90 deg (= 6h RA) during summer solstice, 270 (= 18h RA) during winter solstice etc..&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Latitudes are parallel to each other, longitudes pass through the same two poles.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The 0 deg and 180 deg longitude together form the equinoctial colure.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;equatorial&#34;&gt;Equatorial&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;figure class=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &lt;a href=&#34;../images/celestial-equator.jpg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&#xA;        &lt;img src=&#34;../images/celestial-equator.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &#xA;    &lt;figcaption&gt;&#xA;        Celestial equator and pole star&#xA;        &#xA;    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&#xA;    &#xA;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;apparent-solar-motion&#34;&gt;Apparent solar motion&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Angle between the ecliptic and the celestial equator (they meet at equinoctial points) is around 23 deg.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Among celestial equatorial system logitudes: equinoctial and solstical colures.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;At poles, celestial equator = horizon. No seasonally visible stars = all stars visible at long winter night.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;At equator, celestial pole is at horizon.  Celestial equator is directly overhead.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;During equinox day, sun appears to travel along the celestial equator.  Looking from the poles, sun will be at the horizon then. From the equator, sun will be along the circle passing straight overhead.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Sun appears to go along other celestial lattitudes during other days. During northern solstice day, it will appear to travel along ~23 deg north celestial lattitude.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;measurement&#34;&gt;Measurement&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Equatorial Right ascension (RA)/ declination (dec) relative to spring/ vernal equinox point and celestial poles : &lt;a href=&#34;https://lco.global/spacebook/equatorial-coordinate-system/&#34;&gt;intro&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The advantage of the equatorial coordinate system is that it expresses the position of a star or galaxy in a way that is independent of the observer&amp;rsquo;s position on Earth.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Finding and using the celestial equatorial (and diurnal) planes- &lt;a href=&#34;https://agnimaan.wordpress.com/2018/02/09/solar-plane-of-the-day/&#34;&gt;KV18&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;असय-परचन-परयग&#34;&gt;अस्य प्राचीनः प्रयोगः&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;shukla-yajurvedasya shatapathabrAhmaNe: &amp;ldquo;एता ह वै प्राच्यै दिशो न च्यवन्ते | सर्वाणि ह वा अन्यानि नक्षत्राणि प्राच्यै दिशश्च्यवन्ते तत्प्राच्यामेवास्यैतद्दिश्याहितौ भवतस्तस्मात्कृत्तिकास्वादधीत&amp;rdquo;। Proper East. 90deg from north. Possible only if the star is on the celestial equator. Then the star will rise exactly at east. Krttikas on celestial equator around 2900BCE (two centuries before and after can be considered as acceptable)। [&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/agnimaan/status/984433779967082496&#34;&gt;TW&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;ecliptic-with-equatorial-projection&#34;&gt;Ecliptic with equatorial projection&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Aka &amp;ldquo;Polar longitude&amp;rdquo; (ecliptic longitude, but projection on meridian lines) in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.astro.com/swisseph/swisseph.htm#_Toc19109057&#34;&gt;astro.com&lt;/a&gt;. Certain ayanAMsha-s are defined based on this system.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;ayanamsha-offset-ecliptic-coordinates&#34;&gt;ayanAMsha-offset ecliptic coordinates&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;See &lt;a href=&#34;../../naxatram/&#34;&gt;chAndra-naxatram page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Diurnal plane and apps</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/mAnam/diurnal_plane/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/mAnam/diurnal_plane/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;motivation&#34;&gt;Motivation&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;There was a long discussion about the following brAhmaNa of the taittirIyakas- तैत्तिरीयब्राह्मणे &lt;a href=&#34;../../kalpe_svamatam/brAhmaNam/taittirIyam/kriyA/puNya-naxatra/&#34;&gt;ऽत्र&lt;/a&gt;।.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The classical commentators (as well as modern shrauta and smArta ritualists familiar with ancient and modern astronomy I checked with) clearly require measurement of the time required by the sun to &amp;ldquo;reach&amp;rdquo; a certain point &amp;ldquo;behind&amp;rdquo; the position of a desired naxatra at sunrise. Of course, this means reaching a certain point on the sun’s daily path, [let’s say that it lies in something called the Diurnal circle (defined below)], which is comparable (say in altitude or proximity) to the point where the nakShatra was last seen.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Eras</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/mAnam/eras/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/mAnam/eras/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Saka (National), Sayana Solar, year 1 = 78 AD, 1942 year begins 21 Mar. 2020&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Saka (shAlivAhana), Nirayana Lunar (Chaitra Sukla Pratipad), 1942 year begins 25 Mar. 2020&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Saka (Traditional), Nirayana Solar (Meshadi, True Sun), 1942 year begins 14 Apr. 2020&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Kali / national nirayaNa, Nirayana Solar (Meshadi, True Sun), 5121 year begins 14 Apr. 2020&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Buddha Nirvana, Nirayana Luni-solar (Buddha Purnima), 2564 year begins 07 May 2020&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Mahavira Nirvana, Nirayana Luni-solar (Kartikadi), 2547 year begins 16 Nov. 2020&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Vikram Samvat (chaitrAdi), 2077 begins 25 Mar. 2020&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Vikram Samvat (kArtikAdi),  2077 begins 16 Nov. 2020&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Bengali San, Nirayana Solar (Meshadi) Bengal, 1427 begins 14 Apr. 2020&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Hejira, Lunar, 1442 begins 21 Aug. 2020&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Kollam / malayALam, Nirayana Solar (Simhadi), 1196 begins 17 Aug. 2020&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Tipu assumed that Muhammad was born in 572 A.D. His ‘Maulud-i-Muhammad’ calendar started then.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;kali-start&#34;&gt;kali start&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;The current Kaliyuga began on Friday 18, 3102 BC at Sunrise at Lanka (a hypothetical place on the equator where the meridian of Ujjain intersects it, which synchronised with the beginning of the light half of Luna (synodic) month of Chaitra. &amp;hellip; The current Kalpa, according to Aryabhata I, started on Thursday 1,98,28,80,000 years or 7,24,26,41,32,500 days before the beginning of the current yuga; and 1,98,61,20,000 years or 7,25,447,570,625 days before the beginning of the current Kaliyuga.&amp;rdquo; -KS Shukla&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Not accounting for sunrise: &amp;ldquo;The Chaitra Shukla Pratipada on the Kali yuga -3101 (3102 BC) happened on 22nd January at 7:04:07 IST. The date is based on “Proleptic Gregorian Calendar” The Date as per Julian Calendar is February 17th.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;caveats&#34;&gt;Caveats&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;The follower of Surya Siddhanta Ayanamsa may note that, the conjunction of the luminaries happened on 20th February instead of 22nd January, which is different from the Conventional wisdom.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Closest great conjugation between Jupiter and Saturn happened on 3104-12-1.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;gregorian-and-julian-year-numbering&#34;&gt;Gregorian and julian year numbering&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The conventional BC/AD (or BCE/CE) scheme has no year 0 because at the time of it&amp;rsquo;s creation, Europeans were widely ignorant of the concept of the number zero, thus the year before 1 AD is 1 BC. This makes arithmetic awkward.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;astronomical-numbering&#34;&gt;Astronomical numbering&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Astronomers often use a different scheme, referring to AD dates as a positive integer, and re-designating 1 BC/BCE as the year 0. (Stellarium uses this.)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Astronomers use the Julian calendar for years before 1582.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Jovian year</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/mAnam/jovian_year/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/mAnam/jovian_year/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;jupter-saturn-conjunction&#34;&gt;Jupter Saturn conjunction&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A great conjunction is a conjunction of the planets Jupiter and Saturn (Κρόνος: Kronos). Kronos gives the measure of time to Jupiter. A Triple Conjunction is a conjunction of Jupiter and Saturn at or near their opposition to the Sun.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;periods&#34;&gt;Periods&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Every twenty years (19.859), Saturn and Jupiter will have a conjunction at about 123 degrees apart (approximately ninth from the previous conjunction).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Every 60 years (59.577) that conjunction will return to the same sign.&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;If a conjunction happened in Aries, in twenty years, the next will happen in Sagittarius, then Leo in twenty more years, and then back to Aries after 60 years from the original Aries conjunction.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;In this way, the conjunctions will move in the same rAshi trines creating a triangle in the zodiac. &amp;hellip; The cycle will stay in one rAshi trine for about 200 years, then it will enter the next rAshi triad. &amp;hellip;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The cycle will move through all the zodiac signs every 800 years (794.37 years or 40 conjunctions) returning to within .93° of the starting point if one uses a tropical calculation. (A given vertex will take ~800 years to reach the sign occupied by the next vertex, they being 4 rAshis apart.)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;figure class=&#34;thumbnail&#34;&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &lt;a href=&#34;../images/great_conjunction_triangles_1941.jpg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&#xA;        &lt;img src=&#34;../images/great_conjunction_triangles_1941.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &#xA;    &lt;figcaption&gt;&#xA;        Great conjunction triangles&#xA;        &#xA;    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&#xA;    &#xA;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;connection-to-yugas&#34;&gt;Connection to yugas&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;This 1° discrepancy creates a larger cycle in which the exact degree returns in 288,000 years (800 X 360). In Satya Yuga there are 6 of these cycles, in Tretā Yuga there are 4.5, in Dvāpara there are 3, and in Kali Yuga there are 1.5 which gives a total of 15 of the grand 288,000 year cycles in a Mahāyuga.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tipu&#39;s calendar</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/mAnam/Tipu/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/mAnam/Tipu/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;intro&#34;&gt;Intro&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;He used the maulUdI &lt;a href=&#34;../eras/&#34;&gt;era&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Basically a copy of the South Indian Luni-solar calendar with the following changes:&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;new names for months (2 sets, called abjad and abtah) and (12 of the) saMvatsaras&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;unique number for tithis from 1 to 30 or 29.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In 1921, J.R. Henderson who documented Tipu Sultan’s coinage across his realm was confronted with the problem of identifying the exact Mauludi dates on the coins and relating them to the Hijri and Christian Eras so as to ascertain periods of existence of the royal mints vis-a-vis Tipu’s possession of the territories that these mints were in. He requested the Hon’ble Diwan Bahadur L.D. Swamikannu Pillai, M.A., L.L.B., author of Indian Chronology (Madras, 1911) and a well known authority on the subject to examine these dates.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>पूर्वाह्णापराह्णभेदः</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/mAnam/pUrvAhNa_vs_aparAhNa/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/mAnam/pUrvAhNa_vs_aparAhNa/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;veda-s-and-sutra-s-speak-of-aprahna-in-two-contexts&#34;&gt;Veda-s and sUtra-s speak of aprAhNa in two contexts:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Two fold division of day&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;वसन्तो ग्रीष्मो वर्षा - ते देवा ऋतवः। शरद्+हेमन्तः शिशिरस् - ते पितरः। य एवापूर्यते ऽर्धमासः - स देवा, योऽपक्षीयते स पितरो, ऽहर् एव देवा, रात्रिः पितरः, पुनरह्नः पूर्वाह्णो देवा, अपराह्णः पितरः। &amp;hellip;&amp;hellip; स यत्र उदगावर्तते देवेषु तर्हि भवति। देवांस् तर्ह्य् अभिगोपायस्य्, अथ यत्र दक्षिणावर्तते पितृषु तर्हि भवति, पितॄंस् तर्हि गोपायति ।&amp;rdquo; śatapatha Brāhmaṇa (ii. 1. 3, 1-3)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;अन्यत्र श्रुतौ -  “पृर्वं दिनं मनुष्याणाम् अपराह्णः पितॄणाम्”, “पूर्वाह्णो वै देवानां मध्यन्दिनं मनुष्याणाम् अपराह्णः पितॄणाम्&amp;quot; इति।&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;“तथा श्राद्धस्य पूवाह्णाद् अपराह्णो विशिष्यते” इति मनुः । “ययास्तं सविता याति पितरस्तामुपासते । तिथिं तेभ्योऽपराह्णो हि स्वयं दत्तः स्वयंभुवेति” स्मृतिः ।&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;द्विधा विभक्तदिनस्य शेषभागः ॥ इति कल्पद्रुमः। &amp;ldquo;लौकिके तु मध्याह्नात्परतः, सूर्य्यास्तात् प्राक्कालोऽपराह्णत्वेन व्यवह्रियते।&amp;rdquo; इति वाचस्पत्यम्।&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;3 fold division of the day&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;प्रभातं च दिनान्ते तु सायं सन्ध्या पितृप्रसूः। प्राह्णापराह्णमध्याह्नास्त्रिसन्ध्यमथ शर्वरी॥ इत्यमरः।&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;त्रिधा विभक्तदिनस्य तृतीयभागः ॥ स तु त्रिंशद्दण्डदिनमाने विंशतिदण्डात् परं दशदण्डं यावत् ।&amp;rdquo; इति कल्पद्रुमः।&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;5 fold division of the day - &amp;ldquo;दे॒वस्य॑ सवि॒तुᳶ प्रा॒तᳶ प्र॑स॒वᳶ प्रा॒णः । &amp;hellip;.मि॒त्रस्य॑ सङ्ग॒वः । &amp;hellip; बृह॒स्पते॑र्म॒ध्यन्दि॑नः । &amp;hellip;  भग॑स्यापरा॒ह्णः ।&amp;rdquo;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;“प्रातःकालो महूर्त्तांस्त्रीन् सङ्गवस्तावदेव तु । मध्याह्नस्त्रिमुहूर्त्तः स्यादपराह्णस्ततः परम् ॥ सायाह्नस्त्रिमहूर्त्तः स्यात् श्राद्धं तत्र न कारयेत् । राक्षसी नाम सा वेला गर्हिता सर्व्वकर्म्मसु ॥” इति तिथ्यादितत्त्वधृतवचनम् ॥&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;पञ्चधा विभक्तदिनस्य चतुर्थभागः । स तु अष्टादशदण्डात् परं षड्दण्डं यावत् ।&amp;rdquo; इति कल्पद्रुमः।&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;proper-disambiguation&#34;&gt;Proper disambiguation&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;In the context of muhUrta-s, the 5 fold division is to be taken.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;In the context of pitRkArya-s (used in contrast with pUrvAhNa rather than sAngava etc.., and in juxtaposition with other two fold divisions like ayana, day-night etc.. ), the 2-fold division is to be taken.&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;But sAyAhNa should be omitted, (wrongly) leading to preference of the 5-fold division context: अन्तिमत्रिमुहूर्त्तस्य तु राक्षसवेलात्वेन कर्म्मानर्हत्वात् कर्म्मयोग्य- शेषभागत्वाभावान् नापराह्णत्वम् ।&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;mAdhvas of vyAsarAjamaTha reckon vyApti of the kutupa-muhUrta (8th from sunrise out of 15).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;At times the 5-fold division is assumed indiscriminately; whereas generally 2-fold division makes more sense (shrAddha, pitRkarma, sannyAsi-ArAdhanas etc..). This messes up vyApti decisions (besides making the logic complicated), besides giving ridiculous times for regions with very long/short  day lengths.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
