<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;RNI on ज्योतिषे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/hindu/articles/RNI/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;RNI on ज्योतिषे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/hindu/articles/RNI/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Equinoctial full-moon brahmANDa-purANa, summer solstice</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/hindu/articles/RNI/equinoctial-full-moon_brahmANDa-purANa_summer-solstice_maghA/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/hindu/articles/RNI/equinoctial-full-moon_brahmANDa-purANa_summer-solstice_maghA/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.academia.edu/109640034/Equinoctial_full_moon_of_the_Brahm%C4%81%E1%B9%87%E1%B8%8Da_Pur%C4%81%E1%B9%87a_and_the_nak%E1%B9%A3atra_solar_zodiac_starting_from_summer_solstice&#34;&gt;TW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Indian Journal of History of Science &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1007/s43539-023-00100-5&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1007/s43539-023-00100-5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;ARTICLE&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Equinoctial full moon of the Brahmāṇḍa Purāṇa and the nakṣatra solar zodiac starting from summer solstice R. N. Iyengar · Sunder Chakravarty Received: 26 June 2023 / Accepted: 22 September 2023 (RN.Iyengar AAA jainuniversity.ac.in)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Centre for Ancient History and Culture, Jain University, Bangalore 560078, India&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;© Indian National Science Academy 2023&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;0&#34;&gt;0&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The first theoretical system of tracking sun in the tropical annual cycle is cryptically mentioned in the Maitrāyaṇīya Āraṇyaka Upaniṣat (MAU) of the Kṛṣṇa Yajurveda, as the southern sojourn of sun starting at the summer solstice. This is called maghādyaṁ, the first point of the maghā nakṣatra, identified most likely with the early morning visibility of ε-Leo, near the azimuth of the sunrise point on the horizon as observed at Kurukshetra. Twenty seven equal nakṣatra sectors named in the traditional sequential order cover one tropical circuit of sun of 366 days with the winter solstice falling exactly at the middle of the śraviṣṭhā sector. Even though MAU mentions each nakṣatra to be made up of four quarters, no practical application of this ¼-nakṣatra sky part amounting to 3º20´ in longitude is seen in Vedic texts till we come to the Brahmāṇḍa Purāṇa, a text closer to the Vedas. This Purāṇa states, observed equinoctial full moon positions corresponding to spring equinox at ¼-kṛttikā and autumn equinox at ¾-viśākha exactly 180º apart as they should be. This statement is analysed in this paper by computer simulation of full moon time series for the years − 2400 to − 800 to show that the Purāṇa data would be realistically valid for the period 1980 BCE to 1610 BCE. It is further demonstrated that the Purāṇa has followed the maghādi system of solar nakṣatra system stated in the MAU. The central epoch circa 1800 BCE of this maghādi equal nakṣatra solar zodiac got modified, due to precession effects, to the śraviṣṭhādi scheme of Parāśara, Vṛddha Garga and Lagadha dateable to circa 1300 BCE.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>parAshara: solar zodiac and agastya</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/hindu/articles/RNI/parAshara_solar-zodiac_and_agastya/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/hindu/articles/RNI/parAshara_solar-zodiac_and_agastya/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;PARAŚARA’S SIX SEASON SOLAR ZODIAC AND HELIACAL VISIBILITY OF STAR AGASTYA IN 1350-1130 BC&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;R N IYENGAR&lt;br&gt;&#xA;+++(with comments by vishvAsa in this font.)+++&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The bright southern star Canopus is known as Agastya in India. The first rise of this star is observed with religious fervour in many parts of the country. Legends say that the Vedic sage Agastya crossed the Vindhya Mountains to go south and eventually remained as the southern star known by his name. This star would not have been clearly visible before 3100 BC in the northern parts of India. The star exhibits all the four visibility phenomena namely, heliacal rise, cosmic setting, acronychal rise and heliacal setting. Hence statements about its heliacal visibility and setting in the Parāśaratantra as quoted by Varāhamihira and his commentator are of seminal importance as anchor points of early Hindu astronomy and ancient Indian chronology. This paper analyses the visibility information given by Parāśara in relation to his six season solar zodiac preserved in Utpala’s commentary. It is demonstrated that the observations were realistic for 1350-1130 BC, which is also the estimated date of the ancient Indian astronomer Parāśara.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
