<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;04 The Luni-Solar and Lunar Calendars on ज्योतिषे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar/04_Luni-Solar_and_Lunar/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;04 The Luni-Solar and Lunar Calendars on ज्योतिषे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar/04_Luni-Solar_and_Lunar/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 PRINCIPLES OF LUNI-SOLAR CALENDARS</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar/04_Luni-Solar_and_Lunar/01_PRINCIPLES_OF_LUNI-SOLAR_CALENDARS/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar/04_Luni-Solar_and_Lunar/01_PRINCIPLES_OF_LUNI-SOLAR_CALENDARS/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Egyptians appear to have been the only cultural nation of antiquity who discarded the moon entirely as a time-marker. Other contemporaneous cultural nations, e.g. the Sumero-Akkadians of Babylon, and the Vedic Indians retained both the sun and the moon as time-markers, the &lt;strong&gt;sun for the year, the moon for the month&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Indian astronomers called the &lt;strong&gt;moon māsakrt&lt;/strong&gt;, (month-maker) and before the Siddhānta Jyotiṣa time, the moon was considered more important as a time marker than the sun (vide §5). It was the same with other nations too, for as Pannekoek remarks, we find the opinion written in the sacred books of many nations &amp;ldquo;For regulating time, the moon has been created&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>02 MOON&#39;S SYNOPIC PERIOD OR LUNATION :</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar/04_Luni-Solar_and_Lunar/02_MOONS_SYNOPIC_PERIOD_OR_LUNATION/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar/04_Luni-Solar_and_Lunar/02_MOONS_SYNOPIC_PERIOD_OR_LUNATION/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;EMPIRICAL RELATION BETWEEN THE YEAR AND THE MONTH&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The solar year has thus a pretty nearly constant value, but even the earliest astronomers appear to have observed, that the lunation, or the synodic period of the moon is not a constant, but is variable. As a matter of fact, the period varies from 29.246 to 29.817 days-nearly fourteen hours. The observation of the actual motion of the moon formed the most formidable problem in ancient astronomy (vide §4).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>03 BABYLONIANS, MACEDONIANS, ROMANS, AND JEWS</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar/04_Luni-Solar_and_Lunar/03_BABYLONIANS_MACEDONIANS_ROMANS_AND_JEWS/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar/04_Luni-Solar_and_Lunar/03_BABYLONIANS_MACEDONIANS_ROMANS_AND_JEWS/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In addition to the Chaldeans, many other nations of antiquity, viz..the Vedic Indians, the Greeks, the Romans and the Jews and others used the luni-solar calendar, and had to make luni-solar adjustments. It will be tedious to relate how they did it, except in the case of the Vedic Indians (vide § 5). But the knowledge of the nineteen-year rule appears to have diffused to all countries by the first century of the Christian era. From this time onwards, the lunar months of different nations appear to be interchange able. This is shown in the following Table No. 4.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>04 THE INTRODUCTION OF THE ERA</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar/04_Luni-Solar_and_Lunar/04_THE_INTRODUCTION_OF_THE_ERA/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar/04_Luni-Solar_and_Lunar/04_THE_INTRODUCTION_OF_THE_ERA/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;early-eras&#34;&gt;Early eras&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;For accurate date-recording, we require besides the month and the day, also a continuously running era. But the era came rather late in human history. We find dated records of kings in &lt;strong&gt;Babylon&lt;/strong&gt; from about 1700 B.C. (Kassite kings). They used &lt;strong&gt;regnal years&lt;/strong&gt;, lunar months, and the day of the lunar month. The &lt;strong&gt;ancient Egyptian&lt;/strong&gt; records do not use any era, but sometimes the &lt;strong&gt;regnal years&lt;/strong&gt;. But the use of regnal years is very inconvenient for purposes of exact chronology, because one has to locate the beginning of the reign of the king on the time-scale which often proves to be an extremely difficult problem, e.g., in India, Emperor &lt;strong&gt;Asoka used regnal years&lt;/strong&gt;, but it is a problem of nearly hundred years for archaeologists to find out the exact date of the commencement of his reign. This varies from 273 B.C. to 264 B.C.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>05 The Parthian Era</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar/04_Luni-Solar_and_Lunar/05_The_Parthian_Era/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar/04_Luni-Solar_and_Lunar/05_The_Parthian_Era/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Since the introduction of the Seleucidean era, the practice arose for a nation or a dynasty to start eras commemorating some great event in their national or dynastic life. The first in record is the Parthian era, and the story of its starting is well-known. The Seleucid emperors ruled the Near East from 312 B.C. imposing on the countries under their domination Greek culture, the Seleucidean era, and the Graeco Chaldean system of time-reckoning. About 250 B.C., there were wide-spread revolts against Seleucid rule in Bactria, in Parthia (Eastern Persia), and other parts of the Near East. The revolt in Parthia was led by one Arsaces and his brother Tiridates who belonged to an Iranian tribe, which had adopted Greek culture. To commemorate their liberation from Seleucidean rule, the Parthians introduced an era, beginning &lt;strong&gt;64 years after the Seleucid era (i.e. 248 B.C.)&lt;/strong&gt;. But at first this era (&lt;strong&gt;Arsacid era&lt;/strong&gt;) was only rarely used. The early Parthian emperors preferred to use on their coins the Seleucidean era, the Macedonian months, and the Graeco-Chaldean system of time reckoning inscribed in Greek letters. In the &lt;strong&gt;first century A.D.&lt;/strong&gt;, there was a &lt;strong&gt;Zoroastrian revival&lt;/strong&gt;, the S.E. was dropped in favour of the Parthian era and Pehlevi began to be used in place of Greek, though Macedonian month-names were still kept.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>06 THE JEWISH CALENDAR</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar/04_Luni-Solar_and_Lunar/06_THE_JEWISH_CALENDAR/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar/04_Luni-Solar_and_Lunar/06_THE_JEWISH_CALENDAR/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The ancient Jewish calendar was lunar, the beginning of the month being determined by the first visibility of the lunar crescent. As the month-names show (col. 4 of the table No. 4.), they were evidently derived from the &lt;strong&gt;Babylonian month-names&lt;/strong&gt; excepting one or two, viz., Marheshvan and Tammuz. The &lt;strong&gt;day began in the evening&lt;/strong&gt; and probably at sunset. The year used to begin with the &lt;strong&gt;spring month Abib or Nisan&lt;/strong&gt;, the latter being the Babylonian name of the month which was adopted by the Jews in the post-exilic times. &lt;strong&gt;Intercalation&lt;/strong&gt; was performed, when necessary, repeating the twelfth month &amp;lsquo;Adar&amp;rsquo; which was then known as Veadar followed by Adar. The year beginning was subsequently changed and in the last century before Christ, it became the month of Tishri, corresponding to the Macedonian month of Dios. This must have been due to the desire or need to follow the practice of the ruling race.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>07 THE ISLAMIC CALENDAR</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar/04_Luni-Solar_and_Lunar/07_THE_ISLAMIC_CALENDAR/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar/04_Luni-Solar_and_Lunar/07_THE_ISLAMIC_CALENDAR/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Mohammedan calendar is &lt;strong&gt;purely lunar&lt;/strong&gt; and has no connection with the solar year. The year consists of 12 lunar months, the beginning of each month being determined by the first observation of the crescent moon in the evening sky. The months have accordingly got 29 or 30 days and the &lt;strong&gt;year 354 or 355 days&lt;/strong&gt;. The &lt;strong&gt;new-year day&lt;/strong&gt; of the Mohammedan calendar thus retrogrades through the seasons and &lt;strong&gt;completes the cycle in a period of about 324 solar years&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
