<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;06 Indian Calendar on ज्योतिषे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar/06_Indian_Calendar/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;06 Indian Calendar on ज्योतिषे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar/06_Indian_Calendar/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 THE PERIODS IN INDIAN HISTORY</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar/06_Indian_Calendar/01_THE_PERIODS_IN_INDIAN_HISTORY/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar/06_Indian_Calendar/01_THE_PERIODS_IN_INDIAN_HISTORY/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The time-periods in Indian history necessary for our purpose are shown in the Chronological Table.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The earliest civilization so far discovered in India is the &lt;strong&gt;Harappa-Mohenjo-Daro&lt;/strong&gt; civilization (sometimes also called the Indus-Valley civilization) named after the two ancient buried cities of Harappa in the Punjab and Mohenjo-Daro in Sind. They were first brought to light by the late R.D. Banerjee, Superinten dent of the Western Circle of Archaeology of India in 1924. It has now been ascertained that this civilization extended right upto Rupar on the Sutlej in the east and to the Narmada valley in the south. This civilization was certainly contemporaneous with the Mesopotamian civilizations of about 2500 B.C., nearly 500 years before the city of Babylon had risen to supremacy amongst the cities of Sumer and Akkad ; and with the first dynastic civilization of Egypt. How far back it projected into the time-scale is not yet known, but certainly many thousand years back.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>02 CALENDAR IN THE RIG-VEDIC AGE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar/06_Indian_Calendar/02_CALENDAR_IN_THE_RIG-VEDIC_AGE/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar/06_Indian_Calendar/02_CALENDAR_IN_THE_RIG-VEDIC_AGE/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;( -1200 B.C.)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-vedic-literature&#34;&gt;The Vedic Literature&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The knowledge of the calendar in this age can be obtained only from the Vedic literature which consists however of different strata, greatly differing in age. According to the great orientalist Max Muller four periods each presupposing the preceding can be distinguished. They are :&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(a) The Chandas and Mantras composing the Samhitās or collections of hymns, prayers, incantations, benedictions, sacrificial formulas, and litanies comprising the four Vedas : The Rk, Sara, Yajus, and Atharva.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(b) The Brāhmaṇas which are prose texts containing theological matter, particularly observations on sacrifices and their mystical significances ; attached to the Brāhmaṇas, but reckoned also as independent works are the Aranyakas or Upaniṣads containing meditations of forest hermits and ascetics on God, the world, and mankind. These treatises are attached to each of the individual Vedas.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(c) The Sutras or Aphorisms, or Vedangas. Vedāngas&amp;rsquo;, lit. limbs of Vedas, are post-Vedic Sūtra or aphorism literature which grew as results of attempts to understand the Vedas in their various aspects, and sometimes to develop the ideas contained in the Vedas. According to the orthodox view, there are six Vedāngas as follows:&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(1) Śikṣā : or phonetics; texts explaining how the Vedic literature proper is to be pronounced, and memorized.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(2) Kalpa : or ritualistic literature, of which four types are known : Srauta Sutras dealing with sacrifices ; Grhya Sutras dealing with domestic duties of a householder ; Dharma Sūtras dealing with religious and social laws; Sūlva Sūtras dealing with the construction of sacrificial altars.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(3) Vyakarana or Grammar, e.g., Panini&amp;rsquo;s famous Aṣtādhyāyī, which once for all fixed up the Sanskrit language. The Aṣtādhyāyi is however the culmination of attempts by large number of older authors, whose works were rendered obsolete by Panini&amp;rsquo; masterpiece.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(4) Nirukta or Etymology: explanation of the Vedic words ascribed to one Yaska, who lived before Pānini.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(5) Chandas-Metrics ascribed to Pingala.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(6) Jyotiṣa-Astronomy: the Rg-Jyotiṣa is ascribed to one Lagadha, of whom nothing is known.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Only the sixth Vedanga or Jyotisa interests us, though there are occasional references to the calendar in all Sātra literatures.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>03 CALENDARIC REFERENCES IN THE YAJUR VEDIC LITERATURE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar/06_Indian_Calendar/03_CALENDARIC_REFERENCES_IN_THE_YAJUR_VEDIC_LITERATURE/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar/06_Indian_Calendar/03_CALENDARIC_REFERENCES_IN_THE_YAJUR_VEDIC_LITERATURE/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;role&#34;&gt;Role&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Atharva Veda consisting mostly of magic incantations also contain calendaric references, but we shall make only occasional use of them, as the text of this Veda has not probably come to us in unadulterated form, for the Atharva Veda was not regarded as holy as the Rg-Veda.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Of the two other Vedas, the Sama-Vedas contain no new matter than what is contained in the Rg-Veda. But there are copious calendaric reference in the Yajurveda for obvious reasons, which are clearly brought out in the following extracts from Winternitz&amp;rsquo;s introductry remarks to Yajurvedic studies (p. 158-159) :&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>04 THE Vedānga Jyōtiṣa CALENDAR</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar/06_Indian_Calendar/04_THE_VEDANGA_JYOTISHA_CALENDAR/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar/06_Indian_Calendar/04_THE_VEDANGA_JYOTISHA_CALENDAR/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;intro&#34;&gt;Intro&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The history of the Indian calendar from the end of the Yajurveda period to the beginning of the Siddhānta Jyotiṣa period is very imperfectly known though there are plenty of calendaric references in the Brāhmanās, Sūtras, and the epic Mahābhārata and various literature. On time-scale, it extends from an unknown antiquity, which is set by some at 1300 B.C. to 900 A.D.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;Vedānga Jyōtiṣa&lt;/strong&gt; is generally assigned to this period. It may be said to be a sort of collection of short aphorisms giving mathematical rules for fixing the calendar in advance, and is known in three versions : the Rg-Jyotiṣa consisting of 36 verses, attached to the Rg-Veda and ascribed to one Lagadha as mentioned earlier, the Yājuṣ Jyotiṣa attached to the Yajurveda and consisting of 43 verses, and there is a text ascribed to one Somakara, a commentator of unknown age of the Vedas. The dffferent texts contain about the same matter, but the verses are haphazardly arranged showing that the original texts have not come down to us in an unadulterated form. The number of independent verses in all the versions is not more than 49, and some of the verses have not been interpreted.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>05 INSCRIPTIONAL RECORDS ABOUT CALENDAR</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar/06_Indian_Calendar/05_INSCRIPTIONAL_RECORDS_ABOUT_CALENDAR/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar/06_Indian_Calendar/05_INSCRIPTIONAL_RECORDS_ABOUT_CALENDAR/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;intro&#34;&gt;Intro&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In this chapter, we are undertaking a critical review of the references to the calendar in ancient inscriptions, because, from the point of view of accurate history, inscriptional records are far more valuable than any references in ancient scriptures or classics, as they are contemporary documents, which have remained unaltered since the framers left them.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;* Sometimes inscriptions and copper plate records have been found to have been forged at a latter date but such instances are rare and can not escape detection by an experienced archaeologist.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>06 SOLAR CALENDAR IN THE SiddhAnta JYOTISHA PERIOD</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar/06_Indian_Calendar/06_SOLAR_CALENDAR_IN_THE_SiddhAnta_JYOTISHA_PERIOD/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar/06_Indian_Calendar/06_SOLAR_CALENDAR_IN_THE_SiddhAnta_JYOTISHA_PERIOD/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[Jumbled 2 column text needs to be fixed]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Rise of Siddhāntas or Scientific Astronomy:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Vedānga Jyotiṣa calendarical rules appear, from inscriptional records, to have been used right up to the end of the reign of the śātavāhanas (200 A.D.). The analysis of inscriptional data on methods of date recording given in § 5.5 shows that it was the śaka and Kuṣāṇa rulers (50 B.C. - 100 A.D.), who introduced the Graeco-Chaldean methods of date-recording, prevalent in&amp;rsquo; the Near East into India. These methods require a knowledge of the fundamentals of astronomy, which must have been available to the śaka and Kuṣāna rulers. In India, as &amp;rsquo;the inscriptional records show, some purely Indian dynasts probably accepted the system in full from about 248 A.D. (date of foundation of the Kalachuri era, the earliest era founded by Indian kings, leaving aside the śaka era which is admittedly of foreign origin and the Vikrama era whose origin is still - shrouded in mystery). During the time of the Guptas who founded an era commemorating their accession to power in 319 A.D. the integration of the western system with the Indian appears to have been complete.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>07 THE LUNAR CALENDAR IN THE SiddhAnta JYOTISHA PERIOD</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar/06_Indian_Calendar/07_THE_LUNAR_CALENDAR_IN_THE_SiddhAnta_JYOTISHA_PERIOD/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar/06_Indian_Calendar/07_THE_LUNAR_CALENDAR_IN_THE_SiddhAnta_JYOTISHA_PERIOD/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[Jumbled 2 column text needs to be fixed]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Justification of the Solar Calendar as proposed&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;by the Committee It has been shown that the intention of the maker of Sarya Siddhānta and of other Siddhāntas was to start the year from the moment of sun&amp;rsquo;s crossing the vernal equinoctial point and to start the civil year from the day following. The Committee has also adopted this view and proposed that the civil year for all-India use should start from the day following the V. E. day, i.e., from March 22. In the Vedic literature also it is found that the starting of the year was related with one or other of the cardinal days of the year. The Vedānga Jyōtiṣa started the year from the winter solstice day, the Brāhmaṇas started the year from the Indian spring (Vasanta) when the tropical (Sayana) longitude of the sun amounted to 330°, but in the Siddhāntic period the year-beginning coincided with the V. E. day. So in adopting the Sāyana system in our calendar calculations, the Indian tradition, from the Vedic times up to the Siddhāntic times, has been very faithfully observed. This has ensured that the Indian seasons would occupy permanent places in the calendar. .&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>08 INDIAN ERAS</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar/06_Indian_Calendar/08_INDIAN_ERAS/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar/06_Indian_Calendar/08_INDIAN_ERAS/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Whenever we wish to define a date precisely we have to mention the year, generally current of an era, besides the month and the particular day of the month, and the week-day. This enables an astronomer, well-versed in technical chronology, to place the event! correctly on the time-scale. In international practice the Christian era is used, which is supposed to have started from the birth-year of Jesus Christ. But as mentioned in Chapter II, it is an extrapolated era which came in use five hundred years after the birth of the Founder of Christianity, and its day of starting may be widely different from the actual birthday of Christ, about which there exists no precise knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>09 AP 5A The Seasons</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar/06_Indian_Calendar/09_AP_5A_The_Seasons/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar/06_Indian_Calendar/09_AP_5A_The_Seasons/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[Jumbled 2 column text needs to be fixed]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We have seasons because the celestial equator is oblique The amount of daylight received at any place determines to the sun&amp;rsquo;s path (or the ecliptic), or in modern parlanoo, the season. When we have maximum sunlight, we have the axis of rotation of the earth is not perpendioular to its the bot season. When we have minimum sunlight, we shall orbit, but inclined at an angle of 661. This causes varying have winter. The other seasons come in-between. Bain, amounts of sunlight to fall on a particular locality through frost, etc., are secondary effects produced by varying out the year. If the earth&amp;rsquo;s axis were perpendicular to the amounts of sunlight, and of the atmospherio conditions ecliptic, in other words the obliquity were zero, overy stimulated by the sunlight received. The sun is the sole portion of the earth from the equator to the pole would Srbiter of the seasons. have had 12 hours of sunlight, and- 12 hours of shade. Hence the definitions of seasons as given by the ancient There would have been no seasons on any part of the earth, astronomers, whether Western and Indian, which base them just as we have now for places on the earth&amp;rsquo;s equator, whore on the cardinal days of the year, are the only correct, we have no variation of geason throughout the year, because definitions. A system which deviates from this practice is the day and night are equal for all days of the year.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>10 AP 5-B Zero-point of the Hindu Zodiac</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar/06_Indian_Calendar/10_AP_5-B_Zero-point_of_the_Hindu_Zodiac/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar/06_Indian_Calendar/10_AP_5-B_Zero-point_of_the_Hindu_Zodiac/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[Jumbled 2 column text needs to be fixed]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Zero-point of the Hindu Zodiac&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;i By this is meant have been given taking the position of the. V.E. point at the the Vernal Equinoctial Point (first point of Aries) at the Observer&amp;rsquo;s time as the fiducial point. It is : possible to time when the Hindu savants swibobed on from the old locate it, 48 Burgess had shown in his edition of the 8.8., if Vedāriga-Jyōtiṣa calondar to the Siddhānitio calendar (let with the aid of the data given, d; i.o., celestial longitude of us call this the spoch of the Siddhānta-Jyōtiṣa or S. J.). the junction-stars in the epoch of S.J. is calculated, and There is a wide spread belief that a definite location can be compare it with the i of the same stars for 1950: - Let the found for this point from the data given in the Sūry&amp;amp; two values of Å be denoted by lz and dg, die being the value Siddhārta and other standard trbatiges. This impression is at the spoch of S. J., dg for the year 1950. Thenigde however wrong&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>11 APPENDIX 5-C Gnomon Measurements in Aitareya Brahmana</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar/06_Indian_Calendar/11_APPENDIX_5-C_Gnomon_Measurements_in_Aitareya_Brahmana/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar/06_Indian_Calendar/11_APPENDIX_5-C_Gnomon_Measurements_in_Aitareya_Brahmana/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[Jumbled 2 column text needs to be fixed]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;References to the observation of the solstice are found The Vedic year-long sacrifices were begun in the earliest in vory early litorature as the following passage from the times on the day following the winter solstice. Honoo the Aitareja Brāhmaṇa shows?:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Viṣuvān which means the middle day of the year was the *They perform the Ekaviméa day, the Viṣuvān, in the&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;summer solstice day. The above passage shows that the middle of the year : by this Ekavimba day the gods raised&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>12 AP 5-D Precession of the Equinoxes amongst Indian Astronomers</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar/06_Indian_Calendar/12_AP_5-D_Precession_of_the_Equinoxes_amongst_Indian_Astronomers/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar/06_Indian_Calendar/12_AP_5-D_Precession_of_the_Equinoxes_amongst_Indian_Astronomers/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[Jumbled 2 column text needs to be fixed]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;On p. 226, we have given references to pre-Siddhāntio The surmise that the early Siddhāntic astronomers were notices of the location of the vernal point in the sky. We ignorant of the movement of the equinoxes is supported by saw that ancient Indian savants noticed its gradual shift the fact that neither of the early eminent astronomers ( due to procession ), but were only puzzled by the pheno&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>13 APPENDIX 5-E The Jovian Years</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar/06_Indian_Calendar/13_APPENDIX_5-E_The_Jovian_Years/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar/06_Indian_Calendar/13_APPENDIX_5-E_The_Jovian_Years/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[Jumbled 2 column text needs to be fixed]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(Bārhaspatya Varṣa)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The sidereal period of Jupiter, according to the surya Siddhānta is 4332.32 days which is nearly 11.86 sidereal years. Therefore Jupiter roughly stays for one year in one zodiacal sign, if we calculate by mean motion.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This was taken advantage of to devise &amp;amp; cycle of 12 Jovian years. If we divide the Sūrya Siddhānta period by 12, we get 361.026721 days which is takon as the length of &amp;amp; Jovian year. This is 4.232 days less than the Sūrya Siddhānta solar year. So if &amp;amp; Jovian year and an ordinary solar year begin on the same day, the Jovian year will begin to fall back, completing a complete retrogression in 8501solar years, according to the Sūrya-Siddhānta.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>14 CORRIGENDA AND ADDENDA</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar/06_Indian_Calendar/14_CORRIGENDA_AND_ADDENDA/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar/06_Indian_Calendar/14_CORRIGENDA_AND_ADDENDA/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[Jumbled 2 column text needs to be fixed]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Part A Page 2, 1st ool, line 36, For O § 4&#39;10, read 0 8 4&#39;9 Page 3, 2nd col. line 46, For happend, read happened Page 4, 1st col. line 12, For was, read were Page 21, 2nd col. No. 35, Insert Ceylon after Chavakachcheri&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Part B śaka 1877 Page 56, Aṣāḍha 9—For Ravinārāyaṇa ekādasi, read&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Lakṣminārāyaṇa ekādasi Page 57, Śrāvana 1-Insert Jāgratgauri pañcami.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>15 BIBLIOGRAPHY</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar/06_Indian_Calendar/15_BIBLIOGRAPHY/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar/06_Indian_Calendar/15_BIBLIOGRAPHY/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Achelis, Elisabeth (1955)-Of Time and the Calendar, New York.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Alter, D. &amp;amp; Cleminshaw, C. H. (1952)—Pictorial Astronomy, New York.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Aryabhaṭīya of Āryabhaṭa-translated with notes by W. E. Clark, Chicago, 1930.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;American Ephemeris &amp;rsquo; &amp;amp; Nautical Almanac for the years 1954 and 1955.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Bachuofer, Dr. L. (1936)-Herrscher and Munzen in spaten Kushanas, Journal of American Oriental Society. Vol. 56. - (1941) On Greeks and śakas in India, Journal of American Oriental Sooiety, Vol. 61, p. 223.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Basak, Dr. Radhagovinda (1950)&amp;ndash;Kauţiliya Arthaśāstra, Bengali translation, Calcutta.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Bhandarkar (1927-34)—Inscriptions of Northern India, Appendix to Epigraphia Indica, Vols. XIX-XXII. Brennand, W. (1896)-Hindu Astronomy.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Burgess, Rev. E. (1935)-The Sūrya-Siddhānta, English translation, with an introduction by P. O. Sengupta (Republished by the Calcutta University).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Clark, Walter Eugene (1930)—The Aryabhaṭīya of Arya bhata, English translation with notes, Chicago.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Couderc, Paul (1948)—Lo Calendrier, France.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Cunningham, Alexander (1883)—Book of Indian Eras with tables for calculating Indian dates, Calcutta.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Debevoise (1938)—Political History of Parthia.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Deydier (1951)-Le date de Kaniṣka etc. Journal Asiatique, Vol. 239.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Digha Nikāya (1890), Vol. I, Pali Text Book Society&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Dikgit, S. B. (1896)—Bbāratiya Jyotiśāstra (in Mārāthi).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Discovery (1953), Vol. XIV, p. 276, Norwich (Eng.).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Dreyer, J.L.E. (1953)A History of Astronomy from :: Thales to Kepler, Dover Publications, Inc.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Dvivedi, Sudhākara (1925)-The Sūrya Siddhānta, translation under his editorship, Asiatic Society of Bengal, Cal.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Encyclopaedia Britannica (14th edition)- Articles on Chronology, Calendar and Easter. Encyclopaedia of Religion &amp;amp; Ethics—Vols. I, II &amp;amp; III, Now York (1911),&amp;mdash;Articles on Calendar and Festivals.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Epigraphia Indica, Vol. XXVII.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Flammarion, C. &amp;amp; Gore, J. E. (1907)—Popular Astronomy, London.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Fotheringham, Dr. J. Ko (1935)-The Calendar, article published in the Nautical Almanac, London 1935.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Ginsel, F. K. (1906)-Handbuch der Mathematischen und Technischen Chronologie, Bd. I, Leipzig.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Haug, Dr. Martin-Aitareya Brāhmaṇa of the Rig Veda.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Herzfeld (1932)&amp;ndash;śakasthan, Archaeologische Mitteilungen ans Iran.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Jacobi, Prof. Hermann (1892)-The computation of Hindu dates in inscriptions, Eph. Ind. Vol. I, p. 403.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Jones, Sir H. Spencer (1934, 1955)-General Astronomy, : London - (1952)—Calendar, Past, Present &amp;amp; Future . --a lecture delivered at the Royal Society of Arts, London, 1952. - (1937) The measurement of time, published in the Reports on Progress in Physics, Vol. IV, London. Journal of Calendar Reform, New York.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Keith, Dr. Berriedalo—The Veda of the Black Yajur School entitled Taittiriya Samhitā, Part. 2. Khandakhādyaka of Brahmagupta&amp;ndash;Edited with an introduction by Babua Misra-translated by P. C. Sengupta (1934), Calcutta University, 1934.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Konow, Dr. Sten (1929)-Corpus Inscriptionum Indicarum, Vol.II, Karoṣthi Inscriptions.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Krogdhal, Waslog. S.&amp;ndash;The Astronomical Universe, U. S. A.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Labiri, N. C. (1952)—Tables of the Sun, Calcutta.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Luders (1909-10)– A list of Brāhmi Inscriptions from the earliest times to 400 A.D.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Appendix to Epigraphia Indica, Vol. X. (The references are given, 0.8., Luders 942, which means inscription No. 942 of Lūders).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Majumder, N. G. (1929) Inscriptions of Bengal, Rajshahi, Bengal.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Majumder, R. C. (1943)-The History of Bengal, Vol. I. Dacca University.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Nautical Almanac (British) for the years 1935 &amp;amp; 1954 to 1956.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Neugebauer, O. (1952)—The Exact Sciences in Antiquity, Princeton, New Jeresy, (1954) Babylonian Planetary Theory, Proceedings of the American Philosophical Society, Vol. 98. No. 1, 1954 Newcomb, Simon (1906)-A Compendium of Spherical Astronomy, New York.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Norton, Arthur P. (1950)&amp;ndash; A Star Atlas, London.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Pannekoek, Antone (1916)&amp;ndash;Calculation of Datos in Baby lonian Tables of Planets, Proc.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Roy. Soc. Amste I, 1916, 684. - (1951)—The Origin of Astronomy, M. N. R. A. S., Vol. III, No. 4, 1951. (1930)&amp;ndash;Astrology and its influence upon the development of Astronomy—Jr.R. A. S. of Canada April, 1930. :&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Panth, B. D. (1944)–Consider the Calendar, New York.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Pillai, L. D. Swamikannu (1922)-An Indian Ephemeris, Vol. I, Suptd. Govt. Press, Madras.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Rapson (1922)——The Cambridge. History of India, Val. I, Ancient India.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Ray Chowdhury, H. C. (1938) Political History of Ancient India, 5th edition, Calcutta University.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Roy. J. C. (1903)-Amāder Jyotiṣ. O Jyotiṣi (Bengali). Calcutta.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Rufus, W. Carl (1942)-How to meet the fifth column in Astronomy, Sky &amp;amp; Telescope, Jan, 1942, Vol. I, No. 3.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Russell, H. N., Dugan, R. S., &amp;amp; Stewart, J. Q. (1945)— Astronomy, 2 Vols, U. S. A.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Sachau, Edward C. (1910)-Alberuni&amp;rsquo;s India, English tran. : slation in 2 Vols., London.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Sachs, A. (1952)—Babylonian Horoscopes, Reprinted from the Journal of Cunieform Studies, Vol. VI, No. 2.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Saba, M. N. (1952)— Reform of the Indian Calendar, Science &amp;amp; Culture, Vol. 18, 1952. (1952)-Calender through Ages and Countries, Lecture delivered at the Andhra University, 1952. (1953)-Different methods of Dato recording in Ancient and Medieval India and the origin of the śaka era—Jounal of the Asiatic Society, Letters, Vol. XIX, No. 1, 1953.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Sarton, George (1953)-A History of Science, Oxford University Press, London. &amp;ndash; Introduction to the History of Science, Vol. III.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Schmidt, Olaf (1951)-On the Computation of the Ahargaṇa, Centaurus, September, 1952, 2. Copenhagen.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Scientific American, 188, 6-25, 1953, New York.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Sen, Sukumar (1941)-Old Persian Inscriptions of the Achemenian Emperors, Calcutta University.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Songupta, P. C. (1947)—Ancient Indian Chronology, Calcutta University. - Articles published in the Śrī Bhāratz ( Bengali ) (1925)-Khandakbādyaka of Brahmagupta edited with an introduction, Calcutta University.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Sowell. R. S. (1924)—The Siddhāntas and the Indian Calendar. – (1912) – The Indian Chronography Sowell, R. S. &amp;amp; Dikpit, S. B. (1896)-The Indian Calendar, London.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Shamasastry, R. (1936)-Vodānga Jyautisha-edited with English translation &amp;amp; Sanskrit commentary. Mysore.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Sirkar, D. C. (1942)-Select inscriptions bearing on Indian history and civilization, Calcutta University.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Sky &amp;amp; Telescope, Vol. I, 1942 &amp;amp; Vol. XII, 1953, Cambridge, Mass., U. S. A. Smrtitirtha, Pt. Radbavallabha-Siddhānta Siromani of Bhāskarācārya-Bengali translation in 2 Vols. Calcutta.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Svāmi, Vijñānānanda (1909)—Sūrya Siddhānta, Bengali translation with notes, Calcutta.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Thibaut, G. (1889)-The Pañca Siddhāntikā-the Astrono. mical works of Varā bamihira, odited by G. Thibaut &amp;amp; Mm. Sudhakara Dvivedi, Banaras.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Tilak, B. G. (1893)-Orion or Researches into the Antiquity of the Vedas, Poona. Universal History of the World, Vols. I &amp;amp; II, edited by J. H. Hammerton, London.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Van der Waerden-Science Awakening.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Van Lohuizen de Leeuw (1949)—The Scythian Period, Leiden, (shortly called L. de. Leeuw or Leeuw with page following).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Varāhamihira—Bịhat Samhitā, Bengali translation by Pt. Pañcānana Tarkaratna (1910), Calcutta. 5 Pañca Siddhāntikā—edited by G. Thibaut &amp;amp; Mm. Sudhakara Dvivedi, Banaras, 1889.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Watkins, Harold (1954)—Time Counts, London.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Webster, A. G.&amp;ndash;Dynamics of Particles and of Rigid Elastic &amp;amp; Fluid bodies.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Winternitz-History of Indian Literature, Vol. I, Calcutta University.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Woolard, Edgar W. (1942)—The Era of Nabonassor, article published in the Sky &amp;amp; Telescope, Vol. I, No. 6, April, 1942.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Yampolsky, Philip (1950)-The Origin of the Twenty-eight Lunar mansions, published in Osiris, Vol. IX, 1950.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Zinner, Dr. Ernest (1931)-Die Geschichte der Sternkunde, Berlin.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>16 INDEX</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar/06_Indian_Calendar/16_INDEX/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar/06_Indian_Calendar/16_INDEX/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;171&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Abbe Mastrofini, 171&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Artemidorus of Puṣkalåvati, 230&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Brāhmaṇas, 193, 214, 221, 241, 245 Abd al-Rahámān al-Būfi, 206&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Arthasūstra of Kautilya, 235, 236&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Brahmi, 227, 229, 231, 232, 233 Achelis, Miss Elisabeth, 12, 171&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Arunodaya, 108&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Brhat Samhitā, 226, 267 Adar, 179&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Aryabhaṭa I, 204, 234, 236, 237, 238, 240, 252, Brown, 193 Addaru, 175,176&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;253, 254, 267&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Buddha, 231, 235; . Adhika ( = mala) month, 7, 247, 250&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
