<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;01 Intro on ज्योतिषे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/calendar_reform_comittee_report/01_Intro/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;01 Intro on ज्योतिषे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/calendar_reform_comittee_report/01_Intro/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 Nehru&#39;s MESSAGE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/calendar_reform_comittee_report/01_Intro/01_Nehrus_MESSAGE/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/calendar_reform_comittee_report/01_Intro/01_Nehrus_MESSAGE/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I am glad that the Calendar Reform Committee has started its labours. The Government of India has entrusted to it the work of examining the different calendars followed in this country and to submit proposals to the Government for an accurate and uniform calendar based on a scientific study for the whole of India. I am told that we have at present thirty different calendars, differing from each other in various ways, including the methods of time reckoning. These calendars are the natural result of our past political and cultural history and partly represent past political divisions in the country. Now that we have attained independence, it is obviously desirable that there should be a certain uniformity in the calendar for our civic, social and other purposes and that this should be based on a scientific approach to this problem.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>02 MEMBERS OF THE CALENDAR REFORM COMMITTEE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/calendar_reform_comittee_report/01_Intro/02_MEMBERS_OF_THE_CALENDAR_REFORM_COMMITTEE/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/calendar_reform_comittee_report/01_Intro/02_MEMBERS_OF_THE_CALENDAR_REFORM_COMMITTEE/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAIRMAN Prof. M. N.Saha, D. Sc., F. R. S., M. P., Director, Institute of Nuclear Physics, 92, Upper Circular Road, Calcutta-9..&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;members&#34;&gt;MEMBERS&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Prof. A. C. Banerji, M. A., M. Sc., F. N. I.,  Vice-Chancellor, Allahabad University, Allahabad.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Dr. K. L. Daftari, B. A., B. L., D. Litt., Mahal, Nagpur.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Shri J. S. Karandikar, B. A., LL. B., Ex-Editor, The Kesari, 568 Narayan Peth, Poona-2.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Dr. Gorakh Prasad, D. Sc., Reader in Mathematics, Allahabad University, Beli Avenue, Allahabad.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>03 TRANSLITERATION</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/calendar_reform_comittee_report/01_Intro/03_TRANSLITERATION/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/calendar_reform_comittee_report/01_Intro/03_TRANSLITERATION/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The scheme of transliteration of Sanskrit alphabets into Roman script adopted in this publication is the same as generally followed. The corresponding scripts are given below :&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;N. B. Diacritical marks have not generally been used in names of persons belonging to recent times as well as in well-known geographical names,&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>04 PREFACE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/calendar_reform_comittee_report/01_Intro/04_PREFACE/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/calendar_reform_comittee_report/01_Intro/04_PREFACE/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;goals&#34;&gt;Goals&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Calendar Reform Committee was appointed in November, 1952, by the Council of Scientific and Industrial Research (of the Government of India) with the following terms of reference:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;To examine all the existing calendars which are being followed in the country at present and after scientific study of the subject, submit proposals for an accurate and uniform calendar for the whole of India&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In accordance with its terms of reference, the Committee (for personnel, see p. 4) has scientifically examined all the calendars prevalent in India (vide Part C, Chap. V), viz.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
