<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;26 Appendices on ज्योतिषे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/articles/Hamlets_Mill__Santillana_Dechend/26_Appendices/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;26 Appendices on ज्योतिषे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/articles/Hamlets_Mill__Santillana_Dechend/26_Appendices/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/articles/Hamlets_Mill__Santillana_Dechend/26_Appendices/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/articles/Hamlets_Mill__Santillana_Dechend/26_Appendices/01/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Appendix 1&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The only master of this kind of observation hitherto has been Marcel Griaule (d. 1956) but he left an impressive cohort of disciples. They have renewed the understanding of African studies, showing that such systems are still alive with the Dogon, whom Griaule &amp;ldquo;discovered,&amp;rdquo; in the true sense of the word.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;As Germaine Dieterlen writes: &amp;ldquo;The smallest everyday object may reveal a conscious reflection of a complex cosmogony . . . Thus for instance African techniques, so poor in appearance, like those of agriculture, weaving and smithing, have a rich, hidden content of significance . . . The sacrifice of a humble chicken, when accompanied by the necessary and effective ritual gestures, recalls in the thinking of those who have experienced it an understanding that is at once original and coherent of the origins and functioning of the universe.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>02</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/articles/Hamlets_Mill__Santillana_Dechend/26_Appendices/02/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/articles/Hamlets_Mill__Santillana_Dechend/26_Appendices/02/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Appendix 2&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The father of Saxo&amp;rsquo;s Amlethus was &lt;em&gt;Horvandillus&lt;/em&gt;, written also Orendel, Erentel, Earendel, Oervandill, Aurvandil, whom the appendix to the &lt;em&gt;Heldenbuch&lt;/em&gt; pronounces the first of all heroes that were ever born. The few data known about him are summarized by Jacob Grimm: [1]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;He suffers shipwreck on a voyage, takes shelter with a master fisherman Eisen, [2]  earns the seamless coat of his master, and afterwards wins frau Breide, the fairest of women: king Eigel of Trier was his father&amp;rsquo;s name. The whole tissue of the fable puts one in mind of the Odyssey: the shipwrecked man clings to a plank, digs himself a hole, holds a bough before him; even the seamless coat may be compared to Ino&amp;rsquo;s veil, and the fisher to the swineheard, dame Breide&amp;rsquo;s templars would be Penelope&amp;rsquo;s suitors, and angels are sent often, like Zeus&amp;rsquo;s messengers. Yet many things take a different turn, more in German fashion, and incidents are added, such as the laying of a naked sword between the newly married couple, which the Greek story knows nothing of. The hero&amp;rsquo;s name is found even in OHG. documents: Orendil . . . Orentil . . . a village Orendelsal, now Orendensall, in Hohenlohe . . . But the Edda has another myth, which was alluded to in speaking of the stone in Thor&amp;rsquo;s head. Groa is busy conning her magic spell, when Thorr, to requite her for the approaching cure, imparts the welcome news, that in coming from Jötunheim in the North he has carried her husband the bold Örvandill in a basket on his back, and he is sure to be home soon; he adds by way of token, that as Örvandil&amp;rsquo;s toe had stuck out of the basket and got frozen, he broke it off and flung it at the sky, and made a star of it, which is called &lt;em&gt;Örvandils-tâ&lt;/em&gt;. But Groa in her joy at the tidings forgot her spell, so the stone in the god&amp;rsquo;s head never got loose (Snorri&amp;rsquo;s Skaldskap. 17).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>03</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/articles/Hamlets_Mill__Santillana_Dechend/26_Appendices/03/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/articles/Hamlets_Mill__Santillana_Dechend/26_Appendices/03/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Appendix 3&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Now, apart from the circumstance that the snowy burial ascribed to the followers of Kai Khusrau, Enoch, and Quetzalcouatl could hardly be claimed to be an &amp;ldquo;obvious&amp;rdquo; feature, the fate of Quetzalcouatl&amp;rsquo;s companions might further our understanding; more correctly, the topos where this event is supposed to have happened might do so. The &amp;ldquo;five mountains&amp;rdquo; of Mexican myth, their &amp;ldquo;gods&amp;rdquo; respectively, the &lt;em&gt;Tepictoton&lt;/em&gt;, [1]  appear to represent the five Uayeb (= Maya; with the Aztecs: Nemontemi), the Epagomena, those days gained by Mercury from the Moon during a game of checkers, in order to help Rhea/Nut to days &amp;ldquo;outside of the year,&amp;rdquo; when she could bring forth the five planets. As a matter of fact, in his chapter on the clothes and emblems of the gods, Sahagún puts the &amp;ldquo;Mountain-Gods&amp;rdquo; at the end of the list. [2]&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>04</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/articles/Hamlets_Mill__Santillana_Dechend/26_Appendices/04/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/articles/Hamlets_Mill__Santillana_Dechend/26_Appendices/04/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Appendix 4&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It is as yet too early in the day to deal with &amp;ldquo;Uncle Kamsa,&amp;rdquo; whom lexicographers make a &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;mūra-deva&lt;/em&gt;,&amp;rdquo; allegedly a &amp;ldquo;venerator of roots&amp;rdquo; (&lt;em&gt;mūla/mūra&lt;/em&gt; = root). In his &lt;em&gt;Kleine Beiträge&lt;/em&gt; (p. 11), Jarl Charpentier earnestly wishes us to accept as that &amp;ldquo;among the Indian natives fighting against the invading Aryans there were such,&amp;rdquo; namely, &amp;ldquo;venerators of roots&amp;rdquo; (and venerators of worms as well). Although we do not doubt that the species Homo sapiens is capable of any &amp;ldquo;belief,&amp;rdquo; we cannot perceive any cogent reason for subscribing to Charpentier&amp;rsquo;s view. &lt;em&gt;Mūla/mūra&lt;/em&gt;, the &amp;ldquo;root,&amp;rdquo; is a Nakshatra, a lunar mansion woven around with tales: it is the sting of Scorpius, serving as Marduk&amp;rsquo;s weapon in: the &amp;ldquo;Babylonian Genesis&amp;rdquo; and as Polynesian Maui&amp;rsquo;s fishhook; with the Copts it is &amp;ldquo;statio translationis Caniculae . . . unde et Siôt vocatur,&amp;rdquo; i.e., the Coptic table of lunar stations takes lambda upsilon Scorpii as the precise opposite of Sirius/Sothis, as we are informed by Athanasius Kircher, whereas Indian tables ascribe the role of exact opposition to Betelgeuse, ruled by &amp;ldquo;Rudra-the-destroying-archer.&amp;rdquo; Although we cannot pursue these and other tales further here, we think it at least appropriate to mention the concrete problems arising with such characters as &amp;ldquo;Uncle Kamsa,&amp;rdquo; instead of accusing a true Asura of &amp;ldquo;veneration of roots.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>05</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/articles/Hamlets_Mill__Santillana_Dechend/26_Appendices/05/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/articles/Hamlets_Mill__Santillana_Dechend/26_Appendices/05/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Appendix 5&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sem Snaebjoern krad:&lt;/em&gt;  &amp;gt;  &lt;em&gt;Hwatt kveda hraera Grotta&lt;/em&gt;  &amp;gt;  &lt;em&gt;hergrimmastan skerja&lt;/em&gt;  &amp;gt;  &lt;em&gt;ut fyrir jardar skauti&lt;/em&gt;  &amp;gt;  &lt;em&gt;Elyudrs niu brudir;&lt;/em&gt;  &amp;gt;  &lt;em&gt;ther er, lungs, fyrir laungu&lt;/em&gt;  &amp;gt;  &lt;em&gt;lid-meldr, skipa hlidar&lt;/em&gt;  &amp;gt;  &lt;em&gt;baugskerdir ristr bardi&lt;/em&gt;  &amp;gt;  &lt;em&gt;bol, Amloda mólu&lt;/em&gt;  &amp;gt;  &lt;em&gt;Her er kallat hafit Amloda Kvern.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Gollancz (&lt;em&gt;Hamlet in Iceland&lt;/em&gt;, p. xi) retranslated his translation into Old Norse so that the original and the &lt;em&gt;nolens volens&lt;/em&gt; interpreting translation might be compared. The retranslation runs thus: kveda niu brudir eyludrs hraera hvat hergrimmastan skerja grotta ut fyrir jardar skauti, thaer er fyrir longu molu Amloda lid-meldr; baugskerdir ristr skipa hlidar bol lungs bardi. Elton translates the passage:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>06</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/articles/Hamlets_Mill__Santillana_Dechend/26_Appendices/06/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/articles/Hamlets_Mill__Santillana_Dechend/26_Appendices/06/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Appendix 6&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It is not as easy to dispose of &lt;em&gt;Mysing&lt;/em&gt;, as the specialists pretend, e.g., by preferring to interpret his name as &amp;ldquo;mouse-gray&amp;rdquo; instead of the equally possible &amp;ldquo;son of a mouse.&amp;rdquo; Olrik (pp. 459f.) proposes to identify straightaway &amp;ldquo;King Mysing who killed Frith-Frothi, and the cow that struck down Frothi the Peaceful . . . King Mysing is merely a rationalistic explanation of the ancient monster.&amp;rdquo; (For the death of Frodi by means of a sea cow, see also P. Herrmann&amp;rsquo;s commentary on Saxo, pp. 380-84. This &amp;ldquo;cow&amp;rdquo; — in Iceland they remain within the frame of zoology and make it a stag — was, according to Saxo, a witch, who was pierced through by Frodi&amp;rsquo;s men. Afterwards they kept Frodi&amp;rsquo;s death a secret for three years, in the same manner as told by Snorri in his &lt;em&gt;Heimskringla&lt;/em&gt; about Frey.)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>07</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/articles/Hamlets_Mill__Santillana_Dechend/26_Appendices/07/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/articles/Hamlets_Mill__Santillana_Dechend/26_Appendices/07/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Appendix 7&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We want to stress the point that the haughty verdicts as given by Genzmer, Olrik, and others on Snorri&amp;rsquo;s tale are not unknown to us. Their opinions run along these lines: &amp;ldquo;The last part of the story of Grotti and Mysing is &amp;lsquo;How the sea grew salt.&amp;rsquo; This is a different motif, in no wise connected with the peace of Frothi.&amp;rdquo; [1]  Genzmer&amp;rsquo;s wording is more arrogant still. The transportation of the mill by Mysing and the grinding of salt aboard the ship is &amp;ldquo;die Anschweissung einer zweiten selbständigen Sage; der grossartig einfache, ahnungsvolle Schluss unserer Dichtung wird durch ein solches Anhängsel tödlich geschädigt.&amp;rdquo; [2]&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>08</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/articles/Hamlets_Mill__Santillana_Dechend/26_Appendices/08/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/articles/Hamlets_Mill__Santillana_Dechend/26_Appendices/08/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Appendix 8&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Vafthrudnismal 35 is rendered by Gering: &amp;ldquo;Ungezählte Winter vor der Schöpfung / geschah Bergelmirs Geburt. / Als frühestes weiss ich, dass der erfahrene Riese / Im Boote geborgen ward.&amp;rdquo; Simrock translates similarly, and he remarks (&lt;em&gt;Hdb. Dt. Myth&lt;/em&gt;., § 9): &amp;ldquo;Das dunkle Wort &lt;em&gt;ludr&lt;/em&gt; für Boot zu nehmen, sind wir sowohl durch den Zusammenhang als durch die Mythenvergleichung berechtigt.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;R. B. Anderson (&lt;em&gt;The Younger Edda&lt;/em&gt; [1880], pp. 60f.) translates the verse — quoted by Snorri (&lt;em&gt;Gylf&lt;/em&gt;. 7) — as follows: &amp;ldquo;Countless winters / Ere the earth was made, / Was born Bergelmer. / The first I call to mind / How the crafty giant / Safe in his ark lay.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>09</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/articles/Hamlets_Mill__Santillana_Dechend/26_Appendices/09/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/articles/Hamlets_Mill__Santillana_Dechend/26_Appendices/09/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Appendix 9&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;As a matter of fact, Simrock already (&lt;em&gt;Handbuch der Deutschen Mythologie&lt;/em&gt;, pp. 240f.) ventured to interpret Fengö (Amlethus&amp;rsquo; evil uncle) as &amp;ldquo;the grinding,&amp;rdquo; and Amlethus as &amp;ldquo;the grain&amp;rdquo;; &amp;ldquo;wo selbst der Name mit Amelmehl (Greek &lt;em&gt;amylon&lt;/em&gt;), Stärkemehl, Kraftmehl übereinstimmt.&amp;rdquo; He even thought of the possibility (although taking this thought for audacious, &amp;ldquo;gewagt&amp;rdquo;) to derive the family name of Thidrek&amp;rsquo;s clan, i.e., the name of the Amelunge, from &amp;ldquo;Amelmehl&amp;rdquo; We shan&amp;rsquo;t dwell upon the strange information given by Athenaeus (&lt;em&gt;Deipnosophistai&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;3&lt;/em&gt;.1 14f.) about &amp;ldquo;Achilles, or very fine barley&amp;rdquo; (cf. Theophr. &lt;em&gt;8&lt;/em&gt;.4-2. Aristoph. &lt;em&gt;Eq&lt;/em&gt;. 819: Achilles cake), or on the surname of Ningishzida, namely Zid-zi &amp;ldquo;Meal of Life&amp;rdquo; (K. Tallqvist, &lt;em&gt;Akkadische&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;Götterepitheta&lt;/em&gt;, p. 406; cf. Riemschneider, &lt;em&gt;Augengott&lt;/em&gt;, p. 133), and we point only to Ras Shamra texts, where the lady Anat ground Mot. (See C. Gordon, &lt;em&gt;Ugaritic Literature&lt;/em&gt;, p. 45.) H. L. Ginsberg (ANET, p. 140) translates I AB, col. II:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>10</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/articles/Hamlets_Mill__Santillana_Dechend/26_Appendices/10/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/articles/Hamlets_Mill__Santillana_Dechend/26_Appendices/10/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Appendix 10&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;For the first Irish harp (&lt;em&gt;cruit&lt;/em&gt;), see Eugene O&amp;rsquo;Curry, *On the Manners and Customs of *&lt;em&gt;the Ancient Irish&lt;/em&gt;, vol. &lt;em&gt;3&lt;/em&gt; (1873), pp. 236f.; see also Rudolf Thurneysen, *Die irische *&lt;em&gt;Helden- und Königssage bis zum 17&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Jahrhundert&lt;/em&gt; (1911), pp. 264f.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;There once lived a couple . . . And the wife conceived a hatred to him, and she was flying from him through woods and wilderness; and he continued to follow her constantly. And one day that the woman came to the sea shore of Camas . . . she met a skeleton of a whale on the strand, and she heard the sounds of the wind passing through the sinews of the whale on the strand, and she fell asleep from the sounds. And her husband came after her; and he perceived that it was from the sounds the sleep fell upon her. And he then went forward into the wood, and made the form of a &lt;em&gt;Cruit;&lt;/em&gt; [1]  and he put strings from the sinews of the whale into it; and that was the first Cruit that was ever made.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>11</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/articles/Hamlets_Mill__Santillana_Dechend/26_Appendices/11/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/articles/Hamlets_Mill__Santillana_Dechend/26_Appendices/11/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Appendix 11&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Christensen, in his work on the Kayanids, [1]  states: &amp;ldquo;La tradition nationale fait grand cas du forgeron Kâvag, qui s&amp;rsquo;insurgeait contre l&amp;rsquo;usurpateur Dahâg (le Dahâka des Yashts) et hissait son tablier de cuir sur une lance, ce qui flit l&amp;rsquo;origine du drapeau de l&amp;rsquo;empire sassanide, appelé &lt;em&gt;drafš ê kâvyân&lt;/em&gt;, &amp;lsquo;drapeau de Kâvag.&amp;rsquo; Cette légende, née d&amp;rsquo;un malentendu, la vraie signification du nom de drafš ê kâvyân étant &amp;rsquo;le drapeau royal,&amp;rsquo; est inconnue dans la tradition religieuse.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>12</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/articles/Hamlets_Mill__Santillana_Dechend/26_Appendices/12/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/articles/Hamlets_Mill__Santillana_Dechend/26_Appendices/12/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Appendix 12&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It should be stressed that the disinclination of philologists to allow for the &amp;ldquo;essential&amp;rdquo; connection of Chronos and Kronos rests upon the stern belief that the &amp;ldquo;god&amp;rdquo; Saturn has nothing to do with the planet Saturn, and upon the supposition that an expert in classical philology has nothing whatever to learn from Indian texts. Were it not so, they might have stumbled over Kāla, i.e., Chronos, as a name of Yama, i.e., Kronos, alias the planet Saturn.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>13</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/articles/Hamlets_Mill__Santillana_Dechend/26_Appendices/13/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/articles/Hamlets_Mill__Santillana_Dechend/26_Appendices/13/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Appendix 13&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Some say, he bid his angels turn askance&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The poles of earth, twice ten degrees and more&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;From the sun&amp;rsquo;s axle, they with labour pushed&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Oblique the centric globe: some say, the sun&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Was bid turn reins from the equinoctial road . . .&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;. . . else had the spring&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Perpetual smiled on earth with vernant flowers&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Equal in days and nights, except to those&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>14</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/articles/Hamlets_Mill__Santillana_Dechend/26_Appendices/14/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/articles/Hamlets_Mill__Santillana_Dechend/26_Appendices/14/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Appendix 14&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The name Mundilfoeri (Mundel-fere) raises a cluster of problems, and nothing is gained by evasive statements such as that given by de Vries (&lt;em&gt;Altnord&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Etym&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Wb&lt;/em&gt;., p. 395): &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;Mundilferi&lt;/em&gt;. Name of the father of the Moon . . . &lt;em&gt;Mundill&lt;/em&gt;. Name of a legendary figure.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;As concerns &lt;em&gt;mund&lt;/em&gt;, feminine, it means &amp;ldquo;hand&amp;rdquo; (Cleasby-Vigfusson, s.v.), but &lt;em&gt;mund&lt;/em&gt; comprises the meaning of tutelage, guardianship (cf. German Vor&lt;em&gt;mund&lt;/em&gt;). &lt;em&gt;Mund&lt;/em&gt; as a neutrum means &amp;ldquo;point of time, mood, humor, measure, and the right time&amp;rdquo; (de Vries, &lt;em&gt;loc&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;em&gt;cit&lt;/em&gt;.).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>15</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/articles/Hamlets_Mill__Santillana_Dechend/26_Appendices/15/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/articles/Hamlets_Mill__Santillana_Dechend/26_Appendices/15/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Appendix 15&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;As concerns the removing of the Pole star, the most drastic version is told by the Lapps:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;When Arcturus (alpha Bootis, supposed to be an archer, Ursa Major being his bow) shoots down the North Nail with his arrow on the last day, the heaven will fall, crushing the earth and setting fire to everything. [1]&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Other legends prefer to deal with the fate of circumpolar stars, the result being the same.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>16</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/articles/Hamlets_Mill__Santillana_Dechend/26_Appendices/16/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/articles/Hamlets_Mill__Santillana_Dechend/26_Appendices/16/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Appendix 16&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;For &lt;em&gt;Hallinskidi&lt;/em&gt; see Reuter, p. 237; Simrock, &lt;em&gt;Handbuch&lt;/em&gt;, p. 277; Gering (&lt;em&gt;Edda&lt;/em&gt; trans., p. 320): &amp;ldquo;gebogene Schneeschuhe habend.&amp;rdquo; Much (in &lt;em&gt;Festschrift Heinzel&lt;/em&gt;, p. 259), connecting -&lt;em&gt;skidi&lt;/em&gt; with Celtic skêto, skêda (English: humerus, scapula) and taking &lt;em&gt;halle&lt;/em&gt; for &amp;ldquo;stone,&amp;rdquo; ventures to propose the reconstruction &amp;ldquo;he with the stone shoulder . . . which would presuppose a similar story as that about Pelops and his ivory shoulder.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;As concerns &lt;em&gt;mjötvidr&lt;/em&gt;, A. V. Strom renders vol. &lt;em&gt;2&lt;/em&gt;: [1]&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>17</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/articles/Hamlets_Mill__Santillana_Dechend/26_Appendices/17/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/articles/Hamlets_Mill__Santillana_Dechend/26_Appendices/17/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Appendix 17&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;To prevent rash critics from hurling into our faces the — maybe they will style it thus — “complete absence of technological knowledge,&amp;quot; we hasten to assert that the relevant inquiries are not as foreign to us as they might assume. [1]  Curwen might point to his enlightened sentence:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We are, happily, emerging from that state of blissful ignorance of the subject which made possible such an anachronism as Décamps&amp;rsquo; well-known picture of &amp;ldquo;Samson grinding in the Prison-house,&amp;rdquo; wherein Samson is seen turning a huge mill-stone by means of a long lever like a capstan-bar, after the fashion of the Roman slaves a thousand years later. [2]&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>18</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/articles/Hamlets_Mill__Santillana_Dechend/26_Appendices/18/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/articles/Hamlets_Mill__Santillana_Dechend/26_Appendices/18/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Appendix 18&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Compare &lt;em&gt;Popol Vuh: The Sacred Book of the Ancient Quiché Maya&lt;/em&gt; (Eng. trans. by D. Goetz and S. Morley, [1951], pp. 90-102). As concerns the escape of Zipacna, compare the distribution map, given by Frobenius (&lt;em&gt;Paideuma 1&lt;/em&gt; [1938], p. 8, map 3 — &amp;ldquo;Der Lausbub im Haus pfeiler&amp;rdquo;).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;For the whole motif of pillars and houses pulled down, compare Eduard Stucken, &lt;em&gt;Astralmythen&lt;/em&gt; (1896-1907): pp. 73f. for the death of Nebrôd, according to Cedrenus — of Cain, according to Leo Grammaticus Chron. p. 8 (Kain, hōs legei Mōysēs, tēs oikias pesousēs ep&amp;rsquo;auton eteleutēsen); pp. 329f. for the case of Susanowo; p. 348 for Turkish Depe Ghöz; pp. 402f. for Zipacna; there, he also wants to incorporate Job 1.18. Stucken&amp;rsquo;s complete blindness to the mere existence of planets has prevented him from better understanding; thus, he claims for the case of Job 1.18: &amp;ldquo;Auch hier ist die Orion-Gottheit (Satan-Ahriman), welche den Hauseinsturz verursacht, urn die Plejaden-Gottheit (Hiob) zu züchtigen.&amp;rdquo; This blindness is the more astonishing as Stucken has read Eisenmenger&amp;rsquo;s huge opus, &amp;ldquo;Entdecktes Judenthum&amp;rdquo; (1711), where he should have detected the identity (as claimed by rabbinical literature) of the planet Mars  with the serpent in Paradise, with Kain, Esau, Abimelech, Goliath, Sammael, the Scape-Goat, and many others.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>19</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/articles/Hamlets_Mill__Santillana_Dechend/26_Appendices/19/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/articles/Hamlets_Mill__Santillana_Dechend/26_Appendices/19/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Appendix 19&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A remarkable amount of information about submarine creatures is contained in Mansikka&amp;rsquo;s inquiry into Russian magic formulae, already mentioned; [1]  intermingled as the material is with the author&amp;rsquo;s rather violent &amp;ldquo;interpretatio christiana,&amp;rdquo; it is well-nigh impossible to lay one&amp;rsquo;s hands on the bare facts. This much can be said, however: in the middle of the &amp;ldquo;Blue Sea&amp;rdquo; (or &amp;ldquo;the middle of the whole earth&amp;rdquo;), there is either (a) an island-most of the time called &lt;em&gt;Bujan&lt;/em&gt;, from the same radical as buoy — “the center of celestial power,&amp;quot; upon which there is a tree, or a stone, or a tree upon a stone, sometimes the cross or the &amp;ldquo;mountain of Zion&amp;rdquo; itself; [2]  or there is (b) the &amp;ldquo;White Altar-Stone,&amp;rdquo; which is a &amp;ldquo;fiery&amp;rdquo; one, lying in the navel of the sea without  being supported by an island; under this stone, there is &amp;ldquo;a green fire, the king of all fires,&amp;rdquo; or an &amp;ldquo;eternal, unquenchable fire&amp;rdquo; that &amp;ldquo;has to be procured from under  the stone&amp;rdquo; (Mansikka, p. 188 — we are not told for what purpose the fire has to be fetched from there; the text says only &amp;ldquo;for burning&amp;rdquo;). Sometimes it is said that upon this stone — regardless of its being &amp;ldquo;holy&amp;rdquo; and the &amp;ldquo;Stone of the Altar,&amp;rdquo; and even &amp;ldquo;Christ&amp;rsquo;s Throne&amp;rdquo; — was the &amp;ldquo;habitation of the Devil himself&amp;rdquo;; [3]  in other formulae the point is stressed that this fire &amp;ldquo;scorches and burns the decayed and impure power of the devil&amp;rdquo; (i.e., &amp;ldquo;die verfallene, unreine Macht des Teufels,&amp;rdquo; where &amp;ldquo;verfallen&amp;rdquo; may mean either &amp;ldquo;decayed&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;forfeited&amp;rdquo;). As long as this unquenchable fire remains safely under a stone, nothing dangerous is going to happen; accordingly, a German formula (Mansikka, p. 37) says: &amp;ldquo;In Christ&amp;rsquo;s Garden there is a well, in the well there is a stone, under the stone lies a golden snake.&amp;rdquo; That snake can also be a scorpion, as we have just seen (footnote 3).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>20</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/articles/Hamlets_Mill__Santillana_Dechend/26_Appendices/20/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/articles/Hamlets_Mill__Santillana_Dechend/26_Appendices/20/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Appendix 20&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Such stories are no jokes, although they make this impression when they cross our way in Eurasian folklore. &amp;ldquo;Air&amp;rdquo; is a strictly astronomical and, therefore, also a &amp;ldquo;religious&amp;rdquo; term. Thus, we hear from Rabbi Eleazar b. Pedath (ca. A.D. 270): &amp;ldquo;Als def Pharaoh aus Agypten auszog, die Israeliten zu verfolgen, erhoben sie ihre Augen gen Himmel und sahen den Engelsfürsten Ägyptens in der Luft fliegen.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;That signifies the fall of Egypt,&amp;rdquo; adds Bertholet, who mentions this case in his article on the &amp;ldquo;guardian angel of Persia&amp;rdquo; (&lt;em&gt;Festschrift Pavry&lt;/em&gt;, p. 38), starting from Isa. XXIV.21 and its rabbinical interpretations. He also points to the utterance of Rabbi Chanina (ca. A.D. 225): &amp;ldquo;Nicht bestraft Gott fine Nation eher, als bis er zuvor ihren Engelfürsten im Himmel bestraft hat,&amp;rdquo; to which he compares Ps. XXIV.21: &amp;ldquo;On that day the Lord will punish the host of heaven, in heaven, and the kings of the earth, on the earth.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>21</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/articles/Hamlets_Mill__Santillana_Dechend/26_Appendices/21/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/articles/Hamlets_Mill__Santillana_Dechend/26_Appendices/21/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Appendix 21&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A faint, though rather pleasant, echo of such huge events, comes from an Esthonian story about the Lake Eim changing his bed (Grimm, TM, p. 599):&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;On his banks lived wild and wicked men, who never mowed the meadows that he watered, nor sowed the fields he fertilized, but robbed and murdered, so that his bright wave was befouled with the blood of the slain. And the lake mourned; and one evening he called his fish together, and mounted with them into the air. The brigands hearing a din cried: &amp;ldquo;The Eim has left his bed, let us collect his fish and hidden treasure.&amp;rdquo; But the fish were gone, and nothing was found at the bottom but snakes, toads and salamanders, which came creeping out and lodged with the ruffian brood.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>22</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/articles/Hamlets_Mill__Santillana_Dechend/26_Appendices/22/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/articles/Hamlets_Mill__Santillana_Dechend/26_Appendices/22/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Appendix 22&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A survival, vague as it is, and evidently mistaking a chariot for a wain, we find in India. The &lt;em&gt;Sūrya&lt;/em&gt;-&lt;em&gt;Siddhānta&lt;/em&gt; states: &amp;ldquo;In Taurus, the 17th degree, a planet of which the latitude is a little more than two degrees, south, will split the &lt;em&gt;wain of Rohini&lt;/em&gt;.&amp;rdquo; [1]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;According to Burgess (p. 214), Rohini&amp;rsquo;s (= Aldebaran) wain &amp;ldquo;contains five stars, in the grouping of which Hindu fancy has seen the figure of a wain,&amp;rdquo; i.e., the Hyades, containing epsilon, delta, gamma, nu, alpha Tauri. Burgess continues (p. 249): &amp;ldquo;The &lt;em&gt;Siddhanta&lt;/em&gt; does not inform us what would be the consequences of such an occurrence; that belongs rather to the domain of astrology than of astronomy. We cite from the &lt;em&gt;Pancatantra&lt;/em&gt; (vv. 238-241) the following description of these consequences, derived from the astrological writings of Varahamihira:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>23</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/articles/Hamlets_Mill__Santillana_Dechend/26_Appendices/23/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/articles/Hamlets_Mill__Santillana_Dechend/26_Appendices/23/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Appendix 23&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;See J. Kepler, &amp;ldquo;De Stella Nova in Pede Serpentarii et qui sub ejus exortum de novo iniit Trigono Igneo,&amp;rdquo; in &lt;em&gt;Opera Omnia&lt;/em&gt;, ed. C. Frisch (1859), vol. 2, p. 636. See also J. Kepler, &amp;ldquo;De vero anno quo Aeternus Dei Filius humanam naturam . . . assumsit,&amp;rdquo; in &lt;em&gt;Opera Omnia&lt;/em&gt; (1863), vol. &lt;em&gt;4&lt;/em&gt;, pp. 346ff.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Kepler was less interested in the revolution of one angle of the trigon through the whole zodiac than in the span of time which the conjunctions needed to pass through all four &amp;ldquo;elements,&amp;rdquo; particularly between conjunctions in the &amp;ldquo;fiery triplicity.&amp;rdquo; The zodiac is divided into four &amp;ldquo;elementary&amp;rdquo; trigons or triplicities in the following manner:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>24</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/articles/Hamlets_Mill__Santillana_Dechend/26_Appendices/24/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/articles/Hamlets_Mill__Santillana_Dechend/26_Appendices/24/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Appendix 24&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Eduard Stucken (&lt;em&gt;Astralmythen&lt;/em&gt;, pp. 190ff.) and, later, F. W. Albright (JAOS &lt;em&gt;40&lt;/em&gt;, pp. 329f.) drew attention to the very same method employed when Rishyasringa, son of Vibhandaka (son of Kashyapa) and a hind, was lured by a courtesan, ordered by King Lomapada, into the latter&amp;rsquo;s town, because only with Rishyasringa present would the country have rain. (Compare H. Luders, &amp;ldquo;Die Sage von Rsyasrnga,&amp;rdquo; in *Philologica *&lt;em&gt;Indica&lt;/em&gt; [1940], pp. 1-42; also Luders, &amp;ldquo;Zur Sage von Rsyasrnga,&amp;rdquo; &lt;em&gt;Philologica Indica&lt;/em&gt;, pp. 43-73.)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>25</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/articles/Hamlets_Mill__Santillana_Dechend/26_Appendices/25/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/articles/Hamlets_Mill__Santillana_Dechend/26_Appendices/25/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Appendix 25&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It is not yet securely established what the word &lt;em&gt;sippu&lt;/em&gt; means. (See W. Baumgartner, &amp;ldquo;Untersuchungen zu den akkadischen Bauausdrücken,&amp;rdquo; ZA &lt;em&gt;36&lt;/em&gt; [1925], pp. 27, 63; A. Schott, &amp;ldquo;Zu meiner Übersetzung des Gilgamesh-Epos,&amp;rdquo; ZA &lt;em&gt;42&lt;/em&gt; [1934], pp. 105f.) For the style of this battle, characterized by Cyrus Gordon as &amp;ldquo;Beltwrestling&amp;rdquo; JNES &lt;em&gt;7&lt;/em&gt;, p. 264), see A. Oppenheim, Or. &lt;em&gt;17&lt;/em&gt;, pp. 29f. &amp;ldquo;They seized each other (by their girdles), like experts they wrestled.! They destroyed the doorpost/ The wall shook&amp;rdquo;. See also E. A. Speiser, &amp;ldquo;Akkadian Myths and Epics,&amp;rdquo; ANET, p. 78. This &amp;ldquo;doorpost&amp;rdquo; is no &lt;em&gt;quantité négligeable&lt;/em&gt; because some similar &amp;ldquo;object&amp;rdquo; comes our way again at the &amp;ldquo;entrance&amp;rdquo; of the Cedar Forest, and does the most devilish things to poor Enkidu. (Compare J. Friedrich, &amp;ldquo;Die hethitischen Bruchstücke des Gilgamesh-Epos,&amp;rdquo; ZA &lt;em&gt;39&lt;/em&gt; [1920-30], pp. 48f., dealing with the Hittite fragments; he established at least that it was not the bolt.) In fact, were we to have started from GE, instead of paying it a casual visit, the several &amp;ldquo;doors&amp;rdquo; with their &amp;ldquo;posts,&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;pillars,&amp;rdquo; with their &amp;ldquo;fillings&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;thresholds&amp;rdquo; would have had as much of a paralyzing effect upon us as the eye of Medusa. Meanwhile, detrimental translations are quite enough to turn the reader to stone.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>26</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/articles/Hamlets_Mill__Santillana_Dechend/26_Appendices/26/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/articles/Hamlets_Mill__Santillana_Dechend/26_Appendices/26/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Appendix 26&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;See P. Gössmann, &lt;em&gt;Planetarium Babylonicum&lt;/em&gt; (1950), 99: &amp;ldquo;ilDapinu, &amp;rsquo;the prevalent, the strong,&amp;rsquo; surname of &lt;em&gt;Nusku&lt;/em&gt; (passim), of &lt;em&gt;Nabu&lt;/em&gt;, of &lt;em&gt;Marduk&lt;/em&gt; . . . As star-god ilDapinu is the Marduk-star Jupiter, identical with dSUL. PA.E3 . . . , mulUD.AL.TAR . . . Since UD.AL.TAR can also mean the fixed star &lt;em&gt;Procyon&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;also&lt;/em&gt; ilDapinu should have this significance (Jensen, &amp;ldquo;der Furchtbare, Gewaltige (= Humbaba),&amp;rdquo; ZDMG &lt;em&gt;67&lt;/em&gt;, S. 517).&amp;rdquo; (For the identification of Nusku with Mercury, see H. and J. Lewy, &amp;ldquo;The God Nusku,&amp;rdquo; Or. &lt;em&gt;17&lt;/em&gt; [1948], pp. 146-59.) See also Gössmann, 137 s.v. mulUD.AL.TAR: &amp;ldquo;I. Akkadian as much as umu dapinu . . . the full name of Jupiter, II. Procyon. Procyon seems to have been counted with Jupiter&amp;rsquo;s hypsoma, Cancer.&amp;rdquo; See also E. Weidner, &lt;em&gt;Handbuch der Babylonischen Astronomie&lt;/em&gt; (1915), p. 25. (For Procyon as part of Cancer, see RLA &lt;em&gt;3&lt;/em&gt;, p. 77; for al. lu5, representing sometimes the zodiacal sign Cancer, otherwise Procyon, see B. van der Waerden, &amp;ldquo;The Thirty-Six Stars,&amp;rdquo; JNES &lt;em&gt;8&lt;/em&gt; [1949], p. 21.)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>27</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/articles/Hamlets_Mill__Santillana_Dechend/26_Appendices/27/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/articles/Hamlets_Mill__Santillana_Dechend/26_Appendices/27/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Appendix 27&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;See A. Oppenheim, “Mesopotamian Mythology,&amp;quot; Or. &lt;em&gt;17&lt;/em&gt; (1948), p. 40: &amp;ldquo;After Enkidu tossed towards her . . . what is euphemistically termed the &amp;lsquo;right thigh&amp;rsquo; of the bull, the goddess and her devotees performed age-old rites over the part of the bull.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;True as this statement certainly is, it does not explain much — nor is it even asked why it must be the right thigh (&lt;em&gt;imittu&lt;/em&gt;; compare H. Holma, *Die Namen der Körperteile im *&lt;em&gt;Assyrisch-Babylonischen&lt;/em&gt; [1911], pp. 131 f. See for the &amp;ldquo;euphemism&amp;rdquo; Holma, pp. 96f.).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>28</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/articles/Hamlets_Mill__Santillana_Dechend/26_Appendices/28/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/articles/Hamlets_Mill__Santillana_Dechend/26_Appendices/28/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Appendix 28&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In the GE Enkidu appears later on the stage of events than Gilgamesh. This does not entitle us to take him for the prototype of the &amp;ldquo;younger brother&amp;rdquo; (see, e.g., W. Albright, &amp;ldquo;Gilgamesh and Engidu,&amp;rdquo; JAOS &lt;em&gt;40&lt;/em&gt; [1920], pp. 312, 318). Actually, the hairy partner of the Twins, the &amp;ldquo;Dog,&amp;rdquo; is the prototype of the older one who is cheated out of his primogeniture in various ways. Esau, the hairy, is the first born; so is Hono-susori no Mikoto (&lt;em&gt;Nihongi&lt;/em&gt;, trans. by W. G. Aston [repr. 1960], pp. 92-108; K. Florenz, &lt;em&gt;Die historischen Quellen der Shinto-Religion&lt;/em&gt; [1919], pp. 204-21) who, together with his offspring, after having been passed by the Japanese &amp;ldquo;Jacob,&amp;rdquo; had to serve as &amp;ldquo;dogs,&amp;rdquo; as clowns, playactors, guardians of the imperial palace for eighty generations; at New Year and during coronation ceremonies these Hayahito had to bark three times.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>29</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/articles/Hamlets_Mill__Santillana_Dechend/26_Appendices/29/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/articles/Hamlets_Mill__Santillana_Dechend/26_Appendices/29/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Appendix 29&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We might call it Lethe, and feel happy about it, were it not for the deplorable uncertainty of Lethe&amp;rsquo;s localization, with respect to the celestial itinerary of the soul particularly. The Milky Way being as large as it is, it does not help to state that one has to look for a galactical section. Worse, it remains unclear at which occasion the souls were supposed to drink from the water of this river of forgetfulness, whether they did so shortly after having arrived in Hades or before their re incarnation, or at both times. Although the supposition of an intake of Lethe right at the entrance of Hades would deprive the underworld jurisdiction, together with the good or bad recompenses for former conduct, of its significance, both views were upheld. (See Stoll, in Roscher s.v. Lethe, col. 1957; O. Gruppe, *Griechische Mythologie und *&lt;em&gt;Religionsgeschichte&lt;/em&gt; [1906], pp. 403-405, 1036-41. On p. 760, n. 8, Gruppe quotes a passage, according to which a soul which has not yet crossed the river Lethe comes back to molest the living.)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>30</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/articles/Hamlets_Mill__Santillana_Dechend/26_Appendices/30/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/articles/Hamlets_Mill__Santillana_Dechend/26_Appendices/30/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Appendix 30&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;See P. F. Gossmann, &lt;em&gt;Planetarium Babylonicum&lt;/em&gt; (1950), 94: “mulGIR2”TAB dIshara tam-tim. Anton Deimel (&lt;em&gt;Pantheon Babylonicum&lt;/em&gt; [1914], pp. 148f.) takes mulGIR.TAB for beta delta alpha Scorpii only: &amp;lsquo;Ishara est dea quaedam partus, quae relationem habet ad Gestin anna, Adad&amp;rsquo;.&amp;quot; See also W. J. Hinke, *A New Boundary Stone of *&lt;em&gt;Nebuchadnezzar 1 from Nippur&lt;/em&gt; (1907), pp. 223, 243; A. Jeremias, HAOG (1929), pp. 223, 385; F. Hommel, &lt;em&gt;Ethnologie und Geographie des Alten Orients&lt;/em&gt; (1926), pp. 563, 770-74, 783; and D. O. Edzard, &amp;ldquo;Die Mythologie der Sumerer und Akkader,&amp;rdquo; in &lt;em&gt;Wörterbuch der Mythologie&lt;/em&gt;, vol. &lt;em&gt;1&lt;/em&gt;, P.9.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>31</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/articles/Hamlets_Mill__Santillana_Dechend/26_Appendices/31/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/articles/Hamlets_Mill__Santillana_Dechend/26_Appendices/31/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Appendix 31&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;These unknown factors, crucial as they are, resist successfully every decoding for the time being. Šu-ut abnē, &amp;ldquo;those of stone,&amp;rdquo; represent &amp;ldquo;an expression which recurs and has not been explained&amp;rdquo; (S. Langdon, &lt;em&gt;Semitic Mythology&lt;/em&gt; [1931], pp. 213f., 405). Alexander Heidel (&lt;em&gt;The Gilgamesh Epic and Old Testament Parallels&lt;/em&gt; [1963], p. 74, n. 157) remarks: &amp;ldquo;The Hittite Version has &amp;rsquo;two images of stone.&amp;rsquo; These images may perhaps have been idols of an apotropaic character enabling Urshanabi to cross the waters of death.&amp;rdquo; Speiser (&amp;ldquo;Akkadian Myths and Epics,&amp;rdquo; ANET, p. 91, n. 173) makes it &amp;ldquo;apparently stone figures of unusual properties . . . &amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>32</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/articles/Hamlets_Mill__Santillana_Dechend/26_Appendices/32/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/articles/Hamlets_Mill__Santillana_Dechend/26_Appendices/32/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Appendix 32&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Considering that removed posts or pegs, pulled-out pins, wrecked axles, and felled trees have accompanied this whole investigation as a kind of &lt;em&gt;basso ostinato&lt;/em&gt;, we cannot pass in silence over these super-important posts; considering, on the other hand, that technical details are not likely to make pleasant reading, we prefer to deal with this specimen outside the main text, although we deem it essential indeed.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The object that Irragal is tearing out is called &lt;em&gt;tarkullu&lt;/em&gt;, Sumerian DIM. GAL, which has been translated into &amp;ldquo;(Anchor-) post&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;ship&amp;rsquo;s mast&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;mooring-post&amp;rdquo; (Heidel), also &amp;ldquo;anchor&amp;rdquo; itself, and even &amp;ldquo;steering-oar&amp;rdquo; (Jensen). [1]  In the Era Epic, Era (=Irragal=Nergal), when announcing a new catastrophe, threatens that he is going to tear out the tarkullu, that he will make the ship drift off, break the steering oar so that the ship cannot land, and remove the mast and all that belongs to it. [2]&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>33</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/articles/Hamlets_Mill__Santillana_Dechend/26_Appendices/33/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/articles/Hamlets_Mill__Santillana_Dechend/26_Appendices/33/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Appendix 33&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The mere notion of the emperors sleeping makes it clear that they are expected to awake and to return one day; [1]  be it Quetzalcouatl (in the heart of the sea), Ogygian Kronos himself, or Arthur, &amp;ldquo;ruler of the lower hemisphere,&amp;rdquo; who announces in a fictitious letter &amp;ldquo;that he has come, with a host of antipodean subjects&amp;rdquo; [2]  — according to Étienne de Rouen (c. 1169; see R. S. Loomis [ed.], *Arthurian *&lt;em&gt;Literature in the Middle Ages&lt;/em&gt; [1959], p. 69); that Geoffrey of Viterbo placed Arthur straightaway into the depth of the sea has been mentioned on p. 299, n. 35.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>34</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/articles/Hamlets_Mill__Santillana_Dechend/26_Appendices/34/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/articles/Hamlets_Mill__Santillana_Dechend/26_Appendices/34/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Appendix 34&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Actually, we are up against a completely incomprehensible narrative of events which occurred during a sea voyage. The plant, according to Albright (AJSL &lt;em&gt;36&lt;/em&gt;, p. 281, n. 2) literally &amp;ldquo;thorny grapevine,&amp;rdquo; is supposed to grow in the apsu, and to be accessible by way of a &amp;ldquo;waterpipe.&amp;rdquo; This pipe, &lt;em&gt;rātu&lt;/em&gt;, however, is a conjecture right here: the word occurs only later when, after his bath in a well, and the following loss of the plant, Gilgamesh complains bitterly about his frustration, i.e., about having obtained a boon for the &amp;ldquo;earth lion&amp;rdquo; instead of for himself. The &amp;ldquo;earth lion,&amp;rdquo; identified with the thievish serpent, is assumed in its turn to live &amp;ldquo;in a well which communicated with the apsu&amp;rdquo; (Albright, AJSL &lt;em&gt;35&lt;/em&gt;, p. 194). It is then (GE &lt;em&gt;11&lt;/em&gt;.298) that the hero says: &amp;ldquo;When I opened the water-pipe and (. . .) the gear, I found that which has been placed as a sign for me: I shall withdraw and leave the boat on the shore&amp;rdquo; (Speiser trans., ANET, pp. 96f.). Heidel makes it: &amp;ldquo;When I opened the . . . I have found something that (has been set) for a sign unto me; I will withdraw!&amp;rdquo; Instead of that &amp;ldquo;sign,&amp;rdquo; Albright (RA &lt;em&gt;16&lt;/em&gt;, pp. 17 Sf.) recognized a flood rising out of the &lt;em&gt;pipe&lt;/em&gt; (if so, why does Gilgamesh talk about it only after his bath in the well?): &amp;ldquo;When I opened the water-pipe, I overturned the cover (?). Let not the sea rise to my side, b(efo)re (it) let me retire&amp;rdquo;; and so did Ungnad-Gressmann (pp. 63f.) and Schmoekel (p. 111). From this passage the translators derive the occurrence of the word &lt;em&gt;rātu&lt;/em&gt; in the earlier passage, where Gilgamesh dives for the plant. Speiser alone [1]  refers to another occasion where the word is used, and it is a decisive occasion; namely, in the (wrongly called) &amp;ldquo;Eridu creation story&amp;rdquo; (v. II), where it is told that before anything was created and when all lands were sea (tamtim), then &amp;ldquo;the spring which is in the sea was a water pipe; then Eridu was made, Esagila was built&amp;rdquo; (Heidel, &lt;em&gt;The Babylonian Genesis&lt;/em&gt; [1963], pp. 61f.). Sayce (ERE &lt;em&gt;4&lt;/em&gt;, p. 129) makes it a &amp;ldquo;current&amp;rdquo; within the sea; with Jensen (&lt;em&gt;Assyrisch-Babylonische Mythen und Epen&lt;/em&gt; [1909], p. 41) it is a &amp;ldquo;Wasserbecken&amp;rdquo;; with Ebeling (AOTAT, pp. 130f.) a &amp;ldquo;Schoepfrinne.&amp;rdquo; Considering that Eridu is Canopus, and Esagila is &amp;quot; l-Iku&amp;quot; the Pegasus-square between the two Fishes that ruled the hibernal solstice during the Age of Gemini — this particular &lt;em&gt;rātu&lt;/em&gt; seems to have been the connection between the two depths of the sea, between Pisces as the depth of the salt sea and Canopus as the depth of the apsu, the sweet water ocean.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>35</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/articles/Hamlets_Mill__Santillana_Dechend/26_Appendices/35/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/articles/Hamlets_Mill__Santillana_Dechend/26_Appendices/35/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Appendix 35&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;There are a few dim and blurred signals to be received from the regions of Styx flowing, as we have heard, in sight of the celestial South Pole. Photius [1]  tells us about Hyllos, son of Herakles, who had a small horn growing out of the left side of his head, and how Epopeus [2]  of Sikyon broke off this horn, after having killed Hyllos in a duel, fetched Styx water with this horn, and became king of the country. Why should he have procured this much dreaded water, if it did not enable him to become king?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>36</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/articles/Hamlets_Mill__Santillana_Dechend/26_Appendices/36/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/articles/Hamlets_Mill__Santillana_Dechend/26_Appendices/36/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Appendix 36&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;For related conceptions in Rome, see Festus (128M, BT [1965], p. 115): &amp;ldquo;*Manalem *&lt;em&gt;fontem&lt;/em&gt; dici pro eo, quod aqua ex eo semper manet . . . &lt;em&gt;Manalem lapidem&lt;/em&gt; putabant esse ostium Ord, per quod animae inferorum ad superos manarent, qui dicuntur manes.&amp;rdquo; (Cf. F. Bömer, &amp;ldquo;Der sogenannte Lapis Manalis,&amp;rdquo; ARW &lt;em&gt;33&lt;/em&gt; [1936], p. 281; Kroll, RE &lt;em&gt;16&lt;/em&gt; s.v. mundus, cols. 56 If. To prevent one-sided conceptions from stealing into the picture, see also Festus 156M, p. 147: &amp;ldquo;Manes di ab auguribus vocabantur, quod eos per omnia manere credebant, eosque deos &lt;em&gt;superos atque inferos&lt;/em&gt; dicebant.)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>37</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/articles/Hamlets_Mill__Santillana_Dechend/26_Appendices/37/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/articles/Hamlets_Mill__Santillana_Dechend/26_Appendices/37/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Appendix 37&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A sidelight falls upon the notions connected with the stag by Hora pollo&amp;rsquo;s statement concerning the Egyptian writing of &amp;ldquo;A long space of time: A Stag&amp;rsquo;s horns grow out each year. A picture of them means a long space of time.&amp;rdquo; [1]  Chairemon (hieroglyph no. 15, quoted by Tzetzes) made it shorter: &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;eniautos elaphos&lt;/em&gt;.&amp;rdquo; Louis Keimer, stressing the absence of stags in Egypt, pointed to the Oryx (&lt;em&gt;Capra Nubiana&lt;/em&gt;) as the appropriate &amp;ldquo;ersatz,&amp;rdquo; [2]  whose head was, indeed, used for writing the word &lt;em&gt;rnp&lt;/em&gt; = year, eventually in &amp;ldquo;the Lord of the Year,&amp;rdquo; a well-known title of Ptah. [3]  Rare as this modus of writing the word seems to have been — the &lt;em&gt;Wörterbuch der Aegyptischen Sprache&lt;/em&gt; (eds. Erman and Grapow), vol. &lt;em&gt;2&lt;/em&gt;, pp. 429-33, does not even mention this variant — it is worth considering (as is every subject dealt with by Keimer), the more so as Chairemon [4]  continues his list by offering as number &lt;em&gt;16&lt;/em&gt;: eniautos phoinix,&amp;quot; i.e., a different span of time, the much-discussed &amp;ldquo;Phoenix-period&amp;rdquo; (ca. 500 years). There are numerous Egyptian words for &amp;ldquo;the year,&amp;rdquo; and the same goes for other ancient languages. Thus, we propose to understand &lt;em&gt;eniautos&lt;/em&gt; as the particular cycle belonging to the respective character under discussion: the mere word &lt;em&gt;eniautos&lt;/em&gt; (&amp;ldquo;in itself,&amp;rdquo; &lt;em&gt;en heauto&lt;/em&gt;; Plato&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;Cratylus&lt;/em&gt; 410D) does not say more than just this. It seems unjustifiable to render the word as &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;the&lt;/em&gt; year&amp;rdquo; as is done regularly nowadays, for the simple reason that there is no such thing as &lt;em&gt;the&lt;/em&gt; year; to begin with, there is the tropical year and sidereal year, neither of them being of the same length as the Sothic year. Actually, the methods of Maya, Chinese, and Indian time reckoning should teach us to take much greater care of the words we use. The Indians, for instance, reckoned with five different sorts of “year,&amp;quot; among which one of 378 days, for which A. Weber did not have any explanation. [5]  That number of days, however, represents the synodical revolution of Saturn. Nothing is gained by the violence with which the Ancient Egyptian astronomical system is forced into the presupposed primitive frame.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>38</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/articles/Hamlets_Mill__Santillana_Dechend/26_Appendices/38/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/articles/Hamlets_Mill__Santillana_Dechend/26_Appendices/38/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Appendix 38&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;See RV &lt;em&gt;10&lt;/em&gt;, 46.2, ed. K. Geldner (1951); cf. V. Rydberg, &lt;em&gt;Teutonic Mythologie&lt;/em&gt; (1907), p. 587. Geldner, vague as ever, spells it “der Gewässer Behausung.&amp;quot; Agni, however, is a title, and the &lt;em&gt;Rigveda&lt;/em&gt; stresses time and again that three Agnis already have gone away, &amp;ldquo;consumed&amp;rdquo; by the “sacrificial service.&amp;ldquo;Agni, too, is not only coming from the confluence of the rivers like Gibil, but is also born in the &amp;ldquo;highest sky&amp;rdquo; (RV &lt;em&gt;6&lt;/em&gt;.8.2): “Im höchsten Himmel geboren wachte Agni über die (Opfer) regeln als ihr Hüter. Der Klugsinnige mass den Luftraum aus.&amp;rdquo; In fact, he has three birthplaces as a rule, in the &amp;ldquo;three worlds.&amp;rdquo; (We have mentioned already that one of the Agnis had &amp;ldquo;seven mothers,&amp;rdquo; like Heimdal.)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>39</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/articles/Hamlets_Mill__Santillana_Dechend/26_Appendices/39/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/articles/Hamlets_Mill__Santillana_Dechend/26_Appendices/39/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Appendix 39&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Excursus on Gilgamesh&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;There are many points from which to start new trips of exploration into the Gilgamesh Epic, once it is  conceded that reasonable questions have to be asked. Among the many we single out two, without intending to &amp;ldquo;get at the bottom of the matter&amp;rdquo;; the first concerns the &amp;ldquo;ferry-man,&amp;rdquo; the second concerns &amp;ldquo;trees.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Face to face with the ferryman Urshanabi, a kind of personified &lt;em&gt;me&lt;/em&gt; who was dragged away from the &amp;ldquo;confluence of the rivers&amp;rdquo; to check the proper measures of Uruk, it can hardly be taken for a farfetched idea that we ask for comparative &amp;ldquo;individuals&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;places&amp;rdquo; in other Mesopotamian texts. There is, indeed, no need for a frantic search: the Enuma elish offers us an equally decisive item from which depends the whole skeleton map, namely &lt;em&gt;Nibiru&lt;/em&gt; (or &lt;em&gt;nēbēru&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
