<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;मानसतरङ्गिणीकृल्-लेखाः on ज्योतिषे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/hindu/precession_records/equinoctial_records/articles/MT/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;मानसतरङ्गिणीकृल्-लेखाः on ज्योतिषे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 15 Jan 2007 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/hindu/precession_records/equinoctial_records/articles/MT/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>The crashing doors</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/hindu/precession_records/equinoctial_records/articles/MT/2007-01-15_the-crashing-doors/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Jan 2007 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/hindu/precession_records/equinoctial_records/articles/MT/2007-01-15_the-crashing-doors/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2007/01/15/the-crashing-doors/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This note should be considered along with our earlier notes on the topic:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2006/11/26/the-crossing-of-ashmanvati/&#34;&gt;The crossing of ashmanvatI&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2006/11/21/the-path-of-fire/&#34;&gt;The path of fire&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;von Dechend and De Santillana while flippantly referring to “the Hindu verbiage” repeatedly find themselves needing to take recourse to the same “Hindu verbiage” to adduce evidence for their conjectures. But they must be credited for noting the significance of mythic motifs that were previously overlooked by most. One point they just allude to, but fail to expand upon is the issue of crashing doors. What exactly are these crashing doors in the language of myth? Based on some myths the above authors conclude that it must have some connection to the frame of time but fail to clarify this explicitly, especially in connection to their central theme — the mythic accounts of the precession of the axis.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The path of fire</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/hindu/precession_records/equinoctial_records/articles/MT/2006-11-21_the-path-of-fire/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Nov 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/hindu/precession_records/equinoctial_records/articles/MT/2006-11-21_the-path-of-fire/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2006/11/21/the-path-of-fire/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In one of the most remarkable books written in all times de Santillana and von Dechend state:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“Fire is the equinoctial colure, the great circle that passes through the celestial poles intersecting the ecliptic at the point where it intersects the celestial equator.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;They also noted the importance of the fire sticks and fire drill in this symbolism. They indeed had seen the truth. One who know this will understand the hymns of sauchIka agni.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Finnish Epic</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/hindu/precession_records/equinoctial_records/articles/MT/2005-09-05_the-finnish-epic/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Sep 2005 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/hindu/precession_records/equinoctial_records/articles/MT/2005-09-05_the-finnish-epic/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2005/09/05/the-finnish-epic/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Kalevala is the only well-preserved piece of mythology Uralic people. A few fragments of the tales of other shamanic peoples of this group exist, but none in a complete epic as the Kalevala, which was rescued from extinction by the Finnish nationalist Loenrot. A number of ancient mythic motifs (often astronomical) might be recognized.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1) Ilmatar the progenitor of the universe breaks an egg which gives rise to heaven and earth. The yolk become the sun and the white the moon. (Compare with the hiraNyagarbha motif)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;2) A giant oak grows that blocks out the path of the sun and there is no light. A tiny man emerges from the sea. He grows into giant and confidentally fells the tree with three blows of his axe. The sun stars shining again and there is growth of plants (Note the similarity with the viShNu mythic motifs)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;3) The fantastic fir tree that emerges due to the spells of Vainaemoienen with the Big Bear (Ursa Major) and the moon on its branches. The smith hero Ilmarinen climbs the tree and is transported by a whirlwind to a different world (The tree as world axis motif again. This may be the new axis emerging after old one was cut down by the one who grew to be the giant).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>indra stuti</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/hindu/precession_records/equinoctial_records/articles/MT/2005-05-30_indra-stuti/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 May 2005 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/hindu/precession_records/equinoctial_records/articles/MT/2005-05-30_indra-stuti/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2005/05/30/indra-stuti/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The indra stuti is another hymn in the pauShya section of the adiparavan of the mahAbhArata (1.3.150-1.3.153 in the critical Poona edition of the mahAbhArata) which appears to be a composition of the “intermediate period”. However it bears certain distinctive features that differentiate if from the ashvina stuti and suggest that it is even closer to the transitional period than the former. It appears in the same frame story as the ashvina stuti of upamanyu: veda of the bhArgava clan was a student of Ayodo dhaumya. After he had gone through his own trial he was granted mastery over the veda and the dharmasutras by Ayodo dhaumya. He then founded his own school and had his own student also of the bhArgava clan, utta~Nka. Once the kShatriyas pauShya and janamejaya invited veda to serve as the brahmA priest in their sacrifice. veda left, instructing utta~Nka to take full care of his household. When he was away veda’s wife moved by amorous arousal asked utta~Nka to have sex with her, but he firmly refused. veda on his return was pleased with the conduct of utta~Nka and graduated him, and asked to proceed on his own. He insisted that he would need to pay veda his parting fee though veda asked him to take it easy. Pressed thus veda asked utta~Nka to ask his wife for whatever she wanted and provide that as the fee. She demanded the earrings of the queen of pauShya. So utta~Nka went on his quest. On the way he saw a gigantic bull and mighty man tending it. The man ordered utta~Nka to eat the dung of the bull and drink its urine. utta~Nka refused but the mighty man commanded utta~Nka to do stating that his own teacher had done the same &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. After partaking of the unclean material, utta~Nka washed his mouth, purified himself and went to pauShya and asked him for his queen’s earrings. The kShatriya asked utta~Nka to go and ask her directly in her apartment. He went there but the queen was not in sight. He came back and asked pauShya why that was so. The king told him that he was impure due to improper purification after his meal and the queen did not give audience to unclean souls. So utta~Nka again rigorously purified himself and went to the queen and made the request for her earrings that were desired by veda’s wife. She gladly gave that to him but stated that he would have to safe guard them from takShaka the nAga who also desired them. The king then asked him to have shrAddha lunch before he left as he was a learned brahmin. It turned out that the lunch was cold and defiled by the hair of a woman. Getting furious utta~Nka cursed the king with blindness. The pauShya was taken aback by the curse and in retaliated by cursing the brahmin with sterility. utta~Nka objected by stating that it was king who had offended him first and showed him the hair and cold food. The king accepted that there had been a problem with the food, so the brahmin stated that pauShya’s blindness would eventually be cured. The king was unable to withdraw his curse but utta~Nka stated that he would eventually smother the curse with his own brahman power as he was not on the wrong.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Wheel of earth - agni</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/hindu/precession_records/equinoctial_records/articles/MT/wheel_of_earth_agni/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/hindu/precession_records/equinoctial_records/articles/MT/wheel_of_earth_agni/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;mUrdhAnaM divo aratim pR^ithivyA&lt;br&gt;&#xA;vaishvAnaram R^ita A jAtam agnim |&lt;br&gt;&#xA;kaviM samrAjam atithiM janAnAm&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Asann A pAtraM janayanta devAH ||&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;One of the awe-inspiring motifs in shruti is that of agni at the head of heaven, as the wheel of earth &amp;amp; as the cup from which the gods feed&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The head of Heaven, the spoked wheel of Earth,&lt;br&gt;&#xA;agni vaishvAnara born in the natural law,&lt;br&gt;&#xA;the seer, the emperor, the guest of the folks,&lt;br&gt;&#xA;As a cup for the mouth, the gods generated.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
