<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;काक-सुभाषः on ज्योतिषे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/kAka-subhAShaH/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;काक-सुभाषः on ज्योतिषे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/kAka-subhAShaH/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Sun&#39;s orbit in brAhmaNas</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/kAka-subhAShaH/solar_orbit_brAhmaNas_subhASh_kAk/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/kAka-subhAShaH/solar_orbit_brAhmaNas_subhASh_kAk/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;title&#34;&gt;Title&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Indian Journal of History of Science, 33(3)1998&lt;br&gt;&#xA;THE SUN’S ORBIT IN THE BRAHMAṇAS&lt;br&gt;&#xA;SUBHASH C. Kak*&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Department of Electrical &amp;amp; Computer Engineering, Louisiana State University, Baton Rouge, LA 70803-5901, USA&lt;br&gt;&#xA;(Received 30 June 1997; after revision 12 January 1998)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;intro&#34;&gt;Intro&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We show that the Brāhmaṇas recognize that the speed of the sun varies with the seasons. The year-long rites of the Brāhmaṇas were organized with the summer solstice (viṣuvant) as the middle point. These rites counted the days upto the solstice and in the latter half of the year, and there is an asymmetry in the two counts. This is an astronomical parameter, which had hitherto escaped notice, that allows us to date the rites to a period much earlier than has been assumed. A fire altar described in the śatapatha Brāhmaṇa represents the motion of the sun and this motion is asymmetric with respect to the earth. The concept of a force field associated with the sun, likened to the wind in the śatapatha Brāhmaṇa, appears to be the basic idea which led to the notions of the mandocca and śīghrocca cycles which are fundamental to the later Siddhāntic astronomy. Key Words: Ancient astronomy, Mandocca, śatapatha Brāhmaṇa, śīghrocca, The sun.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Temple Cosmology- kAk</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/kAka-subhAShaH/temple_astronomy_subhash_kak/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/kAka-subhAShaH/temple_astronomy_subhash_kak/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;intro&#34;&gt;Intro&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Presented at Vaastu Kaushal: International Symposium on Science and Technology in Ancient Indian Monuments, New Delhi, November 16-17, 2002.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Space and Cosmology in the Hindu Temple&lt;br&gt;&#xA;by Subhash Kak&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;According to the Sthapatya Veda (the Indian tradition of architecture), the temple and the town should mirror the cosmos. The temple architecture and the city plan are, therefore, related in their conception. Volwahsen (2001) has remarked on the continuity in the Indian architectural tradition. The Harappan cities have a grid plan, just as is recommended in the Vedic manuals. The square shape represents the heavens, with the four directions representing the cardinal directions as well as the two solstices and the equinoxes of the sun’s orbit.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
