<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;मानसतरङ्गिणीकृल्-लेखाः on ज्योतिषे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/hindu/articles/MT/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;मानसतरङ्गिणीकृल्-लेखाः on ज्योतिषे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 15 Sep 2005 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/hindu/articles/MT/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Nebra Star Disc and Indo-European Archaeoastronomy</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/hindu/articles/MT/2005-09-15_nebra-star-disc-and-indo-european-archaeoastronomy/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Sep 2005 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/hindu/articles/MT/2005-09-15_nebra-star-disc-and-indo-european-archaeoastronomy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2005/09/15/nebra-star-disc-and-indo-european-archaeoastronomy/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Nebra Star Disc &lt;a href=&#34;http://picasa.google.com/blogger/&#34;&gt;&lt;figure class=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &lt;a href=&#34;https://i1.wp.com/photos1.blogger.com/pbp.gif&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&#xA;        &lt;img src=&#34;https://i1.wp.com/photos1.blogger.com/pbp.gif&#34; alt=&#34;Posted by Picasa&#34; title=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &#xA;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://photos1.blogger.com/img/133/1300/640/stardisk_disc.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;figure class=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &lt;a href=&#34;https://i2.wp.com/photos1.blogger.com/img/133/1300/400/stardisk_disc.jpg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&#xA;        &lt;img src=&#34;https://i2.wp.com/photos1.blogger.com/img/133/1300/400/stardisk_disc.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &#xA;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The astronomy of the Indo-Europeans has always been frowned up by the “Western experts”. They like to tell us that the Indo-Europeans were a primitive lot with not much astronomy to talk about. Everything the Indo-Europeans got is from the Middle Eastern civilizations of the Biblical milieu- Assyria, Egypt, Sumeria, Babylonia, Mesopotamia is the root of all astronomical and mathematical knowledge- they like the blather on. Hindu borrowed from the Middle East to produce the primitive vedAnga jyotiSha they tell us. However, a study of the Hindu and the Greek astronomy while revealing several regional developments still have a basic underlying core that was most probably derived from the Indo-European past. The example include the name of the constellation Orion and the name of the Vedic sacrifice AghrayaNa, whose performance was marked originally by the equinoctical position of Orion. The Hindus developed the 27/28 nakShatra system. The origins of this are murky but clearly the “28th” nakShatra abhijit was used to mark the vishuvAn day at a certain point and dropped later after the axial precession had pushed it away from that point. This and other points suggest that the Hindus have been using the nakShatra sytem from at least before 2700 BC, suggesting a long history of their independent developments after branching from the Greeks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Johannes Kepler</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/hindu/articles/MT/2005-08-14_johannes-kepler/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Aug 2005 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/hindu/articles/MT/2005-08-14_johannes-kepler/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2005/08/14/johannes-kepler/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Johannes Kepler has always been a major source of inspiration. He lived a difficult life, full of personal troubles and disease, yet he was remarkably productive and innovative. This was a clear sign of his pure genius.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In 1596 he announced his support for the Copernican model in the book Mysterium Cosmographicum and showed its explanative power. It also contained his false polyhedral model of the solar system.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In 1604 he and his student Jan Brunowski discovered a supernova in Ophiuchus, which went to attain the magnitude of -2.5. Kepler provided the first description of the light curve of a supernova in the pamphlet De Stella Nova, observing it constantly for over and year till it fell below Mag 6.6&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Indians:a bunch of idiots?</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/hindu/articles/MT/2003-09-28_indiansa-bunch-of-idiots/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Sep 2003 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/hindu/articles/MT/2003-09-28_indiansa-bunch-of-idiots/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2003/09/28/indiansa-bunch-of-idiots/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A gentleman called Pingree and his lackey called Plofker would like us to believe that the Indians were a bunch of idiots till the benign rule of the white man brought them to light. In essence what they tell us by means of writing several prolix papers and using sophisticated jargon is the same as what Mr. Macaulay briskly delivered in his minute. “The vast accumulations of Indian literature is worth less than a shelf of books in a good European library.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
