<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;Tilak: Orion on ज्योतिषे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/hindu/articles/tilak-orion/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;Tilak: Orion on ज्योतिषे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/hindu/articles/tilak-orion/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 Front matter</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/hindu/articles/tilak-orion/01_Front_matter/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/hindu/articles/tilak-orion/01_Front_matter/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;THE ORION Or Researches into the Antiquity of the Vedas.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;TILAK B.G.&#xA;Vol. 48 COSMO PUBLICATIONS&lt;br&gt;&#xA;First Published 1893&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>02 PREFACE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/hindu/articles/tilak-orion/02_PREFACE/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/hindu/articles/tilak-orion/02_PREFACE/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;SOME explanation may be necessary for the publication of an essay on the antiquity of the Vedas by one whose professional work lies in a different direction. About four years ago, as I was reading the Bhagavad Gita, it occurred lo me that we might derive important conclusions from the statement of Krishna that &amp;ldquo;he was Margashirsha of the months.&amp;rdquo; This led me to inquire into the primitive Vedic calendar, and the result of four years&amp;rsquo; labour is now placed before the public. The essay was originally written for the Ninth Oriental Congress held in London last year. But it was found too large to be inserted in the proceedings wherein its summary alone is now included. I have had therefore to publish it separately, and in doing so I have taken the opportunity of incorporating into it such additions, alterations and modifications, as were suggested by further thought and discussion.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>03 CONTENTS</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/hindu/articles/tilak-orion/03_CONTENTS/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/hindu/articles/tilak-orion/03_CONTENTS/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;CHAPTER PAGES.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;I. Introduction 1- 9&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;II. Sacrifice alias the Year &amp;hellip; 10-&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;III. The Kr̥ttikas&amp;hellip;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;IV. āgrahāyaṇa &amp;hellip; 61 – 96&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;V. The Antelope&amp;rsquo;s head  96-128&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;VI. Orion and his Belt &amp;ndash;156 &amp;hellip; 107-197&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;VII, r̥bhus and Vriṣākapi&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;VIII. Conclusion 198.-220 &amp;hellip; 291-327&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Appendix&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>04 INTRODUCTION</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/hindu/articles/tilak-orion/04_INTRODUCTION/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/hindu/articles/tilak-orion/04_INTRODUCTION/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;contents&#34;&gt;Contents&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Importance of ascertaining the Age of the Vedas&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Linguistic method, Its defects&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Astronomical method - Its difficulties unduly magnified&#xA;-Views of European and Native scholars examined.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;importance-of-ascertaining-the-age-of-the-vedas&#34;&gt;Importance of ascertaining the Age of the Vedas&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;THE VEDA is the oldest of the books that we now possess, and it is generally admitted &amp;ldquo;that for a study of man, or if you like, for a study of Aryan humanity, there is aothing in the world equal in importance with it.&amp;rdquo;* +++(• India : what it can teach us ? p. 112. The references through. out are to the Arst edition of this work.)+++ There is no other book which carries us so near the beginning of the Aryan civilization, if not the absolute beginning of all things, as maintained by the Hindu theologians; and the importance of ascertaining even approximately the age when the oldest of the Vedic R̥ṣis, like the classical Valmiki, may have been inspired to unconsciously give utterance to a Vedic verse, cannot therefore be overrated.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>05 SACRIFICE alias THE YEAR</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/hindu/articles/tilak-orion/05_SACRIFICE_alias_THE_YEAR/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/hindu/articles/tilak-orion/05_SACRIFICE_alias_THE_YEAR/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;contents&#34;&gt;Contents&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Primitive caleadar co-eval with the sacrificial system&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Prajāpati= Yajña=Saṁvatsara&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Civil or sāvana days.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Sāvana and lunar months&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Lunar and solar years&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Intercalcary days and months in Vedic times&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Solar year was  sidereal and not tropical&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Old beginning of the year and the sacrifice.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The Viṣuvān day&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Vernal equinox and winter solstice&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Uttarāyaṇa and Dakshiṇāyana&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Devayāna and Pitr̥yāna&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Their original meaning&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Bhāskara charya&amp;rsquo;s mistake about the day of the Devas&#xA;-The two year beginnings were subsequently utilised for different purposes.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;intro&#34;&gt;Intro&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It is necessary, in the first place, to see what contrivances were adopted by the ancient Aryas for the measurement and division of time. The present Indian system has been thus described by Professor Whitney in his notes to the Sūrya Siddhānta (1. 13, notes):&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>06 THE KRTTIKAS</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/hindu/articles/tilak-orion/06_THE_KRTTIKAS/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/hindu/articles/tilak-orion/06_THE_KRTTIKAS/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;contents&#34;&gt;Contents&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Nakṣatras in old Vedic times generally mean asterisms and not zodiacal portions&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The present and the older position of the solstices.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;In later works&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;in Vedānga Jyotiṣa -An objection against its antiquity examined&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Passages in the Taittirīya Saṁhitā and Brāhamaṇa&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The Kr̥ttikās head the Nakṣatras&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Deva and Yama Nakṣatras. Their real meaning&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Taittirīya Saṁhitā vii. 4, 8. discussed.&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Jaimini&amp;rsquo;s and Shabara&amp;rsquo;s interpretation of the same&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Conclusions deducible therefrom&#xA;-Winter solstice in Māgha&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Vernal equinox in the Kr̥ttikas&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The age of the saṁhitā - 2350 B, C.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Bentley&amp;rsquo;s arguments and views criticised.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;nakṣatras-as-asterisms&#34;&gt;Nakṣatras as asterisms&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;WE HAVE seen that the ancient Aryas originally commenced their year, which was luni-solar and  sidereal, with the vernal equinox, and that when the beginning was changed to the winter solstice both the reckonings were kept up, the one for sacrificial and the other for civil purposes. Let us now examine if there is any reliable evidence to show that the Vedic priests made any corrections in the calendar when by the precession of the equinoxes the cycle of seasons gradually fell back. All our present calendars are prepared on the supposition that the vernal equinox still coincides with the end of Revati and our equmeration of the Nakshatras begins with Ashvini, though the equinox has now receded about 18° from Revatī. It has been shown by Prof. Whitney (Sūrya Siddhānta, viii., 9 note, p. 311) that the above position of the vernal equinox may be assumed to be true at about 490 A. D. Taking this as the probable date of the introduction of the present system, we have now to see if we can trace back the position of the vernal equinox amongst the fixed circle of stars. The question, so far, as one antecedent stage is concerned, has been thoroughly discussed by Colebrooke, Bentley, Max Mūller, Weber, Whitney, Biot, and other scholars : and I shall therefore only summarise what they have said, noting the points where I differ from them.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>07 AGRAHAYANA</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/hindu/articles/tilak-orion/07_AGRAHAYANA/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/hindu/articles/tilak-orion/07_AGRAHAYANA/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Fhālgunt full-moon, the new year&amp;rsquo;s night-Sāyaṇa&amp;rsquo;s explanation un.&#xA;satisfactory&amp;ndash;Phālguna could not be a Vasaota month-Two lold character of the seasons, lunar and solar, superfluous-Discus. sion of a passage in bhushruta-Bhāskara Bhaṭṭa&amp;rsquo;s explanation. Winter solstice on the full moon in Phaiguda-The position of other cardinal points Veroal quinox in Mr̥gaśiras. Agrahdyant. Native Lexicographers&amp;rsquo; explanation of the word-Grammatically objectionable- Its real meaning according to Panini -Erroneous rank of Margashirsha amongst months according to the Bhagavad Gita and imara-Margashirsha could not have been the first month of the solistitial or the equinoctial year. It leads to the libration of the equinoxes-Possible reason of the libration theory&amp;ndash;Mr̥gaśiras&amp;mdash;Agrahayaga or the first Nakṣatra in the year-Mula, its primary meanirg-Evidence of the summer solstice occuring in Bhidrapada-Origin of the annual feasts to the manes amongst Hindus and l&amp;rsquo;arsis.&amp;ndash;Comparison of the primitive Hindu and Parsi calender-summary of results.&#xA;The passage from the Taittirīya Saṁhitā quoted in the last chapter states that the Chitra and Phalguni full-moons were the beginnings of the year, which then commenced with the winter solstice in the month of Māgha. The words used in the original are Chilra-purna-masa and Phalguni pūrna masa and these must be understood to denote, not the Chaitra and the Phālguna mooths, whether sidereal and synodical, as Prof. Weber seems to have, in one case, sup posed, but the full moon days in each of these munths. This is evident from the fact that these have been recom. mended as alternative times for the commencement of the satra in opposition to the Ekashtaka day. In the case of the Phaiguni.purna-masa we are further told that Viṣūvān&#xA;counted from that time falls during the rainy season, and it is impossible to suppose that Viṣūvan can be counted from a mouth. The whole context, therefore, shows that it is a discussion as to the particular day best suited to commence the yearly sacrifice, and that Chitrd.pūrn a-misia and Phal. guni-pūrna masa must mean the days when the moon is full near the asterisms of Chitra and Phalgupi. In the Tāndya Brāhmaṇa* Phalguni-purna.māsa is rendered by Phalguni and Jaimini has paraphrased Chritā piirna-masa by Chaitri and Phalguni and Chaitri, according to Piṇini (iv. 2. 3), are the names of days. These interpretations have been accept ed by all the Mimānsakas including Sāyaṇa, and we may do the same especially as there are several passages in the Taittirīya saṁhitā where piirna-māsa is used in a similar sense.t&#xA;But why should the Chitrā and the Phalgunī full-moon be called the beginnings of the year? Sāyaṇa thinks that they were so described because they occurred during Vasanta or the first of the seasons. I But the explanation does not appear satisfactory. I have previously shown that according to all astronomical works Shishira commenced with the winter solstice, and that the three seasons of Shi&#xA;* See the passages quoted in the last chapter,&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>08 THE ANTELOPE&#39;S HEAD</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/hindu/articles/tilak-orion/08_THE_ANTELOPES_HEAD/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/hindu/articles/tilak-orion/08_THE_ANTELOPES_HEAD/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Msigashiras-Its oldest form and position-Identification of Robint&#xA;and Rudra, etc.Plutarch on the non-Egyptien origin of Orion, Canis and Ursa-Methods of interpreting mythological legends&#xA;Storm and dawn theories. Their insufficiency-Knowledge of the heavens amongst the ancient Aryks-Heaven and Hell, Devayāna and Pitr̥yaga-Joined by equinoxes, the gates of Heaven&amp;ndash;Dogs at these gates-Kerberos and Yama&amp;rsquo;s dogs The Chinvat bridge and the dogs that guard it-Their identi fication with Canis Major and Canis Minor, when the vernal equinox was in Orion-Celestial river aod Charon&amp;rsquo;s boat Comparison of the R̥gveda and the Avesta dog8Sarama and Shupāsirau-Dog (star) commencing the year-Heliacal and acronycal rising of Orion in apring and autumn-Vishnu and Rudra-Kerberos and Orthros&amp;ndash;The legend of Namuchi alias Vr̥tra-His decapitation by Indra at the gates of heaven, wbere: Orthros is stationed-Represented by the &amp;quot; antelope&amp;rsquo;s head&amp;quot; in the heavens, Vr̥itra being = Mriga-Compact betweco lodra and Namuchi-Watery foam-Its identification, with the Milky Way-Legends of Rudra-How he killed Prajāpati Yajña or Sacrifice at the begining of the year-Shulagava sacr.fice-Tistrya = tri stri, the three star belt of Orion - The Hindu Trinity, Dattārreya-His representation in the sky.&#xA;The part of the heavens, which contains the Nakṣatras, we have now lo consider, is the most attractive and interesting in the celestial sphere. Even a casual observer on a clear night is sure to be attracted by its splendid appearance, and the rising of the sun in this portion of the heavens at the beginning the year must have rendered it doubly attractive to the ancient Aryan observers. It contains no less than five stars of the first magnitude including Sirius and a number of the second, with the stream of the Milky Way passing through them. Here there was a fine field for the virgin imagigation of the ancient poets and&#xA;V.]&#xA;THE ANTELOPE&amp;rsquo;S HEAD. 97 priests and the numerous legends that exist in almost all the sections of the Aryan race about this portion of the heavens fully show that they did not fail to make use of this brilliant opportunity. I intend to examine some of these legends in this chapter with a view to see what corroborative evidence we may get therefrom. If we can more naturally and easily explain the legends that relate to this part of the heavens on the present theory, than has hitherto been done, we may fairly conclude that we have rightly interpreted the passages - from the Brāhmaṇas; if not, we shall have either to revise our assumption or lo give it up entirely. But before we do so we must, as far as possible, try to identify the asterisms and determine their forms as described in the ancient works.&#xA;We shall first take up Mr̥gaśiras or Agrahayani according to Amarasinha. The very name of the Nakṣatra, which means &amp;ldquo;an antelope&amp;rsquo;s head,&amp;rdquo; • suggests the figure of the asterism But the constellation consists of so many stars that it is very difficult to say which of ihem might have suggested the name. I may here remark that the doctrine of &amp;quot; Yogatārās” or the junction stars cannot be supposed to have been developed in the early days we are here&#xA;* I may here, once for all remark that though I have translated the word Mr̥gaśiras by the &amp;ldquo;antelope&amp;rsquo;s head,&amp;rdquo; I do not mean to imply that Mriya necessarily meant &amp;ldquo;an antelope&amp;rdquo; in the Vedic literature. It has been suggested that Mriga may mean &amp;ldquo;a bullock &amp;quot; or some other animal like it. It may, but we have nothing to do with it, inasmucb as the word Mriga itself is still used in the Sanskrit literature to denote the constellation. My translation of Mr̥gaśiras must therefore be considered provisional, remembering that tbough it may change yet the argument in this chapter will still remaiu unaltered.&#xA;speaking of. I do not mean to say that single stars may not have been or were not specifically named. But whereever a constellation is spoken of, it is more probable that the whole group was intended, as in the case of the Seven Bears or the Krittikas; and hence the determination of the junction stars, as given in later astronomical works, cannot help us beyond indicating where we are to look for the constellation described in the old works. For instance, if we take Irigashiras we are told that one of he three small stars in the head of Orion is the junction star. This means that we must look for Mr̥gaśiras in the constellation of Orion. But how can these three stars give us the figure of an antelope&amp;rsquo;s head? The three stars are so close that between them. selves they give us no figure at all. It is, however, suggested that the (wo stars in the shoulders and two in the knees of Orion give us the four feet of the antelope, whose head may then be said to correspond with the three stars in the Orion&amp;rsquo;s head. lo short it is the antelope&amp;rsquo;s head in the same way as it is the head of Orion, But besides being open to the objection da: this gives us the head and not the form of an antelope&amp;rsquo;s head, the explanation presupposes that the whole of the antelope is in the heavens; and if ārdrā be correctly identified with the star in the right shoulder of Orion we shall have also to include this star in the four feet of the antelope. The old Vedic works, however, seem to lay down that it was the head of the antelope and not the antelope itself, that was transplanted to the heavens. Referring to the legend of Rudra piercing Prajāpati, Sāyaṇa in his commentary on the Shalapatha Brāhmaṇa (ii. 1. 2. 8) * observes that he, the&#xA;*पुणा तस्य शिरविण्छेद&amp;quot;&amp;ldquo;इषुः शिरवेत्युभयमंतरिक्षमुरप्लुत्व नक्षत्रात्मना afin ta I Sāyaṇa&amp;rsquo;s commentary on Shat, &amp;lsquo;3r. ii. 1. 2. 8.&#xA;V.]&#xA;THE ANTELOPE&amp;rsquo;S HEAD.&#xA;99&#xA;terrible form created by the gods, &amp;ldquo;cut off Prajāpati&amp;rsquo;s head by the arrow,&amp;rdquo; and &amp;quot; the arrow and the head both jumped up to the heavens and are there stationed.&amp;rdquo; The Aitareya&#xA;Brāhmaṇa (iii. 33) gives the same story and there loo Pashu man or Bhutavan is said to have pierced Prajāpati with an arrow. But it does not distinctly say whether it was the head or the body that was pierced by him though in the śatapatha Brahmaña Mr̥gaśiras is described as the head of Prajā pati. The tradition of piercing the head does not, however, occur in this form in the R̥gveda, though in Rig. x. 61. 5.7 this story of Prajāpati is alluded to. But in many places where lodra is mentioned as killing Vr̥itra we are told that he cut off the head of his enemy (i. 02. 10; iv. :8. 9; viii. 6. 7) and in Rig. v. 34.% and viii. 93. 14, Indra&amp;rsquo;s enemy is described as appearing in the form of an antelope. This shows that the R̥gveda indirectly speaks of an antelope&amp;rsquo;s head having been cut off by Indra, and it may justify us in holdiug that Rudra did the same. The tradition is preserved even in the Greek mythology which tells us that Apollo, indignant at her sister&amp;rsquo;s affections for Orion, made her hit, with an arrow, a mark in the distant sea, which turned out to be the Orion&amp;rsquo;s head. In the heavens we must therefore look for the &amp;ldquo;cut off&amp;rdquo; head of Mpiga with the arrow pierced in it. There are other circumstances which point to the conclusion. Sanskrit writers have described a small group of stars in Mr̥gaśiras called lovakās. Amarasinha tells us thal they are &amp;ldquo;on che top of Mr̥gaśiras. Now if Mr̥gaśiras&#xA;* See Smith&amp;rsquo;s Dictionary of Classical Mythology. Ov. Fast, v,537.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>09 ORION AND HIS BELT</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/hindu/articles/tilak-orion/09_ORION_AND_HIS_BELT/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/hindu/articles/tilak-orion/09_ORION_AND_HIS_BELT/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;contents&#34;&gt;Contents&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;āgrahāyaṇa = Āgrayaṇa in the older works.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Probable derivation of hayana&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The Āgrayaṇa sacrifices. Their number and nature.&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Performed every half-year in Vasanta and śarad&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Greek legends of Orion - Their similarity to Vedic legends&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;German traditions and festivities&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Stag and hind&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Twelve nights&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Dog days&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;All of which indicate the commencement of the year in Orion&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Dr. Kuhn&amp;rsquo;s explanation is insufficient.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The usual adjuncts of Orion - His belt, staff and lion&amp;rsquo;s skin&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The aivyaonghana of Haoma in thc Avesta&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The yajñopavīta of the Brāhmaṇa&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Their sacred character probably borrowed from the belt of Orion or Yajña&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Use of mekhala, ajina and danḍa in the Upanayana ceremony.&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Probably in imitation of the costume of Orion or Prajāpati, the first of the Brāhmaṇs&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Derivation of Orion from Āgrayaṇa&#xA;-Its probability&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Phonetic difficulties&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Conclusion.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;intro&#34;&gt;Intro&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In the last chapter I have quoted an observation of Plutarch that the Greeks gave their own name to the constellation of Orion, and have there discussed some Vedic legends which corroborate Plutarch&amp;rsquo;s remarks and indicate that the vernal equinox was in Orion at that time. In the present chapter I mean to examine other legends which go to shew that the constellation of Orion was known and figured before the Greeks, the Parsis, and the Indians separated from their common home, and that the legends or the traditions so preserved, and perhaps the name of the constellation, can be naturally and easily explained only on the supposition that the vernal equinox was then near the asterism of Mr̥gaśiras.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>10 RIBHUS AND VRISHAKAPI</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/hindu/articles/tilak-orion/10_RBHUS_AND_VRSHAKAPI/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/hindu/articles/tilak-orion/10_RBHUS_AND_VRSHAKAPI/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;contents&#34;&gt;Contents&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Knowledge of astronomy in Vedic times&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The seasons and the year&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The ayanas&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The zodiacal belt or r̥ta&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Observation of a total eclipse of the sun in the R̥gveda&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Knowledge of the planets Shukra and Manthin&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Venus and Vena, Shukra and Kupris&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The legend of the r̥bhus&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Their identification with the r̥tus or the seasons of the year&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Their sleep or rest in Agohya&amp;rsquo;s (sun&amp;rsquo;s) house for 12 intercalary days&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;said to be awakened by dog (Rig. 1. 161. 13) at the end of the year&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Indicates the commencement of the year with the dog-star&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Nature and character of Vr̥ṣākapi&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;His identification with the sun at the autumnal equinox&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The hymn of Vr̥ṣākapi in the R̥gveda x. 80&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Its Meaning discussed verse by verse&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Cessation and commencement of sacrifices on the appearance and disappearance of Vr̥ṣākapi in the form of a Mr̥ga&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Indrāṇī cuts off his head and sets a dog at his ear&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Orion (Mr̥gaśiras) and Canis&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Meaning of nedīyas in the Vedic literature.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;When Vr̥ṣākapi enters the house of indra, his Mr̥ga becomes invisible (Rig *. 86.22.)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Points to the vernal equinox in Orion or Mr̥gam&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Leading incidents in the story stated and explained.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;knowledge-of-astronomy-in-vedic-times&#34;&gt;Knowledge of astronomy in Vedic times&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It is said that we cannot suppose that the Vedic bards were acquainted even with the simplest motions of heavenly bodies. The statement, however, is too general and vague to be criticised and examined. If it is intended to be understood in the sense that the complex machinery of observation which the modern astronomers possess and the results which they have obtained thereby were unknown in early days, then I think there cannot be two opinions on that point. But if by it is meant that the Vedic poets were ignorant of everything except the sun and the dawn, ignorant of the Nakṣatras, ignorant of month, ayanas, years and so on, then there is no authority or support for such a supposition in the R̥gveda.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>11 CONCLUSION</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/hindu/articles/tilak-orion/11_CONCLUSION/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/hindu/articles/tilak-orion/11_CONCLUSION/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Results of previous cbapters-Winter solstice in Phalguna and&#xA;Magha-Successive year.beginoings in old times stared and explaioed-lhe second traditional year.begioning in the Tait. tirtya Saphitd-Winter solstice in Chaitra and vernal equinox in Pusarvasu-Vedic traditions corroborating the same-The commencement of the sacrifice with Aditi, the presiding deity of Punarvasū-The Abhijit day. The asteriemal Prajā pati with Chitra for his head-THB CONCLUSIONS-Periods of ancient Vedic literature stated and described - The Pre-Orion Period, 6000. 4000 B.C. The Orion Period, 4000-2500 B. C. The Krittika Period, 2500&amp;ndash;1400 B. C.-Pre Buddistic Period, 1400-500 B. C.&#xA;Not inconsistent with the results of Comparative Philology or Mythology-Rate of the precession of the equinoxes-Cor. rectly determined by the Hindus.Cootinuous record of the different positicns of the equinoxes in Sankrit literature-Tradi. tions based upon the same-Prajāpati, Rohiṇi and Rudra - Mean. ipg of Rohiṇi&amp;ndash;The Kr̥ttikds in the Taittirīya Saobita and Vedanga Jyotiṣa-The equinox in Ashvini in later works,-Story of&#xA;Vishvamitra- Notices of the recession of the rainy season from&#xA;· Bhādrapada to Jyeshtbu Conclusions shown to be consistent with the traditions regarding the antiquity of Zoroaster and the Vedas.&#xA;We have thus traced back one of the traditions about the old beginnings of the year, mentioned in the Taittirīya Sanhitt, to the oldest of the Vedic works, and what is still more important, shown that the Vedic traditions are in&#xA;this Tespect completely corroborated by the oldest records and traditions of the other two sections of the Aryan race the Parsis and the Greeks. The traditions of each nation taken singly may not be conclusive, but when, putting all these together, and interpreting onc set in the light of another, we find that directly or indirectly all point to the same conclusion, their cumulative effect cannot but be&#xA;CHAPTER VIII.)&#xA;CONCLUSION,&#xA;199&#xA;conclusive. Scholars have already discovered the similarity between the traditions of the three nations, but without any clue to the period when all the Aryas lived together, it was impossible to reduce all these traditions into a harmonious whole. The traditions of Orion, and especially its position at the beginning of the equinoctial year, do, however, supply such a clue, and with its help the mystery about the oldest periods of Aryan civilization is consider ably cleared up. Thus if Orion is now no longer a hunter of unknown parentage, we need not also indulge in uncer tain speculations about the foamy weapon with which Indra killed his enemy, or how the four-eyed dogs came to be stationed at the Chinvat Bridge, or why the r̥bhus are said to be awakened by a dog at the end of the year.&#xA;Astronomically the matter is as simple as it could be. All our measurements of time are directly based upon the changes in the positions of heavenly bodies. But there is no measurement of time, at present determined, which is longer than the period during which the equinoxes complete their revolution in the ecliptic. It is, therefore, the best measurement of time for determining the periods of anti quity, only if we have reliable records about the position of heavenly bodies in early days. Fortunately, such records of the time, when the Hellenic, the Iranian and the Indian Aryans lived tegether, have been preserved for us in the R̥gveda, and with the help of the Greek and Parsi traditions we can now uecipher these records inscribed on the specially cultivated memory of the Indian Aryans. Commencing with the passages in the Taittirīya Sanhits and the Brāhmaṇas, which declare that the Phalguni full. moon was once the new.year&amp;rsquo;s night, we found that Mriga&#xA;shiras was designated by a name which, if rightly inter preted, showed that the vergal equinox coincided with that&#xA;anterium in old times. This was, 80 to speak, a sort of&#xA;· corroborative evidence of the truth of the statement in the&#xA;Taittirīya Sanbita. A reference to the figure will show at a glance that if the sun be at the winter solstice on the Phalguni full moon day, the moon to be full must be diametrically opposite to the sun and also near Phalguni. Uttara Phalgupi will thus be at the summer solstice and the verbal equinox will coincide with Mr̥gaśiras. With the sol stice in Māgha, the equinox will be in the Kr̥ttikās ; while when the Uttarāyaṇa begins in Pausha the equinox is in Ashvini. Ashvint and Pauṣa, Kr̥ttikās and Māgha, and Mr̥gaśiras and Phālguna are thus the correlative pairs of successive year.beginnings depending entirely upon the pre cession of the equinoxes; and the facts, statements, texts and legends discussed in the previous chapters supply us with reliable evidence, direct and indirect, of the existence of all these year.beginnings in the various periods of Aryan civili. zation. It has been further shown that not only the traditions, but also the primitive calendar of the Parsis bears out the conclusions we have deduced from the Vedic works.&#xA;We have so far considered only one of the traditional year beginnings recorded in the Taittirīya Saphita, the Phalguni sull-moon. But it may be asked how we interpret the other mentioned along with it, and almost in the same words. Apalogy al once suggests that we should interpret il in the same way as we have iolerpreted the first. With the Phalguni full-moon, at the winter colstice the verpal equinox was in Mr̥gaśiras; 50 with the Onitra full-moon at the solstice the vergal equinox would be in Punarvasa.&#xA;201&#xA;VIIL)&#xA;CONCLUSION.&#xA;Let us, therefore, see if we have evidence in the Vedic literature in support of such an ia terpretation. It may be observed that we are here entering upon the remotest period of antiquity, when the year was probably first determined with some approach to accuracy; and even in the Vedas there is hardly anything beyond vague traditions about this period, while the Grecks and the Parsis have not, it appears, preserved even these.&#xA;There is no express passage which states that Puaarvasu was ever the first of the Nakṣatras, nor have we in this case a synonym like āgrahāyaṇa, or Orion, wherein we might discover similar traditions. There are, however, some indications about the oldest position of Punarvasū preserved in the sacrificial literature. The presiding deity of Puparyasa is Aditi, and we are told in the Aitareya Brāhmaṇa i. 7, and the Taittirīya Saṁhitā vi. 1, 8.1, that Aditi has been blessed with a boon that all sacrifices must commence and end with her. The story begins with the stateaent that the Sacrifice (the mysterious sacrificial personage) went away from the gods. The gods were then unable to perform any further ceremonies, and did not know where it (the sacrifice) had gone to ; and it was Aditi that helped them, in this state, to find oul the proper commencement of the sacrifices. This clearly means, if it can mean anything, that before this time sacrifices were performed at random, but it was at this time resolved and fixed to commence them from Aditi. Aditi was thus the oldest and the first commencement of the sacrifice or the year. Io the Vājasaneyi saṁhitā 4. 19 Aditi is said to&#xA;• Alt. Br, i. 7. A similar tradition about Orion la narrated in Oreak raytholoty, uit is stated tbat having lost his sight he follow. ed a guide to the cast in search of the sun and there, by, exposing ble tace to the rising sua, his sight was restored.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>12 APPENDIX</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/hindu/articles/tilak-orion/12_APPENDIX/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/observation/history/hindu/articles/tilak-orion/12_APPENDIX/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;agrayana-and-orion&#34;&gt;Agrayana and Orion.&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I have already stated in brief my reasons for provisiopally identifying Sk. Agrayana with Gk. Orion, and here I wish to examine the point more fully, not because my case rests upon it, bnt simply with a view to indicate the real nature of the objections that may be urged against the proposed identification. If philologists are still inclined to hold that the identification is not even probable, we shall have to look for some other Aryan derivation, as the similarity of the Eastern and Western traditions of Orion is, in my opioion, too strong to be accidental.&#xA;Agrayana is evidently derived from agra and ayana, Of these ayana, which is derived from i, to go, may be represent ed by ion in Greek ; cf. Sk. @yus, Gk, aiön Sk. comparative termination (nom. sin.) iyān Gk. ion; Sk. termination dyana, as in Gargyayana, Gk iön, as in Kronion, &amp;rsquo;the descen dant of Kronos&amp;rsquo;. The initial ā in Sk. Agrayana may also become in Greek; as in Sk. ashayana, Gk õkeanos; Sk. dshu Gk, ökus, Sanskrit Ägrayana inay therefore be represent. ed by Ogriön in Greck, and we have now to see if g may be dropped before and Ogrion can be changed into Orion. It is a general phonetic rule in Teutonic languages that a gutteral may disappear before a liquid, whether initially or medially ; cf. Ger, nagel, Eng. nail ; hagel and hail; regen and rain; Sk, kravis, O. H. G. rõ. Prof. Max Mūller has extended the application of this rule 10 Latin and Greek, and Latin and French in his Lectures on the Science of Language, Vol. II., p. 309. He compares Lalin paganus with French paien, Gk, lāchne&amp;rsquo; With Lat, lāna; and points 222&#xA;APPENDIX.&#xA;out that on the same principle luman stands for lucmen, examen for exagmen, Hamma for fagma. K. Brugmann (Oom. Gr. I., 9023.) would derive 0, Ir. dr, Cymr, aer from &amp;ldquo;agro on the same principle. This shows that Sk. agra may be easily represented by ār in Teutonic languages. We may account for the change in two ways. We may cither suppose that the final gutteral of a root is sometimes dropped before terminations begioning with a liquid and thus put luc-men = lu-men, fulg-men-ful-men, Ang-mens Aa-men, ag-men-d-men, ag-11 - dura ( with compensation vowel lengthening; Bopp derives Sk, roman, a hair from ruh-man growing, on the same principle); or we may suppose that the change is in accordance with general phonetic rule which sanctions the omission of a gutteral before a liquid in such cases. But whichsoever explanation we adopt, there no question as to the change itself, It must pot, however, be supposed the rule is an uninflexible one, and that a gutteral must always be dropped before a liquid; for we find that gutteral in such cases is often cither retained or labialised. cf. Sk. gravan, O. Ir. broo, bro, (gen. broon), Cymr, breuan; Sk. spindmi, Q. Ir. gair. The proper rule to deduce from these instances would therefore be, thal gr in Sanskrit may be represented by gr, br or r in Teutonic languages, and that all the three changes are possible.&#xA;Can we pot extend the rule to Greek and Sanskrit? is the next question we have to coosider. I do not mean to deny that there are phunetic rules which are not univer. sally applicable to all languages. But the present rule can be easily shewn not to belong to this clāss. Prof. Max Māller has already extended it to Greek and Latin and&#xA;APPENDIX.&#xA;Vararuchi, in his Prakrita Prakasha II. 2, lays down that &amp;amp; in ga may be medially dropped as between Sanskrit and Prakrit, 6. 8. Sk. sagara, Pk. sa-ara; Sk. nagara, Pk. na-ar, eventually corrupted into nara, as in Jun-nara and other names of cities. This is, in fact, the same rule which, when applied to Teutonic languages, accounts for the change of segel into sail, nagel into nail and so on. Comparison of Avestic tigra with Mod. Per. tir shews that a similar change may also take place between those languages. We may, therefore, fairly say that the rule about the omission of gutteral before a liquid obtains not only in Teutonic langa. ages, but also between Greek and Latio, Latin and French Sanskrit and Old Irish, Sanskrit and Prakrit, and Avestir. and Modera Persian. In the face of these facts it would, I think, be uaduly restricting the applicability of the phonetic rule if we refuse to apply it to Sanskrit and Greek. There is at any rate no a priori improbability in expecting that a similar change may take place as between Greek and Sanskrit. Let Us Dow see if there are any instances as between Greek and Sanskrit to support such a conclusion.&#xA;Prof. Benfey compares Sk. grāvan with Gk. laas (Lat. lapis); and Sk. ghrāno with Gk, nis, rinos. If this comparison is correct, here at least we have two instancos where a gutteral before r in Sanskrit is lost in Greek. It is some. times labialised, as in Sk. krinami, Gk, priami ; Sk guru, Gk, barus ; and sometimes retained as it is, as in Sk, kralu, Gk, kratus ; Sk, gras, Gk, grao, to swallow. From these instances we may therefore infer that as belween Greek and Sanskrit, the initial cutleral in kr or gr in Sanskrit may be either retained as it is, or labialised or dropped in&#xA;rannan nama polim mhich holds good, as shown above,&#xA;224&#xA;APPENDIX&#xA;in Teutonic languages. It may be noticed here ihal while grdvan becomes laos in Greek, it is broon in Old Irish, that is, while the initial g of a Sanskrit word is labialised in Old Irish it is.dropped in Greek. This shews that the initial kr or gr in Sanskrit may be differently represented in different languages. Sanskrit kṣimis, Lat, vermis, Gk, elmis, and Sk. Rlipta, Avestic kerepta, Gk, raptos, may, I think, also be regard. ed as further illustrations of the same rule. I know that the connection between the words last quoted is still considered doubtful, but that is because the rule about the omission of a guiteral before a liquid, as between Greek and Sanskrit, is not yet recognised by scholars. If the examples I have given at the beginning of this paragraph are, however, sufficient to justify us in applying the rule to Greek and Sanskrit, the instances last cited may be taken as further supporting the same view.&#xA;With these instances before us, it would be unreasonable to deny that the three possible changes of kr and gr, which obtain in Teutonic languages, do not take place as between Greek and Sanskrit, at least initially; and if these changes take place initially, a nalogy at once suggests that they would also take place medially. At any rate there is no reason why they should not. It may be urged that a comparison of Sk, chakra with Gk, kuklos shews that a medial kr is retained as it is. But as pointed out above the argument is not conclusive. There may be cases where kr is retained as it is. But we have seen that by the side of such cases, instances can be quoted where it&amp;rsquo; is changed to pr or r initially; and we may expect the same Lhreefold possible change medially. It is admitted that labiali. sation takes place medially; and we have therefore to see if there are any instances where a gutteral is dropped before a liamid io tome body of word. K. Brmamann tells us that&#xA;APPENDIX.&#xA;225&#xA;at one period gn and gm came to be represented by n and m in Greek; cf. gignomai and ginomai, stugnos and stunos. Now this change in the budy of a word is exactly similar to that of agnien inlo amen, and is evidently due to the same rule, which accounts for the latter change. Similarly Gk. anoos may be compared with Sk. ajna, aad Gk. arinos 10 Sk. aghrana. But I do not lay much stress on these inasmuch as these words may be supposed to have been derived by the addition of the prefix alpha to the already existing Greek forms, and not directly obtained from Sanskrit ajna and aghrāna. The chaoge of gignonai into ginomai or of gignosko into ginosko cannot, however, be so accounted for, and if so before n is dropped in the body of a word, there is no reason why it should not be dropped before r on the analogy of the phonetic rule given above. Works oa philology do not give any more instances of such changes, but as observed above, the attention of scholars does not appear to have been direct. ed to this point. Otherwise I do not think it was difficult to discover the similarity between Gk. turos and Sk. takra. Takra is derived from tanch (*teng) lo coatract, to coagulate or curdle, and according to Fick the root is Iado Germanic. It is an old Vedic root, and we have such expressions as dadhna dlanakti coagulates (milk) with curds&amp;rsquo; in the Taittirīya saṁhitā II. 5. 3.8. Takra therefore literally means &amp;lsquo;curdled milk&amp;rsquo; and not curds mixed with water &amp;lsquo;as the word is understood in modera Sanskrit. Now, if we suppose that the rule, which saactions the omission of g or k before y or m in other languages, also holds good as between Greek and Sanskrit, not only initially (as in grivan aad laos) but also medially, as in ginomai and ginomai, Sk takra may be casily identified with Gk, duros meaning &amp;ldquo;cheese&amp;rsquo;. Takra may&#xA;hanne lova, amell ob man maono mariniramo in na rin anim&#xA;a le&#xA;226&#xA;APPENDIX.&#xA;Turas is an old Greek word used in the Odyssey, and it ha not yet been explained by anything in Iado-Germanic. D Schrader therefore records a suggestion that it should b derived from Turko Tataric turak. But if Sanskrit sāra an sarpis are found in Greek oros (whey) and elphos (bulter) is not reasonable to suppose that turos alone was borrowe from a pop-Aryan source. Takra in modern Sanskrit meat&#xA;curds mixed with water and churned&amp;rsquo; and perhaps it may b contended that we cannot identify it with furos, which mean *cheese, I have, however, shewn that takra etymologicall means &amp;lsquo;curdled milk&amp;rsquo; and aot &amp;lsquo;curds dissolved in water&amp;rsquo; whic is evideatly its secondary meaning. Besides when we see the sara which in Sanskrit denotes &amp;lsquo;curdled milk,&amp;rsquo; has becom oros - whey in Greek, and serum in Latin, there is nothin unusual if we find takra and turos used in slightly differen seases in the two languages. I have already suggested in th body of the essay that we may ideatify Sk. Shukra with Gk Kupris. Chakra kuklos, Shukra. Kupris, and takra=turos may thus be taken to illustrate the application of the rul above discussed, regarding the three-fold change of kr or g to Greek and Sanskrit medially; and instances have bee already quoted to show that the rule holds good initially a between Greek and Sanskrit. We may therefore conclude tha the change of signomai into ginomai is not a solitary instance and that as a general rule &amp;amp; may be dropped, labialised o retained before a liquid as between Greek and Sanskrit whethe at the beginning or in the body of a word. We might eve discover further instances of the applicability of this rule for, if takra is thus correctly identified with turos, we may, oi the same principle, identify 8k, agra with Gk. oros, meanin, top summit. It was impossible to represcot Sanskrit agri frumemmomnandha mamlama mo laman 1 million con amor&#xA;APPENDIX.&#xA;227&#xA;sented by agros in Greek as the latter word corresponded to Sk, ajra, a field ; nor can agra be changed to akris which represented Sk. ashri. Sanskrit agra, therefore, naturally came to be represented by oros. Oros, meaning top or sum. mit, has not yet been satisfactorily derived in any other way.&#xA;It will be seen from the above that we have sufficient grounds to hold that the rule about the omission of a gutteral before a liquid, whether initially or medially, applies to Greek and Sanskrit in the same way as it does to other languages; and if so, Sk. Agrayana can be represented by Orion in Greek.&#xA;I have already quoled Brugmann to show that *agra becomes ār or aer in Teutonic languages. Now further com paring Lat. integri, integer with Fr. entier ; Gk. dakru, Goth. tagr with Eng. tear; pagan with paien and regen with rain, we are led to infer that where k org is dropped before y or a liquid we may expect two contiguous vowels, probably because this gr is at first optionally altered into ger or gar. We can now understand why Orion was sometimes spelt as Oarion; and the existence of this double form cooörms, in my opinion, the derivation above suggested. As for union alone we might derive it from oros, limit, or āra, spring, and ion, going thus, giving the same meaniog, viz., the lirit of the beginning of the year or spring, as Agrayana in Sanskrit. But this does not account for the double form Orion and Qarion&amp;ndash;unless the latter be taken for a poetic or a dialectic variation of Orion. I therefore prefer to derive the word from Sanskrit Agrayana.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
