<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;03 The Solar Calendar on ज्योतिषे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar/03_The_Solar_Calendar/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;03 The Solar Calendar on ज्योतिषे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar/03_The_Solar_Calendar/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 ANCIENT EGYPT</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar/03_The_Solar_Calendar/01_ANCIENT_EGYPT/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar/03_The_Solar_Calendar/01_ANCIENT_EGYPT/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;lunar-calendar&#34;&gt;Lunar calendar&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Like other nations of antiquity the early Egyptians had a year of &lt;strong&gt;360 days divided into 12 months, each of 30 days&lt;/strong&gt;; but they found very early from the recurrence of the Nile flood, that the seasonal year consisted approximately of 365 days, and that a month or lunation (period from one new-moon to another) was nearly 29.4 days (real length 29.531 days). But they had already framed a calendar on the 30-day month, and 360-day year, which had received religious sanction. Hence arose the first necessity for calendar reform recorded in ancient history. To persuade the people to agree to this reform their priests invented the following myth :&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>02 OTHER ANCIENT NATIONS</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar/03_The_Solar_Calendar/02_OTHER_ANCIENT_NATIONS/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar/03_The_Solar_Calendar/02_OTHER_ANCIENT_NATIONS/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The story of the calendar in Egypt has been given in full, because the ancient Egyptians evolved a very simple and convenient calendar which, as mentioned before, would have been almost perfect (provided the year was taken to consist of 365 1/4 days instead of 365 days). This was rendered possible by their bold initiative of discarding the moon as a time-marker. But people in the remaining parts of the civilized world (e.g., in Babylon, Greece, India and China) in ancient and moderm times, retained the moon and preferred the more complex luni-solar calendars described in Chap. III. This was rather fortunate, for if their rulers had adopted the Egyptian calendar, the &lt;strong&gt;priest astronomers of ancient nations&lt;/strong&gt;, particularly of Babylon, &lt;strong&gt;would never have taken to observation of the sun, the moon, and the planets, and tried to evolve mathematical formulae for predicting&lt;/strong&gt; their positions amongst stars in advance (the Ephemerides), which form the basis on which our astronomical knowledge has been built up; for the Egyptian calendar was evolved simply from results of experiences extending over centuries, and required almost no astronomical sense, or observations either of the sun, the moon and stars, except the heliacal rising of Sirius. It was simple and convenient, but like many perfect things, it killed intellectual curiosity.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>03 THE IRANIAN CALENDAR</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar/03_The_Solar_Calendar/03_THE_IRANIAN_CALENDAR/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar/03_The_Solar_Calendar/03_THE_IRANIAN_CALENDAR/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The great Iranian conqueror Darius (520 B. C.), whose empire comprised Egypt, Mesopotamia, Syria and Asia Minor, besides his native country of Iran, certainly came into contact with the diverse calendars of older civilizations, but he appears to have &lt;strong&gt;preferred the Egyptian calendar&lt;/strong&gt; to the more complex Babylonian calendar, and introduced it in his vast empire.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;But the astronomers of Darius made correction of the deficit of 1 day of the year in another way. They had all years of 365 days, but used an &lt;strong&gt;interaclary month of 30 days in a cycle of 120 years&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>04 THE FRENCH REVOLUTION CALENDAR</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar/03_The_Solar_Calendar/04_THE_FRENCH_REVOLUTION_CALENDAR/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar/03_The_Solar_Calendar/04_THE_FRENCH_REVOLUTION_CALENDAR/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Egyptian calendar attracted the notice of the calendar committee of the French Revolutionary Government (1789-1795) who wanted to &lt;strong&gt;replace Religion by Reason&lt;/strong&gt;. The committee consisted, amongst others, the great mathematicians &lt;strong&gt;Laplace and Lagrange&lt;/strong&gt; and the poet d&amp;rsquo;Eglantine. Laplace proposed that the year 1250 A.D., when according to his calculations the equinoctial line was perpendicular to the apse line +++(=major axis)+++ of the Earth&amp;rsquo;s orbit should be taken the starting point of the French Revolution Era in place of a hypothetical year of Christ&amp;rsquo;s birth. But the calendar committee did not agree with him but started the era of the glorious French revolution, with the autumnal equinox day of 1792 A.D., as this was nearest in date to the outbreak of the revolution. Sentiment proved stronger than cold scientific reasoning.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>05 THE ROMAN CALENDAR</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar/03_The_Solar_Calendar/05_ROMAN/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar/03_The_Solar_Calendar/05_ROMAN/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;(The Christian Calendar) What is now known as the Christian calendar, and used all over the world for civil purposes, had originally nothing to do with Christianity. It was, according to one view, originally the calendar of semi-savage tribes of Northern Europe, who started their year sometime before the &lt;strong&gt;beginning of Spring (March 1 to 25) and had only ten months of 304 days ending about the time of winter solstice (December 25)&lt;/strong&gt;, the remaining &lt;strong&gt;61 days&lt;/strong&gt; forming a period of &lt;strong&gt;hybernation&lt;/strong&gt; when no work could be done due to the onset of winter, and were not counted at all. The city state of Rome also had originally this calendar, but &lt;strong&gt;several corrections&lt;/strong&gt; were made by the Roman Governments at different epochs and the final shape was given to it by Julius Caesar in 46 B.C.; the calendar so revised is known as the Julian calendar.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>06 THE GREGORIAN CALENDAR</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar/03_The_Solar_Calendar/06_THE_GREGORIAN_CALENDAR/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar/03_The_Solar_Calendar/06_THE_GREGORIAN_CALENDAR/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Julian year of 365.25 days was longer than the true year of 365.2422 by .0078 days, so the winter solstice day which fell on December 21 in 323 A.D., fell back by 10 days in 1582 A.D. and the Christmas day appeared to be losing all connections with the winter solstice. Similar discrepancy was also noticed in connection with the observance of the Easter.*&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;* &lt;strong&gt;Easter&lt;/strong&gt;, the most joyous of the Christian festivals, is observed annually throughout Christendom in commemoration of the resurrection of Jesus Christ, on the &lt;strong&gt;first Sunday after the full-moon&lt;/strong&gt; following the vernal equinox day. The last days of Christ coincided with the Passover fast of the Jews and his death fell upon the day of the feast of the Passover, on the 14th day of the month of Nisan. As the date of Easter is associated with the moon&amp;rsquo;s phases, as well as the vernal equinox day, it is a movable festival, falling anywhere between March 22 and April 25. A movement is going on for narrowing down the range of variation of the Easter day ; in 1928 the British Parliament passed the Easter Act, which contingent upon its acceptance internationally, fixed Easter day as the first Sunday after the second Saturday in April, falling between April 9 and 15. (Vide Encyclopaedia Britannica, Easter).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>07 THE WORLD CALENDAR</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar/03_The_Solar_Calendar/07_THE_WORLD_CALENDAR/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/articles/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar/03_The_Solar_Calendar/07_THE_WORLD_CALENDAR/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;drawbacks-of-gregorian-calendar&#34;&gt;Drawbacks of Gregorian calendar&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;As already stated the Gregorian calendar is a most inconvenient system of time-reckoning. The &lt;strong&gt;days of the months vary&lt;/strong&gt; from 28 to 31 ; quarters consist of 90 to 92 days; and the two half years contain 181 and 184 days. The &lt;strong&gt;week-days wander about&lt;/strong&gt; the month from year to year, so the year and month beginnings may fall on any week-day, and this causes serious inconvenience to civic and economic activities. The &lt;strong&gt;number of working days per month varies&lt;/strong&gt; from 24 to 27, which creates considerable confusion and uncertainty in economic dealings and in the preparation and analysis of statistics and accounts. The present Gregorian calendar is therefore in dire need of reform.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
