<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;मधुसूदनजी-शर्मा-ओझा on ज्योतिषे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/prakIrNam/madhusUdanajI-sharmA-ojhA/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;मधुसूदनजी-शर्मा-ओझा on ज्योतिषे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/prakIrNam/madhusUdanajI-sharmA-ojhA/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>कादम्बिनी</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/prakIrNam/madhusUdanajI-sharmA-ojhA/kAdambinI/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/kAla-mAnam/history/prakIrNam/madhusUdanajI-sharmA-ojhA/kAdambinI/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[कादम्बिनी&#x9;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ebharatisampat.in/readbook3.php?bookid=NjE0NTM4MDAxNjY0OTU1&amp;amp;pageno=MjI0MjQyNjk5NTk=&#34;&gt;EB&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;[&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;[TABLE]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;[TABLE]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;INTRODUCTION&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;No scientist had ever the time to have a close look at the Vedas, Brāhmaṇas and Upaniṣads and understand in his own way what they are all about. No existing interpretations except those of Madhusūdan Ojha (of which most scholars are unaware) will convince him simply because they have never gone deep into the basic concepts which the Aryans had on Nature and her working, which alone will enable one to build up a logical picture of their culture, rituals, concepts, habits and beliefs. Actually the interpreters broadly fall into two main categories. The first one constitutes those who refuse to question the authority of the Vedas and take for granted whatever is said in them and the supporting literature like Brāhmaṇas, Upaniṣads etc. The second type could not accept the above position and at the same time could not discover the logic in many of the statements found in the Vedas and Brāhmaṇas. They therefore came to the conclusion that many of these statements are myths or stories and have no logical or factual basis Some of the scholars belonging to the first type have tried to find some reasoning in many Vedic statements but they have in our opinion miserably failed to find convincing explanation to many of the statements simply because they could not master the entire literature and connect up the passages properly in a coherent way The physical phenomena on the earth or in the atmosphere or the astronomical phenomena in the heavens described in their own way by the Maharṣis and couched in symbolic language could not be resolved by them. The technical words occuring in large numbers in the Vedic and Brāhmaṇic passages have posed the greatest challenge to the interpreters and it is here that no two interpretations agreed, The result has been that many passages were interpreted differently by different scholars. The Vedic Gods, for example as conceived by the Vedic seers are essentially forces of Nature taking part in the creation and maintenance of the universe But the symbolic language used by them as well as the glorification of these forces have misled many interpreters who could not understand their nature correctly. The authors of the six systems of philosophy based their theories on the authority of the Vedas but their conclusions differed from each other, thereby implying that the message of the Vedas can take divergent directions. Sankara, Ramānuja and Madhvācārya interpreted the Vedas Brāhmaṇas and Upaniṣads in their own way and arrived at divergent conclusions. This manoeuverability in the interpretations in course of time led to some serious consequences. For example &lt;em&gt;Rudra&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Viṣṇu&lt;/em&gt; which represent physical forces having complimentary functions in the creative process became gods of differing importance &lt;em&gt;Rudra&lt;/em&gt; (Indra) represents Agni and &lt;em&gt;Visņu&lt;/em&gt; represents the force that constantly feeds Agni with food (Soma) and promotes the creative process (Yajña). It is unfortunate that incorrect interpretation of these have led to the division of a single society into various factions which certainly was&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
